Lara: This meeting is now being recorded.
Cole: Yeah. So, today is November 5, 2020, and I'm here with Lara [...]. So Lara, we're gonna start with the beginning of your life. Well, first of all, where'd you grow up? And who are your parents?
Lara: I grew up in Minneapolis, Minnesota. And my parents are Erica [...] and Gabriel [...]. And I have an older brother. (laughs)
Cole: What is your earliest memory of growing up?
Lara: That's a good one. I think my earliest memory is--- there are a few really, really shaky memories of being at a house that we had on Zenith and scootering down to the park. And there was like a little spot where the cars had to turn so they would slow down. And I always remember trying to, like, pick up speed to go around that turn with like all the neighborhood kids. So that's probably the earliest. I was like four.
Cole: Okay, and who were these neighborhood kids? Did you hang out with them a lot?
Lara: Yeah, I did, actually. One of them is, in a roundabout way, my best friend now. But the neighborhood kids then were my older brother, there were another similar duo across the street and a similar duo living two doors down. And that was pretty much who we hung out with for a few years there.
Cole: Yeah. Did you--- what about school? What schools did you go to, and what was that like?
Lara: So, I went to Lake Harriet Elementary, and then Lake Harriet Middle, and then I went to school at a place called Southwest [High School]. But elementary and middle school were like--- it was just the most--- it's the most private that you can get without it actually being a private school, if that makes sense? It was the whitest---
Cole: Say more about that.
Lara: Well, it was--- it was incredibly sheltered and privileged, incredibly white. And incredibly hoity toity about how amazing it was.
Cole: Hmm.
Lara: You were training little A students.
Cole: What else was--- do you remember anything from elementary school?
Lara: Yeah, I mean, I remember like, that's when my parents got divorced. So that was pretty formative in terms of how I, you know, relate to elementary school. But I remember--- I mean, it was hard. Elementary School is hard. But it was fun, and I was just a kid. I remember teachers, really good ones. That was one of the things I'm most grateful for having gone to Lake Harriet was that there are some seriously knockout teachers who really cared. Yeah, I'm grateful to have gone where I went, even though it definitely had some damaging effects. But I think that every school does.
Cole: What do you mean by damaging effects?
Lara: I'd say that it altered the way that I view the world in unproductive ways. Because it wasn't--- yeah, I think--- I think that it was a little too sheltered. I think it was a little too white, in that--- that's not the real world, and that's not the way that, you know, the United States looks, and to have a public school be that autonomous? I don't even know if you can use that word. But to have it be so of one thing was unproductive and that that's not real. And they didn't--- and no one ever talked about it. Like none of the teachers addressed it or none of--- yeah.
Cole: So during elementary school--- you talked about how your school is mostly white. Were there any Jewish kids at the school that you knew of, that you could--- that you knew of at the time?
Lara: Isaac [...] and Eva [...], (giggling) and me. (more giggling) That was pretty much it.
Cole: How do you know that they were Jewish? Did you know this back in elementary school?
Lara: I didn't know it in elementary school. I also don't think that I knew I was Jewish in elementary school. But I knew it in middle school. (laughing) And, yeah, it was--- they--- they were gone for like Rosh Hashanah, and they were--- they would be gone for Passover, and, you know, the holidays and stuff and--- and then it became, you know, in middle school, you start talking about your identity because you start to realize that you have one, which is a fun and difficult time. And so we would write poems, and I remember Isaac [...] actually did a spoken word poem about being Jewish. And I think that's probably one of the first times that I realized that, like, it was a thing? that I was also? and that it was a more complicated issue than I had realized, in terms of just identity and history, and yeah. So yeah, I think that was--- those were the Jewish kids, though, that was it. There was like, 100 kids in my grade, and there were three of us. And I was by far the worst Jew of the three.
Cole: What do you mean by worst Jew?
Lara: I joke around that I'm a bad Jew, because I didn't have like a bat mitzvah, and I'm not practicing our religion. And because probably, you know, we didn't really have a chance--- I say we because you are my brother. But we didn't really have a chance to practice any religion, because our parents came from different viewpoints. And then when they got divorced, you know, week on, week off [at different houses], it's kind of hard to--- first of all, it's hard to get into it when you're 10 and eight. And it's hard to do that when you just--- you've got two kids now, and you're with them half the time. So I imagine it wasn't on the forefront of our parents' minds to just suddenly bring religion either way into it. I also think that part of me is insecure of my Jewish identity, because our dad was actually raised Christian. And our mom was actually raised Christian, for a bunch of different complicated reasons. But I still--- I've been able to, in the past couple years, kind of take hold of that Jewish identity by just accepting it and being proud of it, which I'm incredibly proud of it, and also, now that I'm furthering my education here [in college], I am going to be a Jewish Studies minor. And I'm going to be learning Hebrew. So I'm excited to be able to reclaim some of that, that, you know, our dad and us were not able to have.
Cole: Yeah, so you didn't--- you didn't have a bat mitzvah. Did you go to synagogue at all, when you were a child? Or do anything really that was "Jewish," per se?
Lara: Yeah, we--- with our dad, I--- we went to synagogue, I think every other week for-- it felt like a couple years. I don't know if it actually was. But it was--- I thought it was a lot of fun. I love the stories. I love the atmosphere. I think the most alluring thing about religion to me is the community, which was always just so welcoming. And we did that and we still celebrate holidays every year with both our immediate family at times like Hanukkah and with our extended family for Passover. And that is one of my favorite times of the year.
Cole: Yeah, do you remember anything from going to synagogue for that amount of time?
Lara: Yeah, I remember. I remember the songs. I remember some of the stories. It's not a very well rounded understanding of the Torah, but there's definitely some things that I've picked up. I remember all the different rabbis (laughing). And the room! I remember the room so well. It was like a really gorgeous circle with a stained glass roof. And it's, yeah.
Cole: Can you---
Lara: Oh, we'd get dinner every time, at Domico and Sons [a restaurant near the synagogue].
Cole: Can you describe what it--- what it was like there? Like run me through the evening and tell me what you smell, see, hear.
Lara: So we would get there. And everyone would always be talking. And we'd probably always get there late. (laughing) And they always had food out for all of the service goers. So we would always, kind of, gorge ourselves on meals right before, and then you--- we would all like kind of file into this big room and we'd find a bench to sit on and all the bench--- benches are like, say like a light wood, and they're all glossy and pretty. And there's Torahs in the back of every bench. And then--- and then they would start--- they would usually start by walking [unintelligible] there and singing and--- and the rabbis would begin to tell stories and then there would sometimes be prayers for the sick. Which I always found very touching, and of course, because I was probably like 10 years old, I'd get bored and I'd get hungry and so would you (laughing) and we'd probably become little terrors for about the last half hour. But generally it was just chatter, and like, stories and music, and really good food. And I think that's the last thing. And challah. There would always be challah at the end, which I would look forward to immensely. Yeah, it was good. It was fun.
Cole: Yeah. And you said that you--- you always did holidays with family. When were these? What holidays were they? When did you--- do you remember them going back all the way to when you were much younger, when you were born?
Lara: I don't actually remember them. So--- yeah, so our my parents got divorced at kind of like--- I consider it primetime. So it's like, there's the first third of my life. And then they got divorced. And then there's like the middle third. And then that's separated from like, what I consider being like an actual human being with like sentient thoughts and like a personality. So the middle third is when all of this kind of started to happen. So I'd say we only started doing Passover--- it must have been a couple years after our parents divorced, I was probably 10 or 11. And then we've been doing it every year since. Except for of course, this year because of COVID.
Cole: Why--- why do you think that your parents got divorced?
Lara: Um? I don't--- Jesus. I don't know. I mean, I--- I think I know. Stuff happens. Life was hard. It was 2008, and there was a recession, and know that there were some adult troubles happening. But I think that--- it's the most generic and the most boring reason is they just stopped being in love with each other, and their partnership stopped working. And they separated for us so that we could have a stable childhood because, believe it or not, our parents being together was not a stable childhood, at the end there. And it became a lot more comfortable and stable when they got divorced.
Cole: And so you think---
Lara: ---again, but---
Cole: And you said that the divorce precipitated going to Passover and synagogue?
Lara: Yeah.
Cole: Why do you think that is?
Lara: I think that, realistically--- I think there's one of two things. I've never actually asked about this, but if I were to guess, I'd say, either one, our mom didn't want us to. Because our mom is an atheist, which is understandable. You know, you want your kids to have your religious ideals. Or more reason--- like more understandable to me, and more probable is that our parents probably had the religion discussion when they were having you. And they decided to not raise us with religion, because the religion that they were raised with, I think, was damaging in some form for both of them with their relationship with their parents. And Mom, I don't think Mom was raised religious at all, because her dad only became religious in her teenage years. So I feel like she probably had a similar experience to us. But I know that dad was raised religious. I know he was confirmed. Yeah. So I think it was probably just a mindful decision to keep religion out of it. And then once they separated, our dad reconnected with his faith and with his belief in--- and--- and probably what he had wanted to do for a while, but didn't know how to. And so we started being able to participate in it again. I also think that money was part of it, because we couldn't travel every year to go to Passover. And so once we were a little bit more financially--- once we had extra money to just fly across the country, that picked up again.
Cole: Yeah, flying across the country--- where were you and where were your--- your family members.
Lara: So me and my family were in Minnesota. And we moved there before I was born, but when my brother was born--- (giggling) you were born. And our entire extended family is from the East Coast. Some lives on the West Coast now, but at the time everyone was  living in--- in Connecticut, around Boston, or New York City when we started going back because Lizzie was there. But yeah, everyone's from the East Coast. So it was--- it was an easy commute--- easy, comparatively, for them compared to us. But, yeah.
Cole: Do you wish that you had been raised more Jewish? You said that you think it was kind of a pragmatic decision, something that just kind of was.
Lara: Yeah.
Cole: But do you wish that you were?
Lara: Yeah, I do. I do and I don't. I do and I don't, because I understand all of the reasons that I wasn't? And I think that--- I guess--- I guess more the answer is that I don't wish that I was raised more Jewish, I wish that I had sought out Judaism in my own Jewish identity before now. Because I--- once--- once I hit middle school, and I realized, kind of, what the situation was, there are things I could have done. And I should have, and I don't think that it is at any fault of our father, because I think he was probably in the same boat as me. You know, like, we didn't--- I think that as a family unit, the three of us didn't know how to seek that out, or if we even wanted to. But now that I'm like, where I am, I do wish that I had started seeking these things out more recently. And that was greatly due to a course that I took senior year, a history course called History of Africa and the Middle East, where I learned a lot about ancient religions, and I realized that I did want to know more and not more in historical sense. Only more in a--- in a religious sense as well.
Cole: That was a senior year of high school.
Lara: Yes. So that was last year. I'm a freshman [in college] now.
Cole: So in middle school, you passed the age that you would have gotten a bat mitzvah. Do you remember any of your friends getting one? Or maybe even being confirmed--- in--- in the--- the Christian sense?
Lara: Yeah. So again, those other two Jewish kids, they both got their bat and bar mitzvahs, respectively. But a ton of my friends got confirmed. A ton, a ton. My best friend Cozette  did. And I remember that. I remember--- kind of like the excitement of it, I guess? And she is religious, and she's--- was always religious. And so that was an exciting time for her, and I just remember a lot of them doing that together, I'd say? At Lake Harriet. So yeah, I do remember that.
Cole: At Lake Harriet the school?
Lara: Yeah, a lot of my classmates, there. I remember them talking about it. And then that continued--- I think they ended up actually getting confirmed--- like, I think everyone got confirmed our freshman year? But I remember being around that time that they started doing the--- their classes for it? I don't know? I don't know what they do? But they were doing something, on Wednesday nights, for like a year.
Cole: Do you ever feel---did you ever feel left out? Because of that?
Lara: I--- I don't--- I don't think it ever manifested itself into "I felt left out." I think it was just--- there were a lot of Christian kids. And then there were a lot of atheist kids, and then there was kind of just me hanging out there. So I didn't--- I didn't really feel left out, because at the time, I was able to really just blend in with atheist kids, because I didn't really know what I believed. But I knew like--- and I also think that being Jewish, there is like a certain complexity to it that there aren't--- that there isn't in most other religions that I know of, in that it is both a religion and--- and, I--- what is it? It's not a nationality? It's not an ethnicity? Is it an ethnicity? Yeah. Eh, I don't know! It's in my blood. (laughing) Like---
Cole: Yeah.
Lara: You take the DNA test, it tells you you're Jewish. That's not--- doesn't tell you you're Christian. It's like a slightly different thing. So I was--- (laughing) I knew I was Jewish without needing to be religiously Jewish. So I think that there's like, a lot of different kinds of Jewish person in a way that other things can't have that same complexity.
Cole: Yeah, let's talk about that. You--- do you identify as religiously Jewish now?
Lara: I do. I do, and I think that that's something that I need to explore, to be able to be confident in? But I don't feel like I need to explore anything to be confident in my heritage or being Jewish.
Cole: What do you mean by that?
Lara: I mean, that, like we are Jewish in the way that we are Italian, and we are Jewish in the way that we are Scottish, and that's just something that, like, I know, and--- and I'm comfortable with, compared to like the ton of questions that I have about being Jewish religiously, and looking into Judaism as a faith that I want to pursue. Because like one, I think, is more of an absolute truth. Like I am Jewish. Like, my grandparents are Jewish, my dad is Jewish. And then religiously, that's a lot of a gray area in terms of, I am trying to practice Judaism, but it's a bit more convoluted. It's not absolute.
Cole: Why is that? Is it just because you didn't grew up with it, and so you don't know how it works? Or are you having trouble finding Jewish communities that accept you?
Lara: I think it's a bit of a combination of both, because regardless of my heritage, for me to join a synagogue fully, and--- and I'd have to convert because our mother isn't Jewish. Unless I found like a very, I don't even know what they're called. I think they're called--- I don't. But there are some synagogues that don't care, but most of the traditional synagogues care about your mother's heritage, and our father is our Jewish line. So yeah, it's a bit of that, and then it's just a bit of I don't know how and I don't know--- yeah, I don't know how to practice Judaism, which is the thing that I'm sure I can figure out.
Cole: So even though you didn't really grow up practicing it, you still did go to holidays with your family, right? And I think you mentioned Passover being one of these in particular.
Lara: Yes.
Cole: Did you celebrate other Jewish holidays?
Lara: Yeah, we--- not all of them. Just, [because] one, there's a crap ton, and two, I think that us and Dad, we had a bit of a hard time--- it--- we would do Hanukkah, we would light the candles, we would do the prayer. And I feel like there was, at least for the first couple years, there was a lot of really weird nerves surrounding the event. I don't know if that's how you felt but it felt like we all kind of wanted to figure this out, but we didn't really know how because none of us had the building blocks for it. But I think it was a really positive thing nonetheless. You know, we're all kind of just fumbling around for some understanding of what these holidays mean and--- and how we can become more comfortable in, you know, doing the prayers in Hebrew and stuff like that, so. So it was--- it was pretty much only Passover and Hanukkah. At least those are the ones that stand out. If we did anything else, I'm blanking.
Cole: And so Hanukkah was with me and dad. Okay. What about Passover?
Lara: Oh, and Nana.
Cole: Yeah, say more about that.
Lara: (laughing) Our mom's mom--- (long pause) she is married? to a Jewish man. Are they mar--- she is common law married to a Jewish man. And she made us a me--- he made us a menorah, one time, so we did the prayers with her which was fun. Very Nana.
Cole: And she's---
Lara: Love it.
Cole: ---not Jewish.
Lara: No.
Cole: Okay.
Lara: I think she likes Judaism.
Cole: Yeah.
Lara: She's a--- she's a very spiritual person, I think. I don't know if she practices any specific religion, but she definitely believes in things like the power of positive thinking. And I know she likes, like meditation and stuff. So I think she kind of dabbles in all of it.
Cole: Yeah. So tell me about the other holiday that you--- you remember experiencing, Passover. You fly out and--- and then what happens?
Lara: We would--- it's always at our grandmother's house, which is--- I love her house and we always invite way too many people, but we wouldn't have it any other way. It's always like, a fun time to like see, as we got older, of course, the cousins, or when we were little, it was usually just the aunts and uncles and the great aunts and the great uncles and the great grandparents, and the friends of the cousins and the wives of the friends of the cousins, and, you know, it's just a really big gathering. And, I mean, Passover, in itself is just a big story, so I think that that kind of cemented itself as a representation of the faith, and it was community and food and stories and participation. It was always a really good time. Even though we were always stuck at like, a really uncomfortable part of the table because we were the kids. (chuckles)
Cole: So Passover, you said there's there's food. Was there special food? I mean---
Lara: Yeah.
Cole: What--- what types of things do you remember?
Lara: Well, there are symbolic foods that you use with the reading. During the Seder, it's the better herbs in the salt water, and the charoset, and--- what's that stuff? It's like--- it's not spicy, but it's like spicy.
Cole: The maror? The horseradish?
Lara: The horseradish. And then we always have brisket. Oh, I remember, we would go to Passover at our great grandparents before it got moved to their daughter--- their daughter's house. That was fun. In the townhome. That was probably my first memory of a religious experience, was--- that was a long time ago. Must've been like 10?
Cole: What do you remember about that?
Lara: I remember her house. I remember, the way that you would walk in and the kitchen would be on the right, and there would be like a little living room on the left. And it was kind of like a split level, so you'd keep going down like little steps. And I remember the brisket in an old crock pot. And I remember you and me finding the matzah, from G Grandpa. Yeah. And it was--- I had no clue what was going on. I was just excited to be there. We were the only kids because we were like always the only kids. I don't think Sasha and Claire were there. So we definitely were the only kids. Yeah, that was fun. I forgot about that. Geez.
Cole: Okay, so let's talk about high school.
Lara: (sarcastically) Everyone's favorite time.
Cole: What do you mean?
Lara: Everyone just jokes round. Everyone either thinks that high school is the worst thing that ever happened or like the best.
Cole: Which camp do you fall into?
Lara: I don't know. I hope it wasn't the best. If it was, that's pretty sad. For me. (laughing)
Cole: So talk to me about high school. Where'd you go?
Lara: I went to Southwest High School in Minneapolis, Minnesota. All four years. I was there for a bit of a tumultuous period in the school's history with a bunch of changing administration. And COVID, senior year. I liked it. It was a good school. It was a really good public school. Again, we're very privileged. I was very privileged in the schools that I got to go to. And the staff were usually amazing. And supportive.
Cole: So you say you were--- you felt very privileged? Did it feel like elementary school? You talked about how that was super white, it had a damaging effect because of it.
Lara: Yeah, it definitely wasn't. It was still, I think, the whitest high school in our district, but it definitely was a bit--- it was a bit--- it was a lot more diversified from middle school. And, yeah, I think--- I think that was great. I think that was a good step in many that--- I have a lot of opinions about the Minneapolis public school system in terms of the way that they separate areas of the city. Just so off topic, but I think it was a-- it was--- yeah, it was good. More to be done, but good.
Cole: You say it was really diverse. What--- what were the other groups of people there?
Lara: There are--- well there was African American, I think that the majority's--- forgive me if I'm wrong, but I think the majority's were White, African American and then African, from like Somalia. And those were--- and then of course there were other--- other groups as well. But I think that those are--- if you look at Minneapolis, those are the highest--- the majority minorities, of people.
Cole: And so, in high school you--- did these other two Jewish kids from middle school follow you there?
Lara: Yeah, they did.
Cole: Were they the only Jewish kids that you remember in high school? Or were there more that you met?
Lara: Um? I--- there must have been more. Natalie Kent! Forgot about her. She's Jewish. Yeah, there must have been more. It's just--- I don't know. People didn't--- people didn't really talk about it. And I don't think it was that--- I don't know if it was that people were avoiding it, or if it just never--- never came up. But, regardless, it wasn't like a thing that--- I mean, I talked about being Jewish. More as like an antidote--- anecdote to anything.
Cole: You talked about being Jewish when?
Lara: Usually would be like--- usually, it would be like someone would say like, "Oh, you know, like from the Bible" and I'd be like, I'm Jewish. I don't know the Bible, [unintelligible] the Torah, but you don't need to know that. Yeah, so it was usually just like, in a comedic way, if that even counts as an actual type of joke, but--- I had some kids tell me I killed Jesus once, that was fun.
Cole: Talk about that. Who were these kids? And why did that happen?
Lara: Well, it happened a few times, which I thought was hilarious. There was this one kid who was like, very Christian. Like very, and he--- we dro--- we were in choir and I was joking around because we were sinigng a song that I knew from synagogue, in choir. And I was like, Oh, I know this one, I'm Jewish. And he like told me I killed Jesus. And then there was another time in math class when a kid was like, "Lara, you killed Jesus." And I was like, Oh, really? I must be the best at aging ever. I look amazing. Yeah, it was very--- it was just kind of ridiculous, but no big deal.
Cole: Did they say it jokingly?
Lara: Um, yeeee--- one kid didn't. The first kid did not. He meant it. I killed Jesus. But the second kid, he was just honestly, a massive pain in the butt. And I was pretty tired of him by senior year. So I didn't really care. And he was joking, because he thought it was funny.
Cole: Did you think it was funny either of these times?
Lara: No, not really. I don't really get the--- I mean, like, that's the oldest--- it's the oldest one in the book, like the Jews killed Jesus. Like it is--- like, get some new material. (chuckles)
Cole: Okay. So you--- you said you were in choir in high school? How was that?
Lara: I loved choir. I loved it. I did choir in middle school. Mostly just so that I could quit playing the violin, because I hated the violin. But then I realized that I absolutely adored it [choir]. And then, I did it all four years in high school, pretty competitively. Yeah, and I--- one of my favorite things I did in high school. And though-- and the--- I'd say, like, of all of the extracurriculars that I participated in, choir was the longest because I, you know, I played volleyball, and then I stopped, and I did theater. But choir was the constant for me.
Cole: Yeah. What were your parents attitudes towards extracurriculars?
Lara: They were pretty adamant that we have some, and I--- I thought, for me, it always came across--- when I was younger, I probably was like, screw you guys. But I think it was a pretty supportive manner of--- it didn't really matter what we decided to do, they would at least pretend to be interested. Which I appreciate immensely. Yeah, when we were younger, it was "You have to play a sport, we don't care which one. We'll get you there, we'll be there, we'll cheer you on at your games, we'll do our best. But you got to play a sport." Which is great, because then I found volleyball and I loved playing volleyball. And then, you know, we had the same role with an instrument, like "You got to play an instrument, we don't care what." So that's really--- it was--- I played violin, which sucked. And then I---
Cole: How long did you play violin?
Lara: Three years?
Cole: And you didn't like it?
Lara: Our music teacher just blew! He was just so annoying. (laughing) And I was trash, and I hated it to practice. And I hated bringing my--- walking home with my violin. So I thought choir was the answer. And it was! And I loved it.
Cole: So Mom and Dad had us play an instrument, but they didn't necessarily force us to--- to practice or to be excellent at it.
Lara: No, no, there was--- I will say that--- they were--- they're the kind of like--- they're the kind of parents who are just so unbelievably in love with their children. But it doesn't really matter. Especially when we were little, it didn't seem to really matter if we sucked or not. Like they were going to be really excited about the entire situation. I mean, I played soccer. And I laid down during a soccer game. And our dad was literally the coach and he was still just, like, thrilled about it. Like, they were just--- they loved being parents, and of course, there were missteps but they were never the type of parents who were harsh on us for being bad at something unless they knew that--- they were--- they were, I'd--- I'd say a bit stricter on school, but that's because they knew what we were capable of. And I think that, at least with me, they pushed me in a way academically that I needed to be pushed. But they didn't in--- in sports or in theater or in choir, because I was already doing that, because it was an actual passion for me.
Cole: Talk about how they push you academically.
Lara: Well, I'd say probably more so with our dad than our mom, which I needed. I needed one parent that I could just groan about. But I think that I had--- I think I probably had a complex (smiling) in middle school going into high school because of--- not because of you, but because of you. Where it was--- it was like something that you had zero part in. Because you probably believed in me more than I did. But I definitely had it set in my mind that--- for some reason, I had it set in my mind that you were the A student and I wasn't, and that was okay. Because, I mean, I was 14 years old. And Dad kind of just was like, "Absolutely not!" Which was helpful, and I figured it out. And it was a good experience to have. And I feel like a lot of younger siblings have the same experiences I did just knowing that there's like not--- like, everything's kind of been--- it was like I thought, like, everything had been done before, so what was the point? Like, I'd seen what happens. Then I was like, You're stupid. It hasn't been done by you, like, go to school.
Cole: So you said that Dad pushed you more academically than Mom did?
Lara: I don't--- I think that Dad pushed me more academically than Mom did because Dad knew more--- I feel like of our parents, Mom was definitely the one that I went to when I needed just her to tell me like "You can do it. It doesn't matter." Like--- or like, if I, for example, had a bad score on a test, and I needed her to just say like, "Oh, who cares?" Like--- because everyone needs that. Everyone needs just like, it happened. It's over. Don't worry about it. Whereas if I had gone to Dad, and been like, Dad, I did bad on this test. He'd be like, "Lara, like, what happened?" And usually, he was right. I was not studying, or I didn't ask for extra help with the teacher, or I didn't go out of my way to get a better grade. And I think that that balance between the way that they would parent was productive for me, once I figured out that balance. Because in middle school, I was not hard on myself with school and school was not hard for me. And then in high school--- high school it was, but in a way that it was expected. And I think that when it was--- I don't know, I don't really know what it was that caused, like, the whole situation, other than I just couldn't really do it anymore? Like I--- at our middle school, we were like, really pushed hard, we were told that all of these grades are going to matter. And they didn't, ever. So I think that that kind of internalized itself into me for just like a lot of pressure. And it became kind of too much pressure for me to even get started once I got to high school, because it was like, you're staring down the next four years and, according to everyone here, the next four years you're going to decide the rest of your life, which is bogus.
Cole: Why do you think that Dad and Mom had a different attitude towards school?
Lara: Probably because of their childhood, our mom and dad went to UConn [the University of Connecticut]. Our mom and dad--- our mom, I think--- the way that she describes it to me, I'm so sorry, Mom, if this isn't true. But the way that it was described to me was she had a bit of a more easygoing attitude when it came to her high school grades. Not necessarily her education, because she is a highly educated woman, but in terms of like, her high school grades, so she--- I don't think she really felt that pressure. And I don't think she felt the need to, like, impose that pressure on us. Whereas dad was a--- probably, I'd say, like, a bit more traditionally successful in like, a very cliche way in high school. He played soccer, and he was valedictorian, and he, you know, did--- he had a lot--- he had a lot of accomplishments that are, like, you know, what you kind of hear about, when you're talking about a high school education. And then I think that--- and our mom went to UConn, and she studied for four years. She was an English major, and she got her degree. Our dad, on the other hand, did not have all of the choices that he could have been afforded for a ton of reasons that I don't even know all of them. And he ended up going to UConn and then dropping out. So he's--- and then he would go back to school, I think when we were both babies? But he, in the end, did not--- has yet to complete his college degree, his bachelor's. So I think that he was pretty adamant that working hard in high school gives you the choices that he feels he may not have had in the same way. But again, like, I don't--- I don't--- I feel like there's still so much that we don't know about our parents, because it's only now that they're able to--- that we're able to actually relate to them on a sort of adult-to-adult level. And that's just going to grow. And so maybe--- I don't know. I think--- I think it was just the dad really understood what it was like to not have a college education. He's one of the smartest people I've ever met, but to not have that on his resume. And he wanted us to be able to literally go wherever we wanted. So I think that he really pushed it so that we would get in wherever.
Cole: Was college ever not an option for you?
Lara: No, it was always an option. It was always a requirement. I guess there were a couple times my junior and senior year where both of our parents actually pushed me and kind of expressed their support if I should decide to not go to college and to pursue, because I'm a theater major, to pursue performance in a different way. Yeah, and--- and I just--- that was never really alluring to me, probably because of how important college was always made out to be. And I still think it is, for me. I think that there's different paths for everyone. But yeah, college was always expected, up until, like, junior year, and it was like--- yeah, that always surprised me. Especially Dad, being like "If you don't want to go--- like if you want to go try this out." I was like, no, I want to go to school. (laughing)
Cole: So you wanted to go to college independently?
Lara: Yeah, yeah---
Cole: Did you push yourself academically?
Lara: I did. I definitely did. I--- well, after--- you know, I talked about how, like, there was a learning curve there, but, you know, hindsight is always 2020 or whatever. I--- it's very clear to me that even if I had gotten the grades that I got freshman year, I still would have gotten into a very good college. And that is definitely due to the schools that we went to, like, 100%. If we had gone--- I think that if I had gone with my, you know, inability to pay attention, and inability to stop talking. If I had gone to a school where I wasn't given as much one-on-one support, I would have had a very different experience with education. But I did push myself. Yeah.
Cole: Do you think you were successful in high school?
Lara: Um? Yeah, I do. I do think I was successful, in my own way. I'm very proud of what I was able to do. And I think it was a really, really wonderful, like, time especially--- yeah, I think--- I think it was great. I--- I always had, like--- I'd say, like, sophomore year was the roughest, but junior and senior year, and even sophomore year was a blast. Like I--- I did a lot of things that I was really excited to be doing. And I think that was really fun. And that's very successful. Yeah.
Cole: What about your life during high school outside of academics or extracurriculars? What did you do? What would it--- what would your average day be, I guess?
Lara: I don't know. Like, I have--- I had, all throughout high school, like, a pretty tight knit group of friends. And--- and that was superduper great for me, because I think I like that kind of security and like, dependability. So an average day would probably be--- I mean, weekdays, we were all just doing homework. (laughs) And our extracurriculars, but weekends we would [have] movie nights and hang out and go for drives. It was pretty classic teenage girl drama, but it was really good. We were really close. And that was super fun. And then I also had like, different groups of friends, like theater friends and stuff.
Cole: Were any of these friends Jewish, that you know of?
Lara: Natalie Kent. That's it.
Cole: Did you relate to her on that level? Or were you totally friends for a different reason?
Lara: We were friends for a different reason. But once we both realized we were Jewish, we became like--- even--- we became even closer, I think probably because we were like, the only two Jewish people who did theater. And--- and we thought it was really funny to finally be able to joke around someone with that--- like the--- like the ridiculous, like, like, stuff that just happens that like--- because I mean, every--- every group has their own--- I don't know how to explain it. It's like, people can make Catholic jokes, and I won't get them. But for me, Natalie, if we were to make Jewish jokes, like we could actually get them and we could actually laugh at them. (laughing)
Cole: Was was Natalie more practicing than you were?
Lara: Yeah. Yeah. She had a bat mitzvah, and her family was--- all the more Jewish parents were together. But she never cared, which I really appreciated. She was a good friend.
Cole: Yeah. So you said outside of school is kind of the traditional high school girl drama. What was--- what was that like?
Lara: It was all right. I mean, I'm a dramatic person, but not really in my personal life, or I try not to be. But there were ups and downs and when you are friends with the same five people and then four people for six years, it's--- I mean it's just kind of stressful. But for the most part, it was a pretty steady, dependable, cohesive group. And I'm really appreciative of that. But whatever, like, whatever the dramas were, they definitely were not my favorite, and were not my thing.
Cole: And so by the end of high school, you--- you knew you were going to college--- you wanted to. What did you do?
Lara: I, well, I went on a college tour my freshman year for you. You went on a college tour, and I came along. And I really liked it. I really liked the school. And so I got to senior year, and I kind of was torn between two schools that had good programs in my field. And then I kind of just woke up one morning, and I just decided I wanted to go to Northeastern University, and I didn't want to go to any of those other schools, and that I should just apply ED [early decision], make sure I could go here. And--- and I got in, so I--- I had--- I think it's like kind of frustrating to me because college applications are stressful for everyone. And like the ACT, like, sucks, and like all of it. Like I always understood it, but people--- but I only applied to one school. So I definitely did have it easy. Yeah, so I knew by last December where I was going, and then I could just relax a little.
Cole: What did you like about Northeastern?
Lara: I loved the location. I love being in Boston--- I knew I would love being in Boston, because I've wanted to be in Boston since I was 12. I love--- the school that I was applying for, CAMD, that's--- it houses their theater department. It was--- it's a small school. And the theater program is a small program, very, very--- very, very personalized, very one on one. After a year, all the professors--- all of the main like the year round professors will know you--- full time faculty will know you by name. There's just a lot of opportunities here and that was apparent to me. And I just really--- and I love the campus. And--- and of course, when I applied, I was very excited to be able to do theater in a very almost conservatory style of learning, for it being a liberal arts school. But I was also excited to have like a very traditional college experience of going to hockey games and, you know, being in the city and having there be sororities and frats, not that I'm particularly interested in those. But having like--- having those options and those choices was very attractive to me. And that's--- and like, in the end, why I decided between, like what my top school was, which was here, or Emerson College, which is a arts--- it's a fine art school. So that was kind of like the, I don't want to go to a fine arts school right now. And I also kind of realized that I wanted to get my masters anyway, so. I prefer to go to a s--- like a fine arts school for that.
Cole: So theater seems like a major push factor. You liked to the theater program.
Lara: Yeah.
Cole: When did you start doing theater?
Lara: Like, who did I start doing it with?
Cole: Sure, yeah, but also when--- when in your--- when in your life?
Lara: Well, I--- I started doing theater on my own, like, individually, my sophomore year of high school. I had wanted to for a while but I was playing volleyball competitively. And I was--- I was successful in that. And so that's kind of hard to like turn away from because my sophomore year I was on JV. And so it was just kind of like--- you know, that's a lot to, like, just leave six years of work and to start fresh with something else. But I finally was like, I just kind of have to try it out. So I started sophomore year and then I continued all throughout high school. But in terms of theater being introduced into my life, it was definitely from our grandmother on our mom's side. Because we always would watch musicals and she would always take us to plays and musicals, and it was just like a massive part of our childhood actually.
Cole: What--- what drew you to theater?
Lara: I'm a very--- I'm a very creative person. And I love creative expression. And I love visual art. And--- and performance art. I mean, it--- it's all of my favorite things. I love stories. I love books, it's--- it's like one thing I was struck around about here is that theater majors are just English majors with the need for attention. Because that's just what it is. (laughing) It's like, theater--- it's just like nothing will ever be the same as sitting in a dark theater waiting for the curtains to go up. And so I'm going to just spend my--- or even better, being behind the curtain and hearing the audience and waiting for the curtain to go up. So I feel like I'm pretty much just gonna drain every last ounce of that feeling out of theater. And then if I hate it, I'll move on. But I doubt it.
Cole: Did you ever do anything with theater outside of high school? Before it, or--- or like extracurricularly?
Lara: When I was little, I would do theater camps, actually, which I forgot about until, like, a couple like weeks ago. I was like, oh crap! Yeah, for a couple summers, I would do the Children's--- the Minneapolis Children's Theater summer camps where you would like spend a week and put on a play. But that's pretty much nice--- I was very wrapped up in my high school's theater program. I was, you know, very active in it, because I loved it. So I worked on pretty much anything that I could get my hands on. So I didn't really have time or interest in--- in going into the community at that point in my life.
Cole: And in--- in college, you are--- you're theater major. What else do you hope to do? I know it's just the beginning of your first year.
Lara: Well, I--- I plan on joining choir, to keep that in my life. I--- even though I did make that comment earlier, I am actually looking at sororities, against my better judgment. But I think that this is just such a weird year. That I'm just like, I don't even know what there is to do. Like, I want to play--- I guess, I want to play club volleyball. And like, do a nice little pickup team with my friends because like all of my friends played volleyball here, which we always joke around about. Because I'd love to bring that back into my life. And then, I guess just, you know, get involved in things that interest me as--- as the years goes on. I don't--- I don't put a lot of pressure on--- like in high school, I was involved in a lot of extracurriculars, but I would never be involved in an extracurricular that I didn't care about. Which I kind of got flack for a little bit from like peers? Of, like, "Oh, that's your resume?" But it was just kind of, for me, like, what--- what exactly is the point in dedicating a significant amount of time into something that you're really uninterested in? So I'm just gonna not--- I'm trying to not worry about it too much. And just, you know, when I'm interested in something, I'll try it out.
Cole: What do you envision doing after college?
Lara: I want to work, obviously, in my field, if it exists, because of COVID. But hopefully it does. Right now, I'm really intrigued about being a costume designer, or a director. And I also do love acting, but I'm not sure if that's something that I'd like to pursue full time. So I hope to graduate with, you know, experience in those three things and able to find some sort of entry level position that I can start, you know, figuring it out. My--- my ideal job right now, honestly, is--- there's a theater in Minneapolis called the Guthrie. And my ideal job--- I was there over the summer. And I was like--- not the summer, a while ago, COVID. And I like learned about a job position that is popular in a lot of big theaters like that, and that's Creative Director. And I just kind of realized how amazing it would be to--- because I love consistency. I think it--- and I--- I love to be able to watch things, like, change and evolve. And so I think it'd be really amazing if I could get a position like creative director at a theater in some U.S. city so that I could stay there over years and kind of cultivate a--- a community there. So that's my dream right now.
Cole: After college, do you envision going back to Minneapolis?
Lara: I have no idea. I always--- I love Minneapolis. It's a fantastic city. It's where our mom is presumably going to be for the rest of her life. It's where our dad is going to be for the foreseeable future. And, you know, family is very important to me. But at the same time, like I--- I love being in Boston, and--- and I didn't really realize how quickly your life can be somewhere else from where you've always been. And it's only been two months, but I'm like, highly established here? In--- in--- in--- in both comfortability and in, like, friends and stuff. So it's just like, I don't know. And then I also--- I want to live in New York, and I want to live in Chicago, and I want to go to LA for a bit and so. But I do see myself, like in my life, living in Minneapolis again. I'd be really surprised if I didn't. But not anytime soon, realistically.
Cole: So you like Boston a lot, and you said that was one of--- one of the reasons that you picked Northeastern. And you we're also looking at Emerson, which is also in Boston. What do you like so much about Boston?
Lara: I don't really know. We came here--- actually, I don't think I told you this story yet because I find it hilarious. But we came here to visit our uncle and his then girlfriend, now wife. And we stayed with them at their apartment, and we did the Freedom Trail and we got coffee, and it was--- we were--- I don't remember how old we were. I think we were probably like 13 and 11, if I were to ballpark an area. But I remember I just--- it was all brownstones, and it was an old--- it's an old, old city, and it just kind of feels alive. And you can kind of feel how many people have been there. And I just kind of loved that sort of history. But it also isn't like overwhelming, like--- like I found New York to be, when we visited. And so on that trip, I kind of just became obsessed with the idea of being in Boston. I also love the idea of being near our family. And then I moved here and our dad came to visit us. And it turns out I live like six blocks away from Uncle Lukey's house, that apartment. Because Shlyn [her aunt] was at Northeastern Law School. So I'm literally exactly where I wanted to be, when I was 11. (laughing)
Cole: Wow. Wow.
Lara: (sarcastically) Which makes it feel meant to be, awwww!
Cole: Okay. Well, I feel like we've gone over quite a bit of your life and into the future. We asked you to make--- I asked you to make some predictions, I guess. So now we can start talking about some of the other, more abstract questions that I have today.
Lara: Yeah.
Cole: I guess first of all, you said that you feel Jewish--- you know you are Jewish because your dad was Jewish and because your grandmother was Jewish, right? What do you know about your grandparents and great grandparents and any other ancestors who were Jewish?
Lara: I know absolutely nothing. And it was only when I was reading those questions that I realized how little I know. I think I only realized that we were like--- like, ethnically Jewish when we check that DNA test, because it's not--- I don't know which countries we're from, on her side. Like I know--- I know that Nana is Italian and French Canadian. And Opa is German. And Papa is Scottish. Like I know, like, all of it. I've--- I have no idea for Gammy and--- and G Grandma. And I think that's really interesting. And I--- I'd imagine that there is a correlation between that being the Jewish family just due to history? But I don't know where anyone's from.
Cole: So you don't know where they came from, you don't know what [crosstalk] United States?
Lara: I don't know when. I just know that my great grandmother is not an immigrant. So it means that my great great grandparents, at the earliest, were the people who came to the United States. And I know that they're from Europe. But I don't know when. And it wasn't--- time wise, there's no way that it was because of World War Two. Because that would have been a predecc-- like that would have been before. So I have no idea. But we're here.
Cole: Do you--- do you consider yourself the child of immigrants?
Lara: No. I don't, at all. On mom's side, it's--- our--- her father. He's--- he's not a first generation immigrant. But every single other person in his family is. He's the baby. So I think he's good as, but still, like, they were very--- they're very established here. He was the youngest so his--- he--- I don't--- I don't know if like he was an immigrant, but Mom very clearly isn't. Same with Nana, her parents weren't born here, but she was, and Mom was, obviously. And then I know with Dad that that--- that that's--- that his entire family's been here for more than--- more generations. At least on his mom's side. I'm not sure about his dad's side. But I'd say a lot. So I don't really consider it to be daughter of immigrants, even though obviously, we are. Most people are here.
Cole: Yeah, yeah. And we talked about this a little bit, but you said something very interesting. You said you didn't know you were Jewish in elementary school, and you realized it in middle school. Can you say anything more about that?
Lara: I mean, it's not that I realized it in middle school--- well, I did. So I didn't realize that Jewish was--- wasn't just a religion until middle school. And I had no freaking clue that we were any of that until our parents got divorced. And then until we started going to synagogue and seeing our extended family more often. So first was the realization that our family was religiously Jewish, and that we could be too. And that was a couple years after our parents' divorce. And then was the middle school realization of, there's more to being Jewish than religiously Jewish, and you can be religiously Jewish and not be Ashkenazi, and you can be Ashkenazi and not be religiously Jewish, and there are other types of Jewish than Ashkenazi. And that was like more com--- it was just--- it's a complicated--- it's pretty complicated thing to think about when you're 12.
Cole: Yeah, yeah. So you said there are multiple ways of being Jewish? Which ways do you consider yourself Jewish? I know we talked about this a little bit earlier, but.
Lara: I consider myself, you know, like, I'm an Ashkenazi Jew. I'm a forth, at least. But then religiously, I consider myself to be Jewish. But I'd like to explore that a bit more and to be able to be confident in it. But I'm confident in my Jewish, like, ethnicity, heritage. Blood.
Cole: What does it mean to you to be Jewish? Not necessarily how are you Jewish, but what does it mean to you?
Lara: I think it's, it's important to me. It helps me understand where I'm from. It impacts my worldview. I think that I am a lot more interested in--- in that side of my heritage due to its somewhat shaky history than maybe some of my other nationalities. Yeah, it--- it's a very important part of who I am. I think that connecting to and--- and being confident in the fact that I'm Jewish helped me understand, you know, myself in relation to the world a bit better. Yeah, I'm very proud of it.
Cole: You said it impacted your worldview. How did--- how does it do that? Or how--- in which ways does it impact your worldview?
Lara: Realizing anti-Semitism and understanding anti-Semitism as it impacts me and, more importantly, how it impacts people around the world, even in this country, helped me understand the need for, like, radical anti-racism in every part of this country. You know, once I--- then the--- and this happened the middle school, like, obviously, to a certain extent, in a very--- this is where the whole part of our elementary school I think was unproductive was that racism wasn't talked about, racism was probably teached. Taught. Racism was probably taught to us in--- in very nonverbal, very microaggressional ways. And so realizing that I was Jewish, and that people around the world, for no good reason, hated Jewish people, helped me understand a bunch of other complex social issues that probably would have taken me a whole lot longer to understand if I hadn't taken anti-Semitism around the world personally. I know that there are a lot of different--- like there's a lot of different levels to these things and--- and all of that, but--- but recognizing anti-Semitism made me recognize racism.
Cole: Have you ever experienced anti-Semitism personally?
Lara: On an individual level, they're very small microaggressions. Like I've had people make fun of my nose. Even though my nose is Italian. (laughing) The Jesus thing. A couple of other, like, exclusionatory things of like "Well Lara's Jewish, like she won't whatever." Or--- or I've been called cheap. I've been called the cheap Jew. But those are just very--- like, they never really got to me because they were just microaggressions to me. But I think--- you know, nationally, there's definitely some--- there's--- there's some stress, you know, if a synagogue is shot up, if there are literal Nazis. If the president endorses literal Nazis, there's definitely some stress there for my family and--- and my community that I'm trying to be a part of more act--- like, more actively. It's definitely, you know, not really reassuring.
Cole: So last summer, do you remember when Lake Harriet [Community School]--- there was a swastika painted on the door?
Lara: I do.
Cole: How did that make you feel?
Lara: That made me mad. That made me real mad. I don't--- yeah, I just don't understand the--- the thought process behind things like that. It's a freaking children's school. It's for kids to go school--- and it was like--- I think it's cowardly. I think it's ridiculous to be so quiet and sneaky with your hatred. If you're going to have hatred, stop sneaking around and ruining children's playgrounds. At the same time, it's just like swastikas are disgusting. I think that what they represent is even gross--- grosser. So that was just frustrating. I think the thing that got me was like, that's my school. And I think the worst thing about it for me personally was that if I had gone there, I wouldn't have known what it was. Like if I--- because I went there--- I started going to that school when I was what, seven? But then I didn't realize I was Jewish. (laughing) So I wouldn't have I wouldn't have understood. And I wouldn't have cared.
Cole: Can you tell me a little bit more about this comment that you were a "cheap Jew?"
Lara: Yeah, I don't even--- I was--- it was--- it wasn't--- someone didn't say, like, "Lara's a cheap Jew." It was--- we were talking about plans, and I was talking about how I didn't want to do something because it was expensive. And this was in high school. This was like, bowling or something stupid. And I was like, guys, like, we--- I don't want to spend that much money. And they're like, it's because--- someone--- someone goes "It's cuz you're Jewish." And I'm kind of just looking at them, being like, you kidding me? Like, you are 17 years old! And remember them being like "It's a joke. Why can't you take a joke." Like, the sexism and anti-Semitism alone. Just microaggressions. But still, just kind of, are you kidding. You're---you're almost an adult.
Cole: Was that a friend of yours?
Lara: It was.
Cole: Are you still friends with them?
Lara: No.
Cole: Because of the comment, or other things?
Lara: A lot of teenage boys make Holocaust jokes. And they will just never be funny to me. And I don't understand how they could ever be funny to anyone. Like we're talking about mass genocide that people today have lived through. Like, this is not--- yeah, just like, I don't think racist jokes are funny. I don't think that--- like I don't think--- yeah, it's just so--- teenage boys think they're really funny, especially the Catholic ones. And I find that incredibly annoying. So usually, I'm not friends with those kids, so. Whether or not they know I'm not friends with them, that's kind of a different story, but I'm not. (laughing)
Cole: You used this word 'microaggression' a couple of times. Can you say more about what that means?
Lara: Yeah, it's just--- the way that it was explained to me was it's not a blatant act of racism. It's smaller, stereotypical remarks that just like slowly but surely grind your gears. Yeah, things like the idea of Jewish people being cheap. That's a stereotype. And so to make comments about it over and over and over again, it turns into, at least for some people, microaggression, where it just really gets on your nerves. Even though it is just a small, stupid comment. It's not necessarily blatant anti-Semitism. It's just like, that's so annoying. That you're just going to hold on to that stereotype.
Cole: When you--- when you learned about microaggressions, you said somebody told you the definition, right? Did it resonate with you as something you had experienced? Or did it take some time to realize--- because you described your experiences as microaggressions. Did it take some time for that to--- for that realization to come through?
Lara: It definitely took some time for me to realize that I was experiencing microaggressions as a Jewish person. But when the definition of microaggression was explained to me, I instantly resonated with it because I'm a woman. So I definitely could instantly see like a lot of microaggressions that I lived through as a woman, but it took longer for me to understand them as a Jewish person.
Cole: What types of things were microaggressions because you were a woman? Or because you are a woman?
Lara: Just--- there's like names, like, prude, or slut, or anything in between. Stereotype that women aren't funny. Stereotype that women are bad drivers. Stereotype that--- there's just--- I mean, there's hundreds, and there's definitely more that I experienced due to being a woman than I do to being Jewish. And so that's definitely why I was like--- or like the whole take a joke thing, or--- or can't you just relax, or you must be on your period. Like, there's just a lot of that in high school and I'm sure in the world, but I'm hoping not. Yeah, so that was definitely like, easier to understand. In its relation to me. Just sexism.
Cole: Did you ever feel like you were being discriminated against or kind of feel somebody--- or--- I guess, hear a microaggression because you were a Jewish woman?
Lara: Actually---
Cole: Or was it only ever because of one of those two identities?
Lara: I actually don't--- they've intersect--- I haven't had one that I've recognized as being like the product of me being a Jewish woman, but I have had, like, the two for one, where they make a Holocaust joke, and "why can't you take a joke?" And it's like, okay, you've hit everything. Good job. But I don't think--- I don't think I've had any that intersect.
Cole: And so you talked about how outside of individual anti-Semitism, you felt kind of systemic anti-Semitism, or just anti-Semitism out there in the world, like synagogue shootings, and that affected you. Can you talk more about that?
Lara: Yeah, it's just--- I think it's kind of overwhelming to realize. Because it's a realization, unfortunately, that everyone--- that--- not everyone, but that a lot of people have, at some point in their lives, that an identity that you have, something that you identify with, is hated by people, just around the world. And I'm sure that this realization, for me, and I'm incredibly lucky that it was, but this realization for me, was a lot later than, say, Black Americans, like I'm sure that that is a realization that they have before they can, like, really communicate the feelings. When they're--- when they're young children. So I am lucky that it took till middle school to realize these things, but yeah, it's just like--- it's just frustrating to see those situations and--- and that amount of hate and--- and have it feel personal even if it's not. Because it's--- it's what they hate--- what they did to them, they would do to you. And I think that that's very terrifying.
Cole: Yeah. You said earlier that you were proud of being Jewish. Can you talk more about that?
Lara: Yeah, I--- I just--- it's a resilient--- it's a resilient group of people, historically. There's, there's a lot, a lot, and you know, we're talking goes back to the Middle Ages. I'm sure that, you know, every group of people can have that sort of pride of making it through time and standing the test of time. And I just love that, even after the most recent, like, serious genocide of the Jewish people being the Holocaust, like there's already, you know, a lot of rebuilding that's happening. So I'm--- I just--- I think it's incredibly beautiful, that we're of a people that have that sort of resiliency.
Cole: Yeah. Do you consider yourself white?
Lara: Yes.
Cole: How does that intersect with being Jewish?
Lara: I'm the white version of Jew. I'm European Jew. Like I'm straight up from Europe. I'm sure that--- I think--- I think that for me, it intersects with being Jewish in that I am both ostracized from maybe other white people, due to my religion? But I'm also incredibly privileged. And I have a lot of benefits from my skin tone. And I also do not look Jewish in a traditional sense. So people usually wouldn't guess it.
Cole: Do you--- do you think that not looking Jewish has shielded you somehow? And I guess kind of a secondary question is--- is what do you--- what do you mean when you say look Jewish?
Lara: They're--- well, according to media, like, Jewish people have, you know, curly hair and big noses and there's a lot of stereotypes there. And--- and olive skin, and--- and I don't fit, like, a single one of those. Yeah, oh! I told him I was Jewish, and they were like, "You look like Hitler's perfect little---" People are really--- people are weird. Yes, someone was like, "You look--- but you look like Hitler's perfect person?" I was like, Jesus, man. How do you respond to that? But yeah, I think that it most certainly has in ways that I don't even understand because it has been happening. So I'm sure that you know, if you look traditionally Jewish and traditionally, stereotypically Jewish, people are always gonna have something to say. But then again, people are always gonna have something to say, so.
Cole: Hmm. Um, okay. I want to ask you about your, your attitudes towards intermarriage. For a time--- for a very long time, many commentators in the Jewish community have said that intermarriage of Jewish people with people of other religions is bad. And yet, your parents--- your dad was Jewish and your mom was not. And your grandparents--- your--- your grandmother was Jewish and your grandfather was not. What do you think about the claim that intermarriage is a bad thing? And would you ever consider only looking to marry people who were Jewish?
Lara: Yeah, I don't think intermarriage is a bad thing at all. I don't--- I don't like that we use reasons to separate each other. I dated a kid who was Christian, dating a kid who's Jewish, like, it's not really a big deal, to me. (laughing) I don't think it's a big deal at all. I think that if anything, kids are gonna be able to grow up and know a lot more about a lot of stuff. So that's nothing--- nothing bad there.
Cole: What would you say to somebody who considers you not Jewish because your mom isn't Jewish?
Lara: I just think that's a very old-fashioned point of view, but also, I think that it's a complicated issue, because that is part of the religion. And I think that, honestly, that part of the religion doesn't really harm anyone. I don't feel any--- I mean, maybe--- maybe it does. Maybe like psychologically, mentally, emotionally, it could definitely harm someone. But I--- I don't--- I don't--- the amount of--- the type of religion that I'm looking for is not, you know, anything Orthodox, or--- or--- or extreme. So it really won't impact me at all. And I could have--- I could have been going to synagogue this entire time with zero issues. So I don't--- I don't find that--- that doesn't really frustrate me. I've never had that used against me. People are--- most of the time, people are just happy you're there.
Cole: Interesting. So talk to me about this Jewish kid that you're dating. Are they--- do they practice more or less than you? Yeah.
Lara: He practices--- he definitely practiced more than I did. I don't know if he had a bar mitzvah. I don't know. I don't know. But he definitely, like, practiced more than I did as a--- as a kid. And I think--- I don't know if both his parents are Jewish, but I know his parents are together. So he--- he was--- him and his twin sister were raised Jewish.
Cole: When you--- when you kind of meet other people who are Jewish, does it feel often like they practiced more than you?
Lara: (quietly) Yeah.
Cole: Okay.
Lara: Yeah, definitely. Because I didn't practice very much at all. I mean, I guess maybe that's how I view it because our family practiced more than I did. But it usually feels like they practice more, but I think that--- yeah, I think that generally they do practice more than I do (trailing off). Because they did.
Cole: Yeah. Okay. So I think we can move into some of the--- the last questions here. I'll read one of them for you. I sent this to you earlier. Jews are historically overrepresented in certain fields and among high achieving individuals. For example, as of 2010, Jews made up 27% of Nobel physics laureates, 21% of Ivy League student bodies, and 37% of Oscar winning directors. Why do you think this is?
Lara: I think that that's a super complicated issue. And I really hate the term of 'model minority.' I really--- it grinds my gears. Because usually, it's just an excuse for colorism. And people are gonna think that Jewish--- the stereotypical Jewish person is a model minority, because they're close to being white. But in terms of--- because they are white. In terms of the representation, like, the over-representation in those fields, I think that when--- I think that a lot of different--- like, for example, one thing--- this wasn't on your list, but there's a stereotype that Jewish people are the bankers, and they have all the money, and that's why they're horrible and we hate them. But another thing that I learned last year in that course that I was talking about earlier is that the reason that that is the case is because in ancient societies, both Islam and Christianity banned their practicers from giving loans to other people. So they couldn't loan out money. It was against their religion. And they couldn't--- yeah. And that was not the case in Judaism. So naturally, the Jewish people of the societies would give loans, AKA, they were the bankers and it just became family businesses. And--- and that's what you did. And so I think there's probably a lot of different situations like that, where it's just those were fields that Jewish people entered, and then it'd be kind of--- became industries, by Jewish--- run by Jewish people, or with a large Jewish population. But I don't think that it's necessarily a positive or negative. I think that what is negative is the--- maybe the stigma that could surround it of--- of model minority.
Cole: So let's talk about the the model minority phrase. It seems like you took that from the next question. Did you hear it before I sent you these?
Lara: Yeah, I hear that often about Asian Americans and about Jewish people and about some other--- and then--- and then thrown around to different groups of people.
Cole: Where do you hear it? And who do you hear from?
Lara: I hear it, probably, academically, pretty often. It's--- and I hear it in the news, I'd say? I hear it in--- and I--- I don't hear the phrase 'model minority,' but I definitely hear things like, "Why can't you be like them," like, in the news and--- and sort of used generally, like in a racist manner of, "Why can't you be like Asian Americans? Why can't you be--- just be like Jewish people?" Or situations like that where there's comparisons between different minority groups.
Cole: Interesting. So I'll read you the next question. Jewish over-representation has led to claims like--- like you said, you've heard before, that Jews are sort of model minority compared with other groups that are numerical minorities of the United States, like Black Americans, that are underrepresented in the same arenas. Do you think of Jews as a model minority? And I know you said you don't like that term. But do you think they fit that description?
Lara: I think that--- I think that if they do fit that description, it's only because that ideal was fostered in order to kind of avoid actually supporting and changing the way that things are done for other minorities. If that makes sense? It's like, if--- if they could do it, why can't you? Well, it's not that simple, and--- and there are a lot of things holding back--- like you said, Black Americans are underrepresented in those exact same arenas. There are a hell of a lot more things holding back Black Americans than there are supporting them at--- in this--- in this country. So I think that the phrase--- if Jewish people are model minorities, it's only because that phrase was coined to put down other groups of people and not actually give them the support and--- and reparations or recognition or help that they need as a--- as a community that's been, you know, destroyed over and over again.
Cole: So let's talk about model minority applied to other groups. In particular, Asian Americans, like you mentioned. This is something that's been said, at least in the media and in academia, since the 1960s, that Asian Americans are a model minority. For example, Asian Americans are overrepresented in medicine, where 17% of all active physicians identify as Asian and also in Ivy League student bodies. Do you think that Asian American over-representation is related to Jewish over-representation at all?
Lara: I imagine that they are in ways that I don't understand. I think that, realistically, when you see over-representation, there's a reason for it. And it might not be the same reason but I could definitely see them coming about in a similar way. Yeah, I think--- I think over-representation is an issue only when it is directly, like, impacting the representation of other people, but I think it's also a very complex issue. Like, I'm gonna keep borrowing from the next questions, like about the college situation. Like you said, in academia and Ivy League schools. Yeah, I think it's an incredibly complex issue, but I don't find the over-representation of Asian students alarming at all. Because there's still a crap ton more white kids. It's like? (incredulous look)
Cole: Yeah, let's talk about that. Something that's come up recently, in legal arenas and in society, is that a lot of Ivy League schools have a lot of Asian students. And there have been accusations that these--- that these schools have instituted quotas, of a sort, to try to keep Asian student populations low.
Lara: Yeah, I don't---
Cole: What did you say?
Lara: I don't like that very much.
Cole: You don't like quotas?
Lara: Mm mm. I don't--- like I don't like quotas that cap the population of minorities in--- in a school like that. I--- I appreciate quotas that ensure that other minorities are also getting their fair share. But, yeah, I don't--- I think that the only group of people that should be capped in terms of admittance to such a prestigious school are white people.
Cole: So there's an ongoing lawsuit right now to--- about alleged quotas in Harvard's--- and discrimination in Harvard's admissions against Asian Americans. And the lawsuit seeks to also strike down affirmative action. Do you--- do you think that makes sense?
Lara: These--- I--- I don't--- I don't think it makes sense. I think that those are important things that are just the tip of the iceberg for what needs to happen in academia and in college admissions and in education in the United States. I don't--- if I'm understanding correctly, these lawsuits are trying to stop Asian students--- like lower the numbers of Asian students?
Cole: The lawsuits are brought by Asian students, at least some Asian students. And they seek--- they point out that the bar, the bar that an Asian student must--- much--- must reach to get into an Ivy League school, is higher than that of a white student. And the bar for a white student is higher than that, they claim, a Black student or Latino student, or a Native American student. And they say that the fact that different--- that people from different races have different standards--- are required to meet different standards is discriminatory.
Lara: I agree with that. I think that--- I think I just didn't understand the question. But I think that that's ridiculous. I think that, again, the only--- I'm not the most educated on this topic, but the only quotas that makes sense to me, are ones that ensure that white people aren't overrepresented.
Cole: So you'd support--- you'd support white students having to meet a higher bar than, say, Black students if it made if it made sure that Black students were adequately represented in the college?
Lara: I--- I don't know. Because to me, they're--- like, of the applicants of Harvard, I don't think it's that--- if we're talking about Ivy League schools, I don't think it's that, for use of a better phrase, black and white. It's--- of the applicants of Harvard, there are enough absolutely astounding applicants with the grades, with the extracurriculars, with the--- like with the brain, that are Black that would fill up a ton of seats at that school. I don't think that it's that Black students are going to be worse, because we're not letting all of the white kids take their spots. Like there are so many exemplary people applying to college every year, regardless of their race. And it is true that--- that it is so much harder already, just due to societal stereotypes and biases, for a Black kid to get into college that could have the exact same numbers, exact same resume, as if it was a white kid applying. I just think that it's not that some poor super brilliant white kid isn't gonna get into college for working super-duper hard. It's that there was just a--- there was a--- they're the--- like, they're the same student and then, honestly, I think that there needs to be more representation and more diversity in all of these Ivy League's, in all--- in all colleges in general. So I don't think that it's a bad thing at all if white kids don't go to Harvard. Like white kids are fine.
Cole: A slightly related question. Some people recently have started calling Asian Americans the "new Jew." And that's for a couple of reasons. First, they--- they chart out the trajectory of both groups, and they say that there are similarities, both with immigration patterns and relative success in terms of over--- over-representation after immigration. They also point to what we're talking about about quotas, alleged quotas at higher education institutions.
Lara: Yes.
Cole: So, in the 1920s, in response to soaring Jewish enrollments, many prestigious colleges in the northeast, like Harvard and Yale, instituted enrollment quotas that were highly effective at keeping most Jews out of their student bodies. How do you feel about this?
Lara: Yeah, I don't like that either. I think that--- I mean, the 1920s was even a different time than the 2020s in terms of racism and--- not racism, anti-Semitism towards Jewish people. And yeah, I mean a lot was churning on the world stage in terms of anti-Semitism at the time. And I don't--- I don't think that anyone who's considered a minority should be held back because they're doing too well. It just doesn't seem great. If it becomes like a--- like, what we were talking about in terms of industry, that could be concerning, but I don't think it's as deep as it seems. I think it's probably just white people getting pissed off that someone different from them is doing better than them. I'd also like to say that I don't consider myself to be a minority.
Cole: Say more---
Lara: I'm not.
Cole: ---about that.
Lara: I just--- I don't consider myself to be a minority. I'm of--- you know, I'm white, I'm a woman, but I'm a--- I'm a white woman of, like, immense privilege, just like full stop there. But then I have all the privileges in my life from my parents and my, you know, financial stability of my family, and so I don't consider myself to be a minority. I do consider myself to be Jewish. And I know that Jewish people are a minority. But there is definitely a disconnect there, because never in my life has being Jewish--- yeah, I don't know. I think it's--- I think it's a very complicated issue that I haven't really figured out. But I do not consider myself to be a minority.
Cole: Interesting. How do you feel about the claim that Asian Americans are the "new Jew?"
Lara: I think it's just people looking for a way to negate the successes of minorities, especially people of color. They need them to be the "new Jew" because God forbid, they actually are a highly-achieving group of people with an intense work ethic. And really good grades, like---
Cole: Say more about that. What do you mean they need them to be the "new Jew"?
Lara: I think that sometimes racism isn't, you know, white hoods and burning crosses. It's--- it's small biases and stigmas and holding oneself to a higher standard. It can just be simple ideas of us versus them or something like that. So I think that it's--- it's very likely given the amount of racism in--- in our--- in this country that white people's racism, like very, very--- I hate to say the words together, but low key racism, because it's not low key, it's racism, but it's--- it's very quiet racism, would prefer there to be an excuse or a reason for why Asian Americans are so successful in this country. Like a justification for it, of why they're succeeding so much, rather than they are just successful. And--- and by using things like the "new Jew" then they can also say, "Look, they're--- they're good. Like, they can do it, right? Jewish people did it, right? They're doing it, right? Why aren't African people doing it right? Why aren't blank people doing it right?" So they can--- they can get around the whole race issue of the situation by just simply having there be a right way to be an immigrant and a right way to be successful.
Cole: Hmm. (straw slurping sound) I think that's all of the questions that I have. Do you have anything that comes to mind that you'd like to say about the topics that we discussed? About your life, even, about being Jewish?
Lara: Be nice to each other. (laughing) Stop that. No, that's pretty much it. I'm good. That was a lot.
Cole: Well, I will stop the recording.