Cole: Awesome. And so today is November 1, 2020, and I'm here with
Ellen: Ellen [...].
Cole: Awesome. I'm going to call you Gammy just for this because that would be weird otherwise.
Ellen: Yeah, it would be weird.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: AKA, Gammy. Yeah.
Cole: Yeah. Okay, so we're gonna go through the questions chronologically, roughly. So let's start with the first pre-interview question that I sent you about your experience growing up. And I just want to hear anything you can remember about growing up. Where you grew up, who your parents were, what it was like. Anything about that.
Ellen: Okay. So, I must have lost some of this stuff. Sorry, Coley. I had a whole bunch of other stuff on here that it looks like I lost.
Cole: Anything that comes to mind would work great.
Ellen: Sure. So I guess, let me ask you a question about that. Do you want experiences about being Jewish growing up? Or just regular experiences?
Cole: Anything. Anything that you think is important enough to come to your mind. So, if it ends up having to do with being Jewish, that's okay, that's great. If not, then that's still okay. That's great.
Ellen: Okay.
Cole: Some of the questions will be specifically about the experiences in your life where being Jewish might have had an impact. But for this one, I just want to know a little bit about what your life was like, at the beginning.
Ellen: Okay. So, let's see. I was the oldest, so I had four years alone with my parents. I don't think I was particularly thrilled to have another child come along. There are stories about my asking, you know, what if I dropped her on her head, and what if, whatever, but I also have good memories of having sisters, as well. So, we lived in a small house, and I shared rooms with my sisters. We had a lot of close family that were involved in our lives. My mom--- and we can get into this more when we talk about Grandma and Grandpa, but my mom grew up in Hartford [a city in Connecticut], and my dad grew up in Brooklyn, New York, but--- but moved to Middletown [another town in Connecticut]. And my grandparents on both sides lived fairly close. So every week we would see our grandparents. We would go to one of their houses for dinner, or they would come to ours. So I have a lot of memories of both sets of grandparents being involved in our lives. Going to their house, them cooking, having big family things going on. I also have memories of our neighborhood. It was a neighborhood with a lot--- a lot of kids in it. So we did a lot of things and--- and early on, I was always involved in running neighborhood carnivals, or plays, or whatever, for some kind of charity that needed money. You know, it was the Danny Thomas leukemia thing, or the this or the that, but we used to just put together these elaborate kind of singing things and dancing things and acting things and whatever and everybody in the neighborhood--- there were a lot of young families--- you know, we'd have tickets, and we'd have a little tent and we'd have lemonade, and we'd have blah, blah, blah. So that was--- I have great memories of growing up in this small house in Wethersfield [a town in Connecticut near Hartford].
Cole: And so you---
Ellen: And--- oh, go ahead Cole.
Cole: Oh, no, no, you said that--- so you grew up in Wethersfield, but your mom grew up in Hartford and your dad in Brooklyn?
Ellen: Yeah.
Cole: How did--- how did your dad end up in Connecticut?
Ellen: My grandfather, and that's a whole nother story, but he owned bake--- he owned grocery stores in New York. And he decided to start a coffee company. And he then started to drive around and to sell the coffee to different grocery stores.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: And he--- he went into Connecticut, and he really liked Middletown. So he moved his family there. I think when my dad was probably in his, like, teens, early teen--- before high school, because he got in trouble in high school and he went to a military academy in Georgia---
Cole: Wow, okay.
Ellen: ---that he really wanted to go to. He wanted to be in the service. And he wanted to go to this military academy. So he was happy to go there. But, yeah.
Cole: Did your dad ever serve in the military?
Ellen: He did not. He wanted to get into West Point, and he didn't have the grades. Or he thinks he didn't get in because he was Jewish.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: So that was something that he--- he felt he didn't get in because he was Jewish.
Cole: Mm hmm. Was he a--- was he a good student in school? You said he got into some trouble.
Ellen: I think he was a bit of a daredevil. I think he was a good student, if he wanted to be. But he--- I don't think he took it all that tremendously seriously. I think--- when he went to military school, he did very well.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: I think he was a man who really liked rules, I would say. You know, liked to know what was what. And I think that that was probably a better place for him at that point.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: So the other thing that I remember in this neighborhood was we were--- we were--- Wethersfield did not have a huge Jewish community. However, they did have--- there--- there was a synagogue in Wethersfield that my parents were very active in, and it was, you know, the only synagogue in town. And my dad especially was like president of the men's club or vice president of the synagogue, like he was pretty active in it. We went--- you know, there were Saturday morning services for kids, there were Friday night services for adults, and there was Sunday school, and we always did those things. So growing up, you know, Sunday morning was always--- always Sunday school, except in the summer. And as I got older, there was Hebrew school after school where I would walk from whatever school I was in to this--- this woman's house--- Mrs. Fried's house, who--- I can see her today, you know, hair pulled back in a bun and, God, her house always smelled like fish, whenever I walked into it. But she would always give me like milk and a cookie. And there were a couple of us who had Hebrew school lessons with her.
Ellen: And I think I was one of the first females that actually had a bat mitzvah in this synagogue. Because it was conservative, which is--- at that point, didn't let girls do a whole lot of things.
Cole: Yeah, what was your experience with the synagogue? So you went every week, it sounds like, multiple---
Ellen: Yep.
Cole: ---times, maybe?
Ellen: I loved it.
Cole: Yeah, talk---
Ellen: I loved it. I mean, my friends were there. You know, on Sunday mornings, when we had--- we would have Sunday school downstairs, and they always had a--- a bagel and lox break--- breakfast upstairs. And so you'd be downstairs in Sunday school or Hebrew school and you'd smell the coffee and you'd smell everything and I just--- I liked the people there. I liked I think the sense of community, is--- through reading through your questions and through thinking about things, I think that's what I always looked for in a--- in religion is a sense of community. And I love--- I never minded any of that in that synagogue.
Cole: Was there a different one?
Ellen: Yeah.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: Yeah. After I had my bar--- bat mitzvah there, my parents decided--- I was--- when I was 13, that they wanted to go to a synagogue where there were more young people. So, basically, my dad was pretty strict. And he--- you know, I was 13, I was starting to get interested in boys. Actually, I think I started to get int--- interested in boys when I was about five. But--- (laughing) They had a wedding for me! They--- there are pictures, movie pictures of a wedding in this neighborhood, this little neighborhood that we were in. But when I was five, there was a seamstress in the neighborhood, and she made me a wedding dress and I married this neighbor, Tommy Bassel. And they actually had a freaking wedding.
Cole: Wow.
Ellen: With a wedding cake, and favors. I mean, it's ridiculous to think about now, like, what were they--- what were they thinking? You know? I don't know. But---
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: I can remember the whole thing. Probably from the pictures, but whatever. So he would not--- he did not want me to date people--- boys that weren't Jewish. That was a big deal. So they moved to this other synagogue that was reformed, and I absolutely hated it and refused to go to it. So that was kind of it for me with synagogue until much later in my life when I was with Gampy.
Cole: And so you--- that was when you were 14 or so?
Ellen: Yeah.
Cole: 13?
Ellen: Yep, there--- yep. I had my--- we moved to another house, to another neighborhood. Bigger house, fancier neighborhood in Wethersfield. And my parents, they--- actually my mom really wanted to move to like West Hartford or to a suburb that had a way bigger Jewish population.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: And my--- they couldn't afford it. So they did this other thing where they switched synagogues in hopes that their three girls would then meet and marry Jewish men. Of which none of us have.
Cole: Yeah, yeah.
Ellen: None of us have ever been interested in, (laughing) oddly enough.
Cole: Your sisters, at the time when you switched synagogues, they were--- how old were they?
Ellen: I was still drive--- I would drive them there. I had just gotten my license. So they were--- so Elise was four years younger than I was, and Nancy--- so--- say it was--- like, I was 14 or 15, when we started, so Elise would have been, you know, 11. And Nancy would have been seven years younger than me.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: And they both went there and got actively involved in a youth group and did date some Jewish guys and went to dances and parties and events and stuff.
Cole: Yeah. Okay. What was--- what was school like outside of going to Hebrew school at night?
Ellen: Regular school?
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: It was--- Wethersfield., it was not a diverse suburb, at all--- really at all.
Cole: Who--- what do you mean by that?
Ellen: I would say, for people of color, there were maybe three--- two or three. You know, I can remember one guy, that I--- boy that I was friends with or lived near us. There are a lot of other, you know, immigrant families. So I had friends whose families spoke Greek and Italian. I'm trying to think of what else. Maybe Polish, whose parents spoke that. So they had--- you know, they were second generation.
Cole: Did you think of yourself as a product of immigrants in any way?
Ellen: No, I did not. Although, I was--- when I look back on it, I was the first person in my family to graduate college. Because my mom didn't, and my dad did later. I mean he did it as an adult. He went back to school, got his undergraduate degree, and then went on to get his master's.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: Yeah.
Cole: So, the--- the town wasn't very diverse. What was you--- your high school experience. I don't know, were you--- were you like your dad? Were--- were you a little bit of a troublemaker?
Ellen: No, I was pretty--- I was like, secretary of my class and I was a decent--- I was a good--- a good student. Not--- not a tremendous student, but a hard-working, good student. I--- let's see, I worked. I always worked after school. As soon as I was 16. My parents weren't--- you know, they wouldn't let me get like waitressing jobs at a Friendly's [a chain restaurant], or--- they thought that was not appropriate. My dad did. He was worried that like somebody would look up my skirt as I was scooping ice cream. (chuckling) But, I worked. I worked as a dental helper, like I worked in a--- in a dentist's office. I used to walk there after high school. There were no--- in my high school, at that point, it was just--- like, I graduated in 1969, right, so. Right before then, there was just kind of the start of girls sports. There were no girls sports, really, in my high school. So there was nothing that you could--- that I could do. I tried out for cheerleaders, and I didn't make it. But that was like the only--- other than gymnastics, I think, the only sport for girls. I wrote for the school newspaper. I was on student council. I think I was president of student council at one point or something. And we changed it so that girls could wear pants. So at that point, girls had to wear skirts. So that was like a big deal, to be able to wear pants to school. So I pretty much did--- met the expectations for my--- that my parents had on me, in terms of being good in school, being--- I was pretty popular, I--- what I did that they did not know about, and didn't like, when they found out, was that I dated people who weren't Jewish. Like, my dad had this thing that I could only date someone who wasn't Jewish two times, and then I had to break up with them. So it didn't get too serious. That--- that didn't do so well in teaching me about, like, how to have a relationship, you know? (chuckling) But I used to just lie and sneak around.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: So I would have, you know, different friends of the guy I was dating pick me up. And then we would just switch cars. But the issue, the problem I had, is that my dad was a real estate agent in town, and he knew freaking everybody. So, like, if I went to the--- there was a--- a mall in our town, like a--- fairly nice kind of strip mall, and I would go to this store, and I would buy a tie for a boyfriend. And you know, two days later--- and I--- you know, two days later, my dad would say, "Who'd you give that tie to?" You know, I mean, he would just--- he would find out everything that I did. Which was unfortunate.
Ellen: So, yeah. Yes.
Cole: And your--- your sisters, you said they got involved with with the new synagogue.
Ellen: Mm hmm.
Cole: Did they also have bat mitzvahs and---
Ellen: No.
Cole: No.
Ellen: Because reformed Jewish people don't do that.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: So, they did not. They had a confirmation or something that was very different. And Aunty Leese had a bat mitzvah as an adult.
Ellen: When--- in the synagogue in Hebron that we belonged to for a long time.
Cole: Mm hmm. So after you finished high school, you said you were the first in your family to go to college?
Ellen: Well, because Mom--- Mom and Dad both went to college, but both dropped out.
Cole: Okay. Where did they go? Do you know?
Ellen: My mom--- Grandma Sally went to UConn [the University of Connecticut], and lived there for one or two years. And she met Grandpa Alan there on a blind date with a friend. And Grandpa Alan went to Long Island University or some University in New York until he got married and he dropped out.
Cole: Okay, and where did you go?
Ellen: My first year, I went to Lesley College in Cambridge [Massachusetts]. So that was 1969 in--- in Boston, in Cambridge, crazy time. And then I got involved there with like the SDS, the Students for Democratic Society, and the Black Panthers. And decided that it was too bourgeois to go to a private college and pay all that money when other people couldn't go to college. So I went to UConn after that, and I lived at home. UConn, at that point, didn't take transfer students. So I lived wi--- back with my parents for Septemb--- let's see, I lived there that summer, and I was wild and crazy. And I gave my parents agida. And then I went to the branch of Hartford at--- that--- UConn and--- in West Hartford, and I moved out in January. And I moved into an apartment in Hartford with like six other people. It was like a little yoga commune, kind of thing. Yeah.
Cole: So when you were at Lesley College, with--- with the SDS and Black Panthers, was your Jewish identity ever a factor in deciding to become part of those groups? Or were--- were there other reasons?
Ellen: I think there were other reasons. I mean, there was--- the--- you know, the--- there was the Vietnam War, and there was a lot of inequality. So those were the reasons.
Cole: Okay, yeah. And so once you got to UConn--- once you--- once you got there, you moved in with some friends? What was that like?
Ellen: Oh, it was--- you know, we were into yoga. We were into smoking dope. We cooked together. You know, we--- it was--- it was fun, for a while. It was--- it was fun. I like living with people, a lot of people. I've done that a bunch of diff--- another couple times in my life. And that was--- there was a woman there that I was really close to, and I really liked her a lot. So I kind of just found her way of doing things, you know, the yoga that she was doing, and the cooking, and the stuff, really kind of appealing as a way of life that I kind of liked.
Cole: Yeah, tell me a little bit more about her.
Ellen: Her name was Denette. And, I mean I wore, you know, typical hippie clothes at that point, long dresses and beads and stuff. Made a lot of my own clothes. She was into this Kundalini Yoga that I--- I got into too, and did--- and she was with a boyfriend, I guess, a man--- her partner at that point. And so the three of us were very much involved in going to classes every night in Hartford, being part of the as--- I can't remember what they called it. The ashram. The ashram, doing things with that group of people. I actually hitchhiked with them out to Colorado to go to a yogi convention out there, up in the mountains.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Which I think I probably had a breakdown at, actually. (laughing)
Cole: Really?
Ellen: Well, it was a long hitchhike, right? From Hartford to Colorado. And I was hitchhiking with a couple. So we would get picked up by a lot of truck drivers. And they all pretty much assumed that I was fair game, you know, that--- and so it was a little stressful getting out there, although nothing ever really happened, it was just kind of always pushing people away and just---
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: And when we got out there, we were way--- we--- they--- you had to get picked up by this Kundalini yoga group from wherever we were and then taken up into these hills because you couldn't--- you couldn't get there any other way. And there was no--- it was a silent retreat. So there was no talking.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: So you were camping out in the woods. And I--- I think I must have had my own tent and Bob and Denette were in their tent. And you would wake up about three in the morning, and you know, start doing yogi things, chanting, and--- and you'd take a dip in an ice cold brook to get yourself cleaned up. And you couldn't speak, you know, the whole time. So it was--- it was a lot of intense yoga and chanting together and alone time and after about three days of it, I was like, I want to go home. (laughing)
Cole: So what did you do? Did you--- did you go home by yourself?
Ellen: Well, the story is--- you co--- there was no phone there. And there were--- weren't cell phones at that point, so--- and you couldn't leave the mountain. You couldn't get off the mountain by yourself, really, it was a long way. So and you had to ask the people, the yoga--- the yogi, this Yogi Bhajan. If you--- he recently passed away, I think, but if you ever look at a picture of him online, he's a pretty imposing person. So you had to go to his little groupies in this house, because they all got to stay in the nice house, of course. And you had to ask for permission to leave.
Cole: Mm.
Ellen: And, I had to like, have a--- an audience with him.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: And--- and you had to get permission to use the phone inside the house. So I got permission to use the phone, and my parents said they would pay for me to fly home.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Rather than hitch home alone, which was nice of them. And this Yogi talked to me and he said that you shouldn't--- "You shouldn't go, my daughter," he said. He said, you know, "You are meant to follow me. And, you know, how do you think you're going to get home?" And I said, well, I think I'm going to go on an airplane. He said, "Well, what makes you think the airplane is going to make it?" I mean, he was pretty imposing and pretty terrifying.
Ellen: So he wanted me to stay. He wanted me to be one of his little minions and followers. And I left anyway.
Cole: What did your parents think about this? Did they know that you were hitchhiking there?
Ellen: Yeah, they weren't real happy.
Cole: Yeah. And so when you called them and said, I want to--- I want to come home, what were they--- what did they say?
Ellen: They were very gracious. I mean, I--- I think it was probably my mom that was the more gracious and convinced my dad to let me come home.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: Yeah. And who knows, you know? Who knows? I mean, if I stayed, I probably would have been fine. And I came home and I was fine. You know?
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: If--- but a little flipped, I would say.
Cole: And so you came home--- what about the rest of your time at UConn? How--- how long were you there?
Ellen: Well, I--- I lived with this guy Jeff for a while. And my father told me he was going to disown me.
Cole: Because---
Ellen: And---
Cole: ---Jeff was not Jewish.
Ellen: Jeff was not Jewish, and I was young. I was under 21.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: And--- and he said he would disown me, and he forbid my mom to come see me. We lived in Hartford. You know, he--- I moved in with him with Denette and Bob. And then he and I moved out into another house with another bunch of people. And my mom would come see me anyway. You know, she would--- I don't know if she didn't tell him or--- I think she didn't tell him.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Yeah.
Cole: What was your relationship with your dad like?
Ellen: Oof. I think it--- it was really, really good, or I felt it was good, until I became a teenager. And then I think he just didn't know how to handle me. I mean, I didn't know how to handle myself, like what teenager does, you know? And he did what he thought was right, but he was very--- he was very strict. You know, we couldn't take--- we had to eat dinner together every night. You know, we all had to sit at the table till everybody was done. We couldn't get phone calls between five and seven, that was family time. He was just pretty strict. He had a lot of rules and regulations that you kind of had to follow.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Once I went to college, I was not real interested in following his rules and regulations anymore. You know, it was kind of an eye opener, like, there are lots of rules and regulations out there, and there are people that don't have any. So, I think I get to make up my mind about some of these.
Ellen: And I went a little crazy--- wild. I mean, I must say that I--- I'm lucky. There are some times--- I did some things, hitchhiking around by myself, and you know, that were very unsafe. And I was lucky that I survived them.
Cole: Hmm. Yeah.
Ellen: I did a lot of hitching by myself.
Cole: Where would you go? Other than other than the mountains of Colorado?
Ellen: Just to get places, you know? Like, if I--- I lived in Hartford, and I wanted to go visit somebody who was somewhere else I would just hitch, or--- I'm trying to think if I lived somewhere else, and I had to get to work, I would hitch. Or sometimes I would just like, hitch just to go somewhere? Just to take a ride, you know?
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: Yeah. Not something--- I mean, I hope Aunty Liz didn't do that, but who knows?
Cole: And so---
Ellen: She might have. (laughs)
Cole: Yeah, yeah. At this point in time, you were living--- you were living with Jeff, what happened next?
Ellen: We got married.
Cole: Really?
Ellen: We eloped. We eloped to his--- to his great aunt's and--- great aunt's house in New York, where you could be married if you were under 21.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: And we had a little--- we had a service there. And we came back and I told my parents I was married. Because then my dad wouldn't disown me, right?
Cole: How did they react?
Ellen: Again, they were gracious. And they bought us a car because we didn't have a car. So they bought us a used station wagon and they actually had a party for us with all their friends. So I think they were very--- and they welcomed him into the family.
Cole: Yeah, even though he wasn't Jewish.
Ellen: Mm hmm. Even though he wasn't Jewish. Yep. Yep.
Cole: So you were still---
Ellen: Yep, it---
Cole: ---at UConn at the time, right?
Ellen: I was still at UConn, yep. And then Jeff and I moved out thi--- to this area, kind of, to a town about 20 minutes away from UConn. And we rented a house on a lake. And we got two roommates. And I continued on--- we both--- he was in school, too. We both continued on in school. And I switched my major, I think to philosophy. I was polit--- I was--- I wanted to be a teacher when I went to Leslie, and then it was political science, and then philosophy, and--- and then I kind of just started taking like three courses instead of four, and two instead of three. And I ended up dropping out---
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: ---of school and just working.
Cole: Did you--- did you ever go back to school?
Ellen: Yeah. Oh, yeah. Yep, I went--- I went back to school when--- so, I met your grandpa, right? Reid. When Jeff and I were--- we had saved up money and we were going to go to California, and then that fell through. He didn't want to go for some reason. And we moved back to this area, around here [Windham, Connecticut], and lived in a house right up the road from me now, in--- with a bunch of people and had like a farm. And I started to drive school bus and then I met Reid. Or Rusty. And the--- and then I wanted to get divorced, or not be with Jeff anymore. So he ended up going to California by himself. And I ended up with Reid.
Cole: Yeah. So during this time period, you said that you weren't going to synagogue. Were you otherwise involved in a Jewish community at any point?
Ellen: No. Nope, not at that point, that--- you know, we had a--- we had a community of people that lived--- we lived with a--- in a community.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: And that was kind of I guess my community.
Ellen: I probably would never have even, at that point, thought of joining a synagogue. Yeah.
Cole: And---
Ellen: So.
Cole: Oh, sorry.
Ellen: No, that's okay.
Cole: Tell me about--- tell me about Reid. You met him, you you ended up marrying him at some point? How did that happen? And what happened after?
Ellen: So, I got pregnant with your dad pretty quickly. And he was--- Reid was finishing school as an engineer. And shortly after your dad was born, and I think it was--- I don't know. I mean, a side, of--- of Reid came out that I had not known, and had not seen, and was a little frightened of. I guess--- you know, he was also very kind of straight. Things were his way or not. We had different child-rearing thoughts. And he was physically abusive.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: So--- so. After, I think about almost two years, we split up. And--- and I went back to school.
Cole: And so you--- you went back to school at UConn still?
Ellen: Yep.
Cole: And you finished a degree in?
Ellen: Child development and family relations.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: Yep. And so---
Cole: What made you choose that?
Ellen: I guess going back to, you know, originally, I had wanted to be a teacher. And I really liked--- you know, I loved having your dad and I loved being a mom, and I love learning about babies. And that program just seemed more interesting to me, with the human development side of it, and the family constellation side of it than specifically being a teacher, I guess. I think it--- there was also a push at that point to--- to do headstart, and to have a lot of childcare, you know, infant care, preschool things. So that was what my degree was in, you know. I would have been able to run a--- a daycare center, a--- a large center.
Cole: Yeah, yeah.
So--- so yeah, moved a couple times, you know, with your dad. He and I had one really nice kind of older apartment in a--- in a house with a fam--- another family upstairs. And then we moved into a little house that Gampy calls the hovel. It was a little kind of house on its own. It had a wood stove, and I just--- I loved it. I felt very independent there, you know, taking care of your dad. And weirdly enough, Reid moved to the same block. Bought a house and was on the same block. So at that point, your dad would go to your--- your grandpa's for a week and then be with me for a week.
Cole: "Weirdly enough?" Do you think it was a coincidence?
Ellen: (long pause) Probably not. I don't know.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: I don't know. I don't know--- you know, I don't understand that man. And I don't understand, you know, the things that he did and the things that he said. I mean, he said some very anti-Semitic things to me.
Ellen: So, I don't know. I mean, it was the second time that he did it, so, probably, it was, yes. But.
Cole: And so--- how did you meet Gampy, and when did you meet him?
Ellen: Let's see. Your dad was born in [19]75. And I met Gampy I think in 78. I was in school. I was in that human development and family relations. It has its own separate, kind of, you know, building--- its own separate school. UConn's huge, but it--- their building was also big, but small compared to the whole thing. So I had a lot of classes in there. And he was a graduate student in there as well. He was getting a degree in marriage and family therapy. He was working on his master's. And so there was a--- a big, like lounge that had, you know, coffee machine and stuff like that, and chairs to sit in. And I would--- when I--- when your dad would be in--- in daycare, you know, I would sit and study and do all my work while he was in school, if I didn't--- you know, during my classes, so. And Gampy would come there,too, you know, and he--- he had, you know, his little Irish cap, and his little Irish sports jacket, and a briefcase that his parents bought him. He was adorable. Anyway, so we just became friends, we would talk a lot.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: We were good friends. You know, I enjoyed his sense of humor. He was really funny. He was really smart. I thought he was adorable. And it was just nice to have, you know, somebody to talk to him.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: So that's how we met. And, yeah.
Cole: So you said earlier that--- that you--- you stopped going to synagogue when you were 14 or so---
Ellen: Yep.
Cole: --- after you switched, and you didn't pick it up again at any point, you didn't go back ever, until you had met Gabby. Was that--- was that much later after this? Or was that still when my dad was a baby or young?
Ellen: It was much later after that.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: So your--- Reid would take--- after we--- we had to go to court to get a custody agreement. And it was joint custody, but it wasn't the week and a week anymore. He would live with me and see Reid every other weekend. Because Reid lived in Norwich. I mean, he lived like half an hour away. And--- and we at that point lived in--- well, right around here. So there was kind of, he'd have to go to two different schools, I mean, it wasn't like your mom and dad managed to work things out amicably.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: So, at that point, Reid would take your dad to his church. He is an evangelical Christian. And he would send him to camp, you know, when he would have him on vacation, he would send me to a evangelical camp. Which, your dad, I believe, liked. And once Gampy and I had Luke, and Liz, we s--- oh I--- and, there was--- I had forgotten about this, but there was a--- a really good--- a good friend of ours, they were a couple, and she used to watch Lucas after--- after school. And she got cancer, and she died. And I remember going to her church service with Gampy. And feeling such a strong community support for that family. And talking to Gampy later and saying that I want that. You know, I miss that in my life, and I want that. So we kind of did investigation in terms of where to go. You know, I think we went to--- I think I went to a Quaker meeting, and a Unitarian thing. Gampy was brought up Catholic and had no desire to do that. He really does not like the Catholic Church at all.
Cole: Hmm.
Ellen: And, you know, we then found this little interfaith conservative synagogue in Hebron. And I was willing to make the effort to bring Luke there and--- and Liz. And to get involved. And Gampy was willing to let me do it. You know, he felt like, yes, it would be really nice to give our kids something. Some faith that they can do what they want with, you know.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: That sometimes it--- it really helps people, and sometimes people find it gives them strength. And sometimes they don't want it, but we wanted them to have something to turn against or embrace.
Cole: Mm hmm. And so you brought Uncle Lukey and Aunty Liz there, but not my dad.
Ellen: No, because your dad was going--- number one, he was--- Uncle Lukey was already a little bit past the age that we should have started him, like in Hebrew school and learning all this stuff?
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: So he was already a little bit uncomfortable with that. So we probably--- I think it starts around, you know, first grade, or kindergarten. So if Aunty Liz was five, then Uncle Lukey was nine. So he started like when he was nine. Yep. And your dad was 16.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: So number one, he was working. And he was having to go to his dad's every other weekend, and it--- It wasn't like there was a Sunday school class for a 16 year old, you know?
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: So. So we did not--- I mean, and--- I didn't think that it would be good to bring him there as well as having him go to church. I thought it would be really confusing. I don't know if that was the right thing or the wrong thing. And maybe my years are a little off. Maybe he was 15. But it was hard enough to get Reid to allow your dad to participate in other things that were in his life if they were on a weekend that he was supposed to be with him. And the thought of trying to do that with synagogue as well for things just seemed impossible.
Ellen: To me. I mean, it was always painful. It was never--- it was never easy.
Cole: Mm hmm. Alright, let's rewind a little bit and talk about, I guess, like another side of your life after college, which is working.
Ellen: Yep.
Cole: Your first job, it seemed like, was back in high school?
Cole: Maybe even back in middle school. But what did you do after you graduated from UConn?
Ellen: I started applying for jobs. And I got two job offers. One was to be the head of a fairly large daycare center in the Norwich area, I believe it was, and it was for 9,000 dollars a year. And one was at Aetna insurance company to be a coder for 11,000 dollars--- 11,000 a year. And I had been, you know, with your dad alone, and we'd been on food stamps, you know? And I wanted to be able to take care of him, so I took the tech job, the--- well, it wasn't tech at that point. I took the Aetna job.
Cole: What does coding mean? You said to be a coder.
Ellen: Oh, it was weird, Coley. It was--- you had to take information--- I mean, computers were main--- you know, mainframes and data--- data cards, data punch cards. So you had to take documents that an insurance agent would fill out for someone and you had to take that information and transpose it on a worksheet that had, you know, data that somebody was going to then take and key punch in for the cards. So that was it. I mean, it was pretty weird.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: I got the job--- because I had no business classes or background or anything, but I did do some research with a professor and I--- you know, I watched kids in daycare centers interact and had to code their actions and stuff. So when I put that on my application, that's what they picked up on.
Cole: How much money was 11,000 dollars to you at the time?
Ellen: It was amazing. It was a lot of money. And at that point, because--- and I can remember this to this day, be--- I had--- the car I had was a piece of trash.
Cole: Still the same one that your parents gave you?
Ellen: No, no, no, I had an--- an old Volvo, that didn't break very well and didn't start all the time. And so, I--- there was no way I could drive that into Hartford and back every day because I was living out here. So I went to a local dealer and bought a new car, you know. Bought a little Chevy Chevette and they--- and they gave me the--- the loan, whatever, because I have this job at this insurance company. It was pretty amazing. The car was called Jennifer Francis. Ask--- if you ask your dad about Jennifer Francis, he'll remember.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: Yeah. (chuckles)
Cole: What did you--- so you had this job at Aetna. What happened next? Did you--- did you--- well, first of all, did you like the job?
Ellen: Yeah. I mean, I liked the money.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: You know, it was--- to be able to take care of your dad. And--- and--- and myself was empowering. You know, I had always had jobs. I drove a school bus. I did this. I did that, you know? But this was like, my first real salaried, good job.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: And so I get--- through my whole work life, I got bored fairly quickly and moved on from there to doing some testing, I think? Like I met--- there was a woman who was there. And she was kind of in the space where--- she was doing testing for new projects. And somehow I helped her do some testing, and then she was in charge of a new project. So I moved off and did that for a while. And then I moved into another area that was a business area. Moved around a lot. But I ended up moving into data processing. At one point, I had gone--- you know, moved up from the 11,000, and I was making, I think it was 25,000, maybe. And they were starting, or maybe it was 18. I don't know, I can't remember. But they were starting a data processing class for people who wanted it, and--- you know, to become a COBOL programmer. And so I took a huge--- a big pay cut, about a 10,000 dollar pay cut. I think I was making 28 and I--- and then I made 18,000 to get into that class. Or, I was making 18,000 when I got into that class. I had to take a pay cut to get into the class, but I did that. And then I was in IT.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: For the rest.
Cole: How did you end up at the Hartford?
Ellen: Aetna moved p--- they moved their--- a big data area out to Middletown, which was X number miles away. And they provided a package to people who were over that--- like if you were over 30 miles from them, and you would stay for as long as it took for them to find somebody to replace you, then they would give you some type of package. So I took it, and I think Aunty Leese, at that point, was working at the Hartford as a--- a writer. And, anyway, I moved over there.
Cole: When was that in relation to--- I don't know, to the rest of your life? Like how old was my dad? What about your--- Uncle Lukey and Aunty Liz?
Ellen: Oh, well--- they were all older. They were--- Uncle Lukey was born. Uncle Luke probably--- he was probably about three or four. It was before I had Auntie Liz, so he was probably about three when I moved over there.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: So he was born in [19]82, (pause) 83, 84--- like, 85.
Cole: Interesting. And then you worked at the Hartford, still in IT---
Ellen: Mm hmm.
Cole: ---for--- for how long?
Ellen: Until I retired in--- let's see. I don't know, when did I--- when did I retire? Hmm. Let's see. I've been a nurse for seven, eight, nine years. So nine years ago? Maybe nine--- nine, ten years ago?
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Went to nursing school right after.
Cole: What made you go to nursing school right after you retired?
Ellen: Because I wanted another career where I actually felt like I was doing something other than making some decent money.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: I mean, the things I liked about where I worked was usually helping people once I got into management. You know, I really enjoyed mentoring people and helping to promote people and helping them find what they like to do there. But it was a job, not a mission, not a--- you know. It was to make money for our family.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: You know, Gampy had his own business, and it--- it struggled. And then there was the whole thing with the bankruptcy that we had that was, you know, pretty horrible.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Did you ever know that?
Cole: No, talk about that a little bit more.
Ellen: Gampy, always--- you know, he had an IT company. He did a lot of small business stuff, nonprofit stuff. Sold computers, did software development, created a video store system. You know, this was before--- vi--- even before--- yeah. And he always wanted to open a data center. So, you know, he put plans together and got funding. And I think it was two days before--- hey Kev?! He's sleeping up there. Anyway, we took out huge--- a big loan, over a million dollars from a bank. And, you know, I can remember being in this big bank in--- in Hartford and overlooking the whole valley and signing all these things. And so he got money to put together a data center. And then--- could it have been--- yeah, I think it was--- and then a couple days later, 9/11 happened.
Cole: Wow.
Ellen: And the economy went crazy. Anyway, Gampy put together the data center. And, it was beau--- it was really cool. I mean, it was in the old mills in Willimantic. It was very neat, you know, state of the art. He really had some good people working on it with him. And he really, he did know--- he knew exactly what he was doing. It was the time when John Rowland was a governor of Hartford, who was put in jail afterwards. You know, a lot of the things that he did was give contracts to his cronies. And so there was part of the data center, the whole backup thing, and if Gampy was awake, I could get you exactly what it was, that had to be set up completely for the generator and everything. And he had a company that he wanted to have do it. And John Rowland, because they were--- they had control of some of the money for this wouldn't let that company do it. So another company got the rights to do it, and the guy who was running the mills was holding the money. Anyway, it wasn't done correctly. And we had a big storm here. And the generator didn't come up.
Cole: Mm.
Ellen: So you can't have a data center without people being secured, that you're back--- that their backups, or that they're going to be able to keep going.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: So anyway, he struggled for a number of years after that, and then we finally ju--- his--- the company went bankrupt.
Cole: Mm.
Ellen: So that was hard.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Then again, at the same time, I was traveling to India. I went to India twice with the Hartford, because it was just--- we were starting to do this sourcing there and to look at other places, and I can remember being really upset about the possibility of going bankrupt, and you know, maybe losing our house and everything. And then being in India and seeing women and children living under bridges, in sewage, and just kind of like feeling like I wanted to slap myself, you know? And say, Ellen, what the heck are you upset about? You know, you've got your--- you've got your health, you've got your family, you've--- you know, I had my job, but didn't--- do anything to my job. You know, you can--- if you lose your house, you lose your house, you know? You go live in a rental apartment. Who cares? So it was a--- it was a good lesson in humility. And I think what's important. Yeah. Anyway. I also had that with the cancer scare that I had too.
Cole: Yeah, want to talk about that a little bit?
Ellen: Yeah, it was when your dad was 18, and just getting ready to go away to college. And I had had a mole here that my family doctor kept saying, "You really ought to take care of," and every time I'd make an appointment--- you know, I was moving up in--- in work and getting to be director, getting to--- close to a vice president level. And there's just always something, you know? Another meeting, I had to go to a big conference, a this, a that. So I finally made time to get it done. It was right before Christmas. And like, two days later, the doctor called back and said, "You know, it is--- it's a stage three melanoma. It's very close to a stage four. You need to get it taken care of right away." So we went to a doctor in--- in Hartford who basically told me to get my life together. And that--- and that was pretty terrifying.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Yeah. I mean, it was--- it was a really--- you know, I mean, anytime you hear that, it's terrifying. It was a time that what, like your dad was applying to colleges. And, you know, I didn't know if I was going to be alive to help pay for him to go to college. And I was the main breadearner.
Ellen: You know, in the family. I mean, that just worked out. You know, Gampy would do--- he ran his own business, he could take the ki--- all of the kids to work with him if they were sick. You know, they all remember playing at the mills and being at Gray Wolf [the business], and, you know, doing their sick days there and stuff like that. So.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: You know, it was a choice that we made, and it was a fine choice. But the thought of not having that was pretty terrifying.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Yeah.
Cole: What--- so you said that one of the--- you want to be able to pay for my dad's college?
Ellen: Mm hmm.
Cole: What was your relationship to my dad's education? Did you have expectations for him?
Ellen: Yep. Oh, yeah. I mean, he--- he applied to a number of good schools. He applied to, you know, Trinity and Clark, which he loved. He really wanted to go to Clark. And UConn. You know, your dad was pretty strong willed at that point, as--- like I was at that point. And he kind of wanted to manage the things himself. His dad would not complete any paperwork to help--- he wouldn't help pay for college, and he wouldn't complete any paperwork for that. So, he got into Clark. He got into Trinity. He got into UConn honors program. And we could not afford Clark.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: You know, we had two other kids. And we were not sure that I was still going to--- I was going to be around. He--- I think he was on the waitlist at Trinity, and then he got in, and they called his high school. And they talked to his guidance counselor at the high school who called him in, not us. And your dad said he didn't want to talk to Trinity. He didn't want to go there.
Cole: Interesting.
Ellen: Yeah. And so he--- you know, he went to UConn in the Honors Program for--- for one semester. You know, we got him--- the same thing. He lived on campus. We bought all this stuff. We brought him up there. You know, Liz was--- Aunty Liz was a wreck. Because she--- you know, she--- she really loved your dad--- loved Gabe. And she was just crying and crying when he left. And you know, she and I would go up like to bring cookies or stuff like that. She loved going up there to see him.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: So yeah. Then they asked him to not come back.
Cole: Yeah. How--- what did you feel about that?
Ellen: I was really worried. Like, I didn't know what was going on with your dad at that point.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: I mean, he had been--- he's an excellent student. You know, he's brilliant. He really is. He--- and he had a mind--- I mean, your grandpa on the other side also was like that. You know, he can just read a book and remember things. So I don't think he ever really had to study a whole lot in high school. And he was kind of feeling his oats in high school, too. But yeah, I was really worried about him. I--- I didn't know what was up, you know?
Cole: Mm hmm. What about for your other children? What did you do educationally for them? And what were your expectations for them? Whether they same as the ones for my father?
Ellen: Yep, it was always, you know--- well, I mean, I think the thought was, we felt like college was important. That you go to college. You're not going to know what you--- you don't need to know what you want to do. You know, we have to be able to afford it. You'll find out what you want to do. But you will learn how to study and how to think kind of logically more. So the expectation was always--- you know, it was different for each child. Uncle Lukey was not a good student.
Cole: Mm.
Ellen: You know, your dad was an excellent student. Uncle Lukey struggled.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: Interestingly, now he's the one with his doctrine, right?
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: But he was probably a C, B student, all the way through. Did not have a lot of self-confidence at all, in junior high school or in high school. You know, our--- the grad--- the school in Columbia was a K-8. And, at that time, there was the--- the--- the program for the--- all the smart kids, you know, the--- what's it called?
Cole: Like a gifted program?
Ellen: Yeah, the gifted program. And I can remember driving Uncle Lukey to school one day, and there was a big bus there. You know, he says, "Oh, that's--- that bus is ready to take all the smart kids. Yhey're going, you know, into the state capital. And to do this." He says, "All--- and all, the dumb kids have to stay home. Stay back here." So he--- he really felt that, you know, he felt like he wasn't smart. He--- he--- I don't think he would have gone to college unless we pushed him.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: You know, the expectation was, you're going to go somewhere. And he was--- you know, he really had a hard time with math. So that was hard for him. You know, he always--- he was--- he would get extra help in math. We had tutors for him---
Ellen: ---in math for a long time. And, yeah, so I think col--- yeah, so the expectation was that he would go to college and he applied to a bunch of schools. He got into some, he didn't get into--- he didn't get into his first choice, which was St. A's, St. Anselm's.
Cole: Mm.
Ellen: He really wanted to go there, and didn't get in. But Roger Williams was a--- a good school for him.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Hated it--- hated going there. On the ride there the first day, "I don't want to go, this is stupid. I hate this place." And I--- we just said you're going to do a year here. You know, you're not coming home. You're not dropping out. You're doing a year. And Uncle Lukey--- was the kind of kid who just said, "Okay," you know? "I'll do what you say." Like if I--- we told your dad that he, you know--- God knows what he would have done. He wouldn't have listened. He would have done what he wanted. Uncle Lukey did what we wanted. You know, he didn't care that much, I guess.
Cole: What about---
Ellen: So, yeah.
Cole: ---Aunty Liz.
Ellen: Aunty Liz was very kind of politically active all the way through, you know, school. She was always looking out for the kids who didn't have, or--- you know, she--- she was like a mentor to an autistic young man in--- in that K-8 school. She always was interested in, you know, books to peace, and doing this, and doing that. So--- and then, when she was about 13, interestingly, she kind of had a little bit of a switch, and I think she hung out with a group of kids and I think they got into drinking and stuff. So she had--- she had seen that--- Loomis Chafee, that private school, because she had played soccer there. And she really wanted to go to private school for--- for high school. Which I think she says now probably saved her life. I mean, I don't know exactly what she was into. Maybe I'll find out someday, she'll tell me. But I think she was in with a group of kids. And actually, there is this one little story, and that she would go to Loomis during the day. She lived, you know, with us. I would drive her, drop her off. I would go to work, and then I'd pick her up at the end of the day. I was always late because I always had some meeting to go to. She said the janitor was her best friend because she was always hanging out with the janitor. And she always wanted to hang out with her home friends on school nights. You know, and it would--- we would always--- it was always a big fight. And Nancy, Aunt Nancy--- like I talked to her about it. And she said, "Why don't we come up with a contract? You know, you and Liz come up with some kind of contract," where she will stay home on--- on school nights. Unless, you know--- and if she--- but if she gets A's in her classes, then she'll be able to--- whatever. So we sign--- we made up this contract. Aunt Nanny made it up and we signed it. And one night, some of her high school friends in town went to Eastern, the college that's right here. And they must have--- they were drinking. And a guy that she was dating was there. And they came back and there was a horrible car crash. And he--- he ended up passing away.
Cole: Oh my goodness.
Ellen: He was--- yeah, it was--- he was in a coma for probably about six months. And then he died. So I remember when--- when Aunty Liz went to college. She went to the facility where he was and said goodbye to her, and it was so--- really sad.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: But anyway. (ringtone) Oh, let me just tell Uncle Lukey I'll call him back.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: Hi, honey. Luke?
Luke: Hi.
Ellen: Hi, I'm just talking to Coley.
Luke: Oh cool, call me back later then.
Ellen: Okay, babe.
Luke: Bye.
Ellen: Bye.
Cole: So---
Ellen: Yeah, so--- I think she would have gone in that group of kids, except she had some average she had to keep up in a class and---
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Yeah. Anyway.
Cole: At these two high schools, were there a lot of other Jewish students?
Ellen: No.
Cole: No.
Ellen: Nope, Gabe went to Windham High School, that was in Windham. Kind of a--- you know, a more socially diverse and economically diverse town. Not a lot of Jewish kids there. Lucas went to Lyman High School, which was in Lebanon, which is way more, just, you know, farm, white. And Liz went to Loomis, which probably had more--- had more diversity. They had a lot of international students. And scholarship students and stuff. But not big on the Jewish students. And neither of them, after their bar and bar mitzvahs, were interested in going to synagogue again.
Cole: Really?
Ellen: Lucas--- Lucas did a little bit.
Cole: So we went up until they were about 13 or so and then they stopped?
Ellen: Yep. Actually, Lucas would still go. He had a friend who was Jewish. And there was a really small little synagogue, I don't know if you remember when--- you don't, but when we lived in--- in Colombia, there was a little---
Cole: I do remember this.
Ellen: You do?
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: This little synagogue and they would have high holiday services there with a very old Russian rabbi and Uncle Lukey would go with his friend to that.
Cole: Mm.
Ellen: And Uncle Lukey did the--- you know, the birthright trip.
Cole: Mm. When did he do that? At what age?
Ellen: I think it was in one of the college summers.
Cole: Okay.
Ellen: Yep. Or aft--- yeah. One of the college summers.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: I think. Yeah. Aunty Liz never wanted to do that.
Ellen: I mean, the fact that Aunty Liz wanted to get married by a rabbi was a total shock to me.
Cole: Really?
Ellen: Yeah.
Cole: When you had gotten married in the past, had you done a similar thing?
Ellen: When Gampy and I were married?
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: No, we got married by a justice of the peace.
Cole: Okay. This is maybe an abstract question, but do you consider yourself to be Jewish?
Ellen: Yes.
Cole: How? In which ways?
Ellen: Oh, how. I think it's just part of how I feel about myself. Why would that be? I don't know. But if I was--- you know, if I was to describe myself, I would say that I was a Jewish woman.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Yeah. I mean, I've been attracted to other religions too. But never felt like I could not be Jewish. I don't know if that sounds weird. I also have a really strong pull and fascination about the Holocaust. And that whole time, and thinking, what would I have done? If I had been born in that time?
Cole: Mm.
Ellen: You know, I--- every--- I watch a lot of movies about it, and I read books. You know, I just kind of find it compelling, I guess.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: And how would I have acted, you know. Because it's--- I could have been.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: You know.
Cole: Does--- so your--- do you consider your parents Jewish?
Ellen: Yes.
Cole: Yeah. Does their being Jewish influence how you feel about yourself being Jewish? (pause) Or I guess if I were to rephrase that, you said you would never really consider yourself not Jewish, even though you've been attracted to other religions? Is that linked to your parents being Jewish?
Ellen: Probably, Cole. Probably. I mean, it's a shared set of values and tradition that I always felt was important to keep that thread. Whatever it was. You know, I mean, the fact that when your dad was having a hard time after their divorce, that he would go to synagogue. You know, I mean, I don't know why that meant something to him, you know? But it did.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: And, you know, the times that I went with you guys there. The fact that Lucas is--- and Ashlyn [his wife] are bringing the kids up Jewish. The fact that Lucas feels like he's Jewish, the fact that Liz wanted to get married by a rabbi. When I was out there, you know, she wanted to light the Friday night candles. Like, I don't know what it is exactly. But there's something comforting about this kind of long, golden thread that kind of ties me--- you know, that I could go anywhere in the world to a synagogue. And if they were speaking Hebrew in that synagogue, which most--- you know, a lot of them do, I would feel at home. That---
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: ---I mean, I've gone--- yeah, it's--- I've gone to a synagogue in Harlem and felt at home, you know?
Cole: Mm hmm. Kind of a connected question--- do you consider yourself white?
Ellen: Yeah, unfortunately. (laughing)
Cole: How does your Jewish identity interact with your white identity? Or, I don't know about id--- identity, but.
Ellen: I don't know that I have a white identity? I thi--- I mean, I think I have, you know, unfortunately, a white sense of privilege. You know, I never--- I know, the things that have been offered to me that have not been offered to other people because of the color of their skin.
Cole: Mm.
Ellen: And I know the--- the guilt I feel because of that, you know. How unfair it is. I don't know exactly--- you know, there's nothing I can do about what was offered to me and not offered to--- to them.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: But have a very strong sense of the--- of the wrongness of that. And the fact that, I mean, there's a--- the thing in--- in Judaism about, you know, healing the world. And I think that that is a strong part of I--- who I've always been. You know, like Liz, I always felt for the underdog and, you know, would never make fun of people. Knowingly, you know. Was never that kind of kid that would--- that would do that. I would want to make somebody feel comfortable, and whatever.
Cole: Yeah. You said at one point that Reid said anti-Semitic things. And one of the questions that I sent you was how have you experienced anti-Semitism?
Ellen: Yeah. So, you know, there are--- there are the--- the kind of comments that people make, like--- you know, they're just trying to Jew you down. Right, have you--- I don't know if you've heard that one. Which, you know, Jewish people, stereotypically, are very close with their money or cheap. So, you know, it's used--- and like, you're trying to cheat somebody. You're trying to--- so I've heard that, that's--- you know, I find that pretty offensive. The thoughts--- the things that people say, "Oh, you don't look Jewish." Which is ridiculous, because Judaism is a religion.
Cole: Mm.
Ellen: I mean, it is a religion, it is not a nationality. It is not a race. You know, there are all kinds of Jews from all kinds of places. You know, I've had--- I had a high school boyfriend who called me a dirty Jew when he broke up with me. (laughs) And I slapped him across the face. (laughing) Which I'm not really proud of, but I can remember where I was when I did it. You know, people who--- who, "Oh, you're Jewish." That kind of thing? Yeah.
Cole: Do you ever think you were treated differently at school or in work because of it?
Ellen: No, because--- because actually, I think that people just didn't know--- wouldn't know. You know, wasn't--- definitely not in school. I can't--- you know, not--- not growing up. Not in college--- in the colleges that I've gone to. Not the other things that I've done. Not nursing school, not in--- you know, I did a project management program at the Hartford, I did an object-oriented program--- programming program at the Hartford. I mean, all the diff--- did a business mastery program. You know, all of the other kind of certifications that I did, I never felt that. No.
Cole: Yeah. Okay, interesting. In the 1920s. I'm not sure if you--- you mentioned that your--- your grandfather thought he might--- or sorry, your father thought that he might not have gotten into West---
Ellen: West Point.
Cole: ---because he was Jewish. Actually I'll ask you about that first. What--- was that something that he said often? Was that something that came up a lot?
Ellen: No, not a lot, but--- but it did come up.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: You know, if like you talked to him about his life or something. I think he probably experienced it more than I did.
Cole: Anti-Semitism?
Ellen: Yeah.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: I think he and my mom proba--- probably did. You know, and him especially in the business world.
Cole: Hmm. So in the 1920s, in response to soaring Jewish enrollments, many prestigious colleges in the northeast, like Harvard and Yale, instituted enrollment quotas that were highly effective at keeping most Jews out of their student bodies. How do you feel about that? About that type of thing?
Ellen: I mean, I think it was wrong, you know, obviously. Anytime you--- you know, I can remember--- you know, there was a country club in Wethersfield that--- that I remember my parents saying, well, not only could we not afford it, but they wouldn't let Jewish people in. You know, anytime you do anything like that against a people and not a person because of something that they did, it's wrong.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Yeah.
Cole: So we're gonna go back a little bit in time now. I'm bouncing all over the place now that---
Ellen: It's okay, Cole. It's fine.
Cole: ---we've gotten through the bulk of your life, it seems like. What do you know about your--- your grandparents? I know you talked about your grandfather on your dad's side a little bit. What about your grandmother on your dad's side?
Ellen: I don't know that much about her past. Except that she--- I mean, I do have a family tree that I could show, you know, send to you if you wanted to see it. I knew she--- she grew up in Brooklyn. She had a bunch of brothers and sisters, and she married my grandfather. You know, that's kind of all I know. And they were--- they were active in their synagogue. And she was very active with her family.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: And very active and all the Jewish holidays and etcetera. Both my dad and my grandfather were Masons, which I think is kind of strange.
Cole: Were Masons, as an Freemasons?
Ellen: Yeah, as an Freemasons.
Cole: Okay---
Ellen: I don't quite get that.
Cole: ---why do you think that's strange?
Ellen: Huh? I thought that--- I thought that Freemasons was like a kind of Cath--- Catholic thing. I never--- I mean, obviously, they can't tell you, it's all secret, right? So you could never learn anything. But I just found it odd that they had Jewish people in it, that they let Jewish people in it.
Cole: Interesting. When you were younger, you--- you saw your grandparents every week, you said. Was that your dad's grandparents and your mom's grand--- or sorry, your dad's parents and your mom's parents?
Ellen: Yep. They both--- we lived close to both of them.
Cole: Yeah. What do you remember about going to your dad's grandparents house, anything in particular?
Ellen: I have great memories of it. It was--- it was a two family house. They lived on the upper floor and they would rent the bottom one to newlyweds or something. It was in Middletown and it had a huge backyard that was very treed and--- old kind of trees and beautiful. In--- in the front hallway, there was a big banister that you could slide down. Big oak, wooden banister. My grandmother had birds. You know, there was no real dining room, we would eat in the big kitchen. She was a really good cook. They had a great attic that you could go explore and look at trunks of old stuff. It was a kind of jolly happy house with a lot of family coming from New York, you know. All the rest of the family lived in New York. Her brothers, and her sisters, and my first cousin. So my dad had a sister, Selma, and her kids, who were all around the same age as us. So, you know, occasionally my grandparents would take me and my older cousins from New York for a sleepover there. So I remember doing that in the room they had--- you know, they had some toys for us when we came that we could play with, and yeah--- and my grandfather was just a gem. He was a--- Harry was just a wonderful man in--- as a grandfather, and I think in his business, you know. He--- he--- he spoke six languages. He came over from--- he lived in Austria and he came over from Poland when he was about 14. He--- and I think it was 1920. He then worked and he brought his next brother over. And then the two of them worked and brought--- so they brought the whole family over, brothers and sisters. His father in Austria had two wives, the--- different times. One died (laughing) and then the other one. So it's a kind of a huge family. Are you part at all--- are you on Facebook at all?
Cole: I am. I don't use it that often.
Ellen: Okay. There is a [...] family Facebook page, which is kind of interesting. Of the Harry [...] brothers and sisters. And the woman that runs it, because I asked her for some information this morning, says if you want to--- you know, you have to get approved to join it. But if you want to join it, and like look at all the stuff there's, you know, pictures and trees and all kinds of interesting stuff out there.
Cole: Oh, thank you. I'll look into that.
Ellen: Yeah. So I have very good memories of my grandparents on my dad's side.
Cole: What about your mom side?
Ellen: My--- my--- I have good memories of them too. My--- my grandfather on my mom's side died fairly young of a heart attack. I think maybe I was like six or seven? Yeah. So I don't have a lot of real memories of him. And my grandma, who was the first baby grandma, lived much longer, you know, until--- I don't know, maybe the 80s, sometime in the 80s, I think? And she was very kind of prim and, you know, hated my dad because he divorced my mom, and--- but she was great. She was also great, you know. The typical Jewish grandmother worrying about everything. Great ba--- great cook, great baker. You know, not particularly kind, you know. Not concerned about others, I don't think. You know, I don't--- yeah.
Cole: Did--- did she work? Did either of your grandmothers work?
Ellen: I don't think so. Not once they got married, no.
Cole: What about your mom?
Ellen: No. No. And that was--- I think that was part of the reason that my dad ended up falling out of love with her. I mean, he--- he was a real estate agent, and he had good times and bad times. And at one point in their marriage, I can remember him saying, you know, you--- I really need you to work, you know. I can't support this family. And she wouldn't do it. You know, she said "No, this is the deal we made. You know, that I will get to stay home," and yeah.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: Yeah.
Cole: When--- how old were you when they got divorced?
Ellen: I was out of the house. So, I was--- I was probably 23? I think I was 22, 23. Yeah, because--- I think I must have been 22--- well, your dad was born in [19]75. And both Grandma and Grandpa got remarried in the same year, and they had been divorced a year.
Cole: So your mom's parents--- do you know anything about their story? They--- how did they end up in Hartford?
Ellen: I really don't. I just think their parents were there. I don't really know where--- I mean--- I mean, they must have come over--- there must have been--- either their parents generation or the one before came over from Europe. So you know, somewhere. My--- my grandma had a brother, Manis, who also would come and see us quite a bit and he was a great bachelor uncle.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: He was wonderful. He would do all kinds of things with us. You know, take us places and always buy me books. And yeah. And they would come over weekly too. So it was very close family.
Cole: Yeah. So now I have a couple of questions about--- kind of like the--- the question about colleges. So I sent these to you as well. But the first one is about Jewish overrepresentation. So, Jews have been historically overrepresented in certain fields, and among kind of high-achieving groups. I think I sent you that they made up 27% of Nobel physics laureates, 21% of Ivy League student bodies and 37% of Oscar-winning directors. Why do you think this is?
Ellen: Why do you th--- I mean, I guess my question to you is, why do you think they chose those fields? Or why--- I mean, is the overrepresentation number based on where they are in the population?
Cole: So, I think--- yeah, that's a good question. Jews are overrepresented in not--- not only these, but also many--- many fields, although not--- not all. I don't--- I don't have all the numbers on that. But they're overrepresented relative to their percentage of the United States population and the world population.
Ellen: So I think--- I think the--- the Jewish re--- I think there's a lot of push in the Jewish religion to study. So, you know, you study for your bar or bat mitzvah. You have to learn Hebrew. You study the Torah. You know, that's--- there's a push to learn and to continually question. And I think that's another thing, and--- and that--- I don't think the Jewish religion--- the Jewish religion as I see it and I know it, and I'm not talking about orthodoxy, because that is totally different--- doesn't define a lot of things, I don't think. It leaves a lot--- I mean, it doesn't say that, you know, you're going to go to heaven, and there is a hell, and if you say this number of Hail Marys, then, you know, you're going to be okay, or whatever. I think it leaves a lot--- and there's no physical representation of what God is. That's a big thing. You know, there's no picture of God. There's no human picture of what God is supposed to be. So I think it leads to a lot of questioning, and it--- you know, Jewish parents, typically--- I mean, all the ones that I knew, anyway, were ve--- all very interested in their childrens' education. And they always--- you know, there was never really a choice for me--- for any of us whether we would go to college or not. Yes, you're going, it's going to be where and what you want to do with it. So I would say in any profe--- in any--- any field that requires education or advanced education, then that would make sense to me that they would be--- there would be a lot of Jewish people in that field. Now, that's--- I mean, Jewish is a religion. You know, it's not--- like if you say Asian Americans, that's different. You know, that's not a religion. Like you have--- you have African Jews, you have Spanish Jews, you know, you've got German Jews, you've got Austrian Jews, you've got Jews in Nigeria, you've got Jews in India. You know, it's--- it's not a nationality, even though Ancestry.com [a DNA testing service] says it is, which is weird, I think.
Cole: So that's--- when you say Ancestry.com says it is, have you taken one of those tests?
Ellen: Mm hmm.
Cole: And what did it report back for you?
Ellen: That I was Jewish. (laughing)
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: And I--- you know, of European descent. So, that, to me, is weird. Like, that doesn't fit to me. It is not a nationality. Yeah. So, back to your question. I also think probably, that there were a lot of professions that Jews were not allowed in. And I think that they may have then been--- that Jewish people may have been funneled into some of these things where they were allowed. So I think that may account for--- for some of it.
Cole: Yeah. Okay, interesting. The next question is about the model minority theory. Have you--- have you heard of this before I--- before I sent you this question?
Ellen: No, no.
Cole: Okay. To sum it up, it's--- it's the idea that Jews are a model minority because Jews face discrimination in the United States, but managed to be overrepresented in--- in high places, and kind of in elite society in a way. You can say the Supreme Court is an example of Jewish overrepresentation, because there's been--- for much of the 20th century and 21st, there's at least one Jewish justice on the court, even though Jews didn't make up one ninth of the United States population, right? Same thing with Ivy League student bodies, that's a part of elite society. 21% of Ivy League student bodies are--- are Jewish. And so there's this claim that Jews are a model minority. Something about them compared with other groups that are in the numerical minority, like Black Americans, Latinx people, that are underrepresented in those same places. Something about Jews makes them different from--- from these--- these other people who are underrepresented. Do you think that's a fair characterization?
Ellen: No.
Cole: Why?
Ellen: Because I think you just have to look at so much beyond that, that characterization. I mean, are we talking about Black Jews, you know? I mean, there are Black Jews. So that's not--- I don't think what you're talking--- what we're talking about there.
Cole: No, no. But yeah, you are right. There are Black Jews, but no, not--- not for this question.
Ellen: Right. We're talking about white Jews. And--- right?
Cole: I think that they probably would be counted. I'm guessing that these statistics use Jewish self-identification. So if somebody says they're Jewish, then they'd be counted.
Ellen: Okay.
Cole: But I don't have that breakdown, unfortunately.
Ellen: Yeah. No, it's okay. I'm--- I guess, I'm just again saying, you know, Judaism is a religion. It is--- it's not something that you see. You know, you would not know if somebody is Jewish unless they told you, or--- right? So, if you looked at the other things about those people that are overrepresented in those places, is it that they were born in a certain socio-economic class, and that they had certain advantages, and that they had--- you know, I--- I find it difficult to--- to only look at that one thing and think that that's what it is.
Cole: Yeah. So a similar--- commentators and sociologists, since the 1960s, have said the same type of thing about Asian Americans. They've drawn a lot of parallels between the ways that Jewish Americans immigrated, the--- even the industries that they went into, and the--- and the same type of thing when Asian Americans immigrated to the United States in the--- when many of them, did in the mid-20th century. Asian Americans are also overrepresented in certain fields, just like Jews, and an Ivy League student bodies. Do you think that these two phenomenon--- or phenomena are related? Do you think they can be caused by a similar thing? Do you think it's fair to say that Asian Americans are a model minority?
Ellen: (long pause) I think, in the Asian culture, from what I know about it, there's a big push on education. And I think in the Jewish culture there's a big push on education. And on family. So I think that those could possibly be--- could lead to--- to some of that. But, you know, other than that, I mean, what--- I don't--- I can't imagine what other reason there would be, you know?
Cole: Yeah. I want to ask you a little bit about what you mean by Jewish culture. And you said this before as well, when you were talking about kind of the emphasis that Jewish parents, or at least the ones that you knew, put on you to do certain things, like to go to college? How does that--- how does that contradict, or--- or not contradict what you're saying about Judaism being a religion? Is it more than a religion if it has kind of an associated culture?
Ellen: Yes. I think it can--- it can be more than a religion. Well, I mean, most, if you--- I guess, if you think about it, most--- most religions have cultures surrounding them, right? So maybe it's no different than any. You know, if you--- if you read about other religions, there are things that happen as well, that are surrounding holidays and--- and, you know, important traditions.
Cole: Mm hmm.
Ellen: So I don't know, if--- you know, I had a good friend in high school who was Italian, and it was a huge Italian family, and they were--- you know, they were all--- it was, every Sunday, you know, you had dinner together, and--- there were always things that--- that family did that maybe is not so different. You know, maybe it's just that people who--- people look to find some commonality and comfort within people who are similar to them. You know, I kind of done recent reading about historically Black colleges, you know, and how people feel at home there. That they're just comfortable there. They don't have to explain themselves, they don't have to be on guard. And maybe that's what Jewish culture kind of does for Je--- people that are Jewish.
Cole: Would you say that that's the same type of at home feeling that you said you might feel if you go to a synagogue anywhere in the world?
Ellen: Yeah. Yep. Probably not to that--- quite that extent, but yes.
Cole: I don't think I have any more particular questions for you.
Ellen: What a cool thing, Coley!
Cole: Yeah. So I'm going to stop the recording, unless--- unless you have anything else that came to mind that you're kind of thinking about?
Ellen: No. It--- well, one thing, this kind of heal the world thing, you know, Grandpa--- Grandpa Harry, during the Great Depression, he ran an Italian American grocery store. And he gave credit to tons of people to get their food there and to help them get through that time. So, I think that's part of his Jewishness. You know, his watching out for others and trying to make things better and healing the world, but whatever. Yes, that's it.
Cole: Well, I do actually want to ask you a follow up on that. He ran a Jewish--- he ran an Italian American grocery store. Tell me about that.
Ellen: When he moved to Middletown, that coffee thing kind of failed, so he opened a grocery store. His brothers had owned them in New York, and he opened one in Middletown, and there was a large Italian population in Middletown, so that's what he did. And, you know, I used to go in there with my dad and help out. And, they were barrel--- wooden barrels of snails and pickles and dried beans and there was a deli counter, you know, with the mortadella, and the salami, and the cheese, and the--- yeah, it was--- it was a pretty amazing place.
Cole: Yeah.
Ellen: It was--- I wish I had a picture of it.
Cole: And it wasn't--- it wasn't a Jewish deli or a Jewish grocery store.
Ellen: No, I mean, he would make--- you know, he would sell meat and cheese, two things that aren't supposed to mix in the--- in--- you know, if you're kosher, and no wasn't--- it was an Italian American, absolutely, grocery store and he learned Italian.
Cole: Wow. That was one of the six.
Ellen: That was one of the six. Yeah.
Cole: Well, I think that's it. I'll stop the recording real quick.
Ellen: Okay.