Cole: So we are now--- you're now recording?
Gabe: Yep.
Cole: Perfect. I'm here with Gabriel [...], and it's November 13, 2020. So we're gonna start with some questions about your childhood and go chronologically through your life up until the present day.
Gabe: Okay.
Cole: Just broadly, what was your experience growing up? What--- what's the first thing that comes to mind?
Gabe: Like, are you talking about first memory? Or---
Cole: Just when you think about---
Gabe: What are you thinking?
Cole: ---what comes to mind?
Gabe: Honestly, probably the--- probably the most impactful thing is--- is kind of swimming back and forth between my--- my mother's family and my father's family.
Cole: Yeah, talk more about that. When--- how often did you go back and forth, and why were you going back and forth?
Gabe: So my parents, my biological parents, split up when I was too young to remember. And--- and I spent, you know, so I spent my entire childhood, doing this kind of back and forth. We had a calendar that my mom's house. Every weekend was numbered one through eight. And so I was with my mom, and that family, all week, every week. And then--- and each--- each of the numbers--- there were two weekends with my father for the--- for, you know, for the whole--- actually, there were four weekends with my father for the whole weekend. And then two weekends with my mom for the whole weekend. And then the odd ones, it was Sundays, kind of alternating. Just the day, just--- or overnight.
Cole: You said that your parents--- your biological parents split up before you can remember. Do you remember anything about them being together at all?
Gabe: No, no, not at all.
Cole: So--- okay. Do you know--- do you know why they split up?
Gabe: Um, I think that they were just very different people. I think that--- my understanding, and this is kind of--- I mean, obviously, this isn't even first person. These are not things that I--- I know myself, these are things that I've kind of extrapolated in, and kind of combined and interpolate--- interpolated what I think happened. I think when they met, I think they were--- they were much more similar. I think when they got pregnant with me, I think my father had a bit of a--- a bit of a kind of a pause in terms of what he was doing with his life and how he was living his life. And I think that caused him to make some pretty substantial shifts in the way he approached it and his mindset, and I think a lot of those shifts, ended up causing them to be very, very different people. So the parents--- the people that I knew, kind of growing up, were--- were complete opposite ends of the spectrum. Really, really different people, I can't really imagine them ever being together. And I think I think my father shifted much more from what he had been. And I think my mother, I think she probably remained pretty consistent. I think my d--- my father also had--- he had--- he had a lot of unresolved issues as we--- as everyone does. But--- so I think--- I think that kind of manifested itself in--- in a lot of different ways, and then that caused the breakup.
Cole: What--- you say that they were very different. How did that manifest? How were they different?
Gabe: I mean, you know, on the surface. So my mom's this short, very liberal-minded, conservative woman. Sorry, Jewish woman. And my father, the one that I grew up with was, you know, this--- this tall, very conservative, from a religious perspective, fundamental--- fundamentalist Christian, from a political perspective. And I think there was--- there was a lot of animosity from both of them on kind of those differences. I have a feeling that when they met, the differences didn't matter. And--- and a lot of those differences, they didn't come out until after they had split up, like, my--- my father was not religious when they were together. It's something he found, you know, when I was probably around five. They split up--- my understanding is sometime between me being one and like two and a half. And so he didn't--- he didn't join a church and find religion for himself until he was--- when I was four and a half, five years old or so.
Cole: You say your biological parents. What do you mean by that?
Gabe: So both of them ended up remarrying and--- or, you know, finding new partners. And--- and so I grew up with basically four parents. I grew up with kind of two households, two families. You know, one was my father's side, and he was absolutely the patriarch, he was--- he was head of the household and my stepmom didn't work outside the home. And--- and her job was to kind of, you know, raise the children and be at home. And he ruled with an iron fist. On my mom's side, it wasn't quite the opposite. But my mother was for sure, kind of, she's the head of the household, and my stepdad would make jokes that, "I'm the boss, right, honey?" And so like, that was always a joke, but there was some for sure truth in terms of their dynamic. And there's a kind of very different--- I don't know, very different aspects of--- of relationship and love and affection. Some of those things are very common. But some of those things are very different. And so when I say biological, it's definitely to distinguish my stepdad, Kev--- was very much a father figure. And I don't call him dad directly. But when talking about him with my--- with my siblings on that side, I very much use, you know, Dad, when I'm talking to my mom, it's, you know, Dad or Kevo, which they all--- my siblings also use interchangeably. So, it's a bit to distinguish, kind of, the--- the the fact that there were two very distinct families that I grew up with.
Cole: But biological parents, the--- the other--- right, your other parents, doesn't really include your stepmom.
Gabe: What do you mean?
Cole: Well, when I asked you about biological parents, you said it was to distinguish that you really had four parents growing up, but you ended your answer---
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: ---talking to me about Kevin.
Gabe: Yeah. So, Cindy, for sure, was--- I mean, she was very much a mom figure, incredibly loving, you know, very grateful to have had her in my life. And--- and so the reality, though, is that I spent, I spent 75%, or more time with my mom and stepdad. And--- and you know, I'm closer to them, I spent more time with them growing up. I interact with them, you know, way, way, way more. And so, when I think of--- when I think of--- now, of my family, I think of--- I think of that side of my family. And you're asking questions about childhood, so. It shifted over time, for sure.
Cole: Let's talk about the people here. Can you talk about your dad back then? I mean, you gave a brief description of him, but what did he do? What was his career? And how did he relate to his religion?
Gabe: Sure, yeah. He was a--- he was an engineer by--- by training. And all growing up, though, he was a general contractor. He--- he--- he had his own business. I think--- I think part of the reason for that, honestly--- I don't know if it was vindictive or just kind of a kind of a planned approach, but I think he did not want to pay child support. He--- so he worked for himself, and he--- you know, he largely was paid cash when he could, and I think a lot of that had to do with, kind of, his political conservatism, but manifesting in a very personal way, is the way I understand it--- you know, understand it and have kind of internalized it myself. So, he was always--- he was always--- you know, he was always working. He owned--- over the course of my childhood, he owned a couple of properties that, you know, were his, that he was in the process of renovating and rehabilitating and then would either rent it out or for the most part he sold them. So, but he always had some sort of job going on. Some my earliest memories with him were going to a job, you know, with--- with a cooler packed lunch and--- and spending time being insanely bored at a job site, or being given some sort of task. But for the most part, it was--- it was just kind of, you know, I was tagging along, and it wasn't every weekend that I would do that. It would depend on the job and sometimes I'd help, willingly or unwillingly. But often it was just--- kind of just to be there and--- and kind of find my own stuff to do.
Cole: Yeah, do you remember those memories fondly?
Gabe: Yes and no? I mean, more just kind of there. I mean, they weren't bad experiences. I wouldn't say that like, oh, those were--- those were--- like those were--- you know, that was wonderful. What a--- what a time. There's--- you know, there's a few that are, you know, really funny. There's a--- there's--- but there's nothing that was like, Oh, that was--- the sucked. Like I remember climbing--- I remember a job site where there was this huge mud pile and he basically put me in a snow suit, and this was in the spring, so it was warm out. I was--- I remember being very hot doing this. And I was probably like, eight years old. Put me in a snow suit, put me in snow boots. And like, I was--- I mean, literally mud on every inch of my body. Just stuff like that. I remember doing flashing with him once on this window. And he was like, "Be really, really careful. Like, this will cut you." And I've said the exact same thing to you before. And the--- and a couple minutes later, like he all of a sudden, like grabbed my face. And I had this--- I had this huge blood smear. And it was from a mosquito I had hit. And he thought I had sliced my my cheek open. So stuff like that, you know, very warm memories, but nothing like, I don't know, that was the best day of my life type memories, just kind of there.
Cole: Yeah, yeah. Let's talk about your mom. What did she do? What was--- was she around often?
Gabe: Yeah, she was an IT project manager. She worked for insurance companies. And she kind of gradually over the course of her career--- and really, after I left the house, her career--- the trajectory kind of continued and she ended up--- one of the last roles she had was--- was as an acting CIO for a division overseas, but she was was an insurance executive, which is crazy to think about for me in that she's this--- this liberal, hippie, you know, tattoos, kind of crazy hair. And is not when you imagine or envision when you say insurance exec[utive]. You don't picture my mom. But yeah, she was very much around. She, in terms of kind of events and participation, she was the one who was always at everything. And--- and, you know, she'd largely do the driving to go--- you know, sports events and practices and stuff like that. She was, you know, she got roped in. I was president of my eighth grade class, and she was the one--- sort of, the mother of the eighth grade class president was the one who ran a bunch of aspects. So like, yeah, she was always there. And always--- always involved in--- in pretty much kind of all aspects of what was going on in my life and in my siblings as well.
Cole: Was she--- you said that she was an insurance exec at the end of her career, but at the beginning, did she have a lot of money?
Gabe: No. No, not at all. I mean, when I think--- I think when I was--- I think when the first--- some of the first memories I had, she had no money. I think we were on food stamps. And--- and this is kind of pre-Kev in my life and--- and kind of the beginnings of Kev being in my life. But no, and I'd suggest that my entire--- kind of my entire childhood, I don't know that we ever had any--- we never had money. And not--- not in the way--- you know, some people, I think they raise their kids and they are able to kind of hide the--- the presence of money. Or the absence of money as well, but no, we never had--- we never had money. Like purchases were--- were very carefully considered. And yeah, I don't know if that's what you're getting at.
Cole: Yeah, did--- did your dad---
Gabe: You have more questions, I can tell. What?
Cole: Did your dad have money?
Gabe: He was incredibly--- there's no way around it, he was incredibly cheap. And--- and they lived very, very sparingly. Like, I remember going to, like, the Wonderbread thrift shop. And that's where we--- that's where my father, like, that's where they bought, and they would go once a week and they'd buy like, whatever was on sale. Like that's what we would buy. Like, I guess we're eating hot dog buns everyday today--- this week. And so I--- I think, I don't think he had a ton of money either, but my stepmom also didn't work outside the home. So a bit of that was kind of focus and choice. And I--- I think he also--- for him, it was around savings. I don't know that he was very good at it. But I never really had any visibility into his finances.
Cole: Yeah. Yeah. So you said that you remember--- you have at least some inkling of a memory before Kevo entered your life? How young were you when that happened?
Gabe: I mean, really young. He was--- some of my earliest memories involve him. And it was, kind of piecing it back, it was when they were first starting to date. Like, I remember--- I remember watching Roots on--- which is a--- like I think it was [19]78, something like that, seventy--- so we could look up when it came out on TV, but that--- that documentary, the--- the miniseries on TV, and I remember laying on the floor, and I remember him being there. I remember another example. And this is actually the previous house that we lived in. So he was involved in that as well. But I remember getting a splinter. And--- and my mom and Kev trying to get it out. And they couldn't. So I went to my father's where--- they let him know, and I was--- and he proceeded to--- when we got home, he took out a knife and cut it out. And that was incredibly traumatic. So Kev was involved in my life, you know, very, very early on.
Cole: Yeah. And how did that family, on your mom's side, really, how did that family grow?
Gabe: From the, like, the immediate family?
Cole: Yeah, yeah, was it just--- was it just you? I mean, you mentioned that you had siblings on that side. When did they come along?
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: Yeah. So when I was six years old, both sides of my family had--- had--- they had found spouses, and they've gotten married. And they both had--- each had a son when I was six, almost seven. Oddly, the on the same day, so I have two in essence half siblings on on those sides. And then both sides also subsequently had a daughter. My father's side, they had a daughter about a year later. And on my mom's side about four years later.
Cole: And so you're getting pretty old at that point?
Gabe: Yeah, I mean, to some extent. So my stepmom has--- has four--- has four kids from her previous relationship. And so, you know, one of the things that is--- I think is--- for me, it's interesting is that I'm an only child, in that I'm the only one with my--- with my biological parents, but I have eight siblings. I've got four step and four half. Which creates a weird--- and I don't know my step-siblings at all. Like, if I walked past them on the street, I couldn't--- I wouldn't recognize them. Maybe--- maybe, you know, I would be like, oh, but probably not.
Cole: Yeah. Let's talk about your--- your dad's and your mom's religions for a second, because you mentioned---
Gabe: Sure.
Cole: ---that was one of the things that you mentioned when--- when I asked about their differences. How did that---
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: ---how the fact that your mom is Jewish affect the way that--- the way that she appears in your memory? And so I don't mean the way you see her, but why is that something that came to mind immediately when asked about her differences with your father?
Gabe: Yeah, part of is probably just to contrast. Religion is very much a part of my father's life. Like, you know, we would--- we would go to church twice on Sunday. There was--- you know, there were church meetings on days of the week. I wasn't--- you know, I wasn't around for those, for the most part. I'd go to the, you know, vacation Bible camp. You know, my siblings definitely did. I--- me, less so. I went to, you know, a sleep over summer camp every summer growing up, and--- and that was--- that was a religious camp that my dad had organized. And so kind of in contrast, my mom did not practice. She wasn't a practicing Jew, when I was--- when I was younger, and it's a big part of the reason why I primarily grew up going to a Christian Church, is--- is my dad wanted to bring me, wanted me to--- he wanted to raise me Christian, and she didn't have a synagogue at the time. And--- and so she--- and she also didn't want to confuse me. And so when she did start practicing, she didn't necessarily kind of incorporate that into--- into my life, which I assume that we'll end up talking about, but it's something that I--- I regret to a large extent. But all growing up, I mean, you know, holidays, Chr---you know, so Hanukkah, which is a bit of a superficial holiday, but--- but a fun one. But the other holidays were--- were always--- like Passover was always a celebration and more of a kind of a cultural thing? But still very much a part of it. And then both my siblings on my mom's side, were bar and bat mitvah'ed respectively. And I did a few different things, you know, related to Judaism, but nothing--- nothing in terms of practicing when I was growing up.
Cole: Would you consider yourself having grown up as a Christian?
Gabe: Yeah. Yes.
Cole: Interesting. And you say that you regret not--- not being a part of going to synagogue? Why is that?
Gabe: There's probably a few different levels. One, I think it's--- I think it's an important aspect of--- I think it's an important aspect of a Jew's identity. And I think one of the things that's--- that's interesting to me is, there's a shared experience that--- that most Jews have. And--- and I don't. You know, that--- that--- that--- that bar mitzvah or bat mitzvah, that coming of age. And the--- kind of the practicing of the rituals associated to Judaism is something that I don't--- I don't necessarily have. And--- and then there's another aspect of--- of--- kind of, as an adult, looking at Christianity and Judaism. And--- and the things that feel more--- more like home, oddly, are the things of Judaism. And so, there's an aspect of, I wish I had had that earlier in my life. And I wish I had it in a more complete way. If that makes sense?
Cole: Yeah. Did you feel that at the time, or is this something that you got---
Gabe: No.
Cole: ---through retrospective reflection?
Gabe: Very much the latter. Yeah, very much the latter and kind of in hindsight, in retrospect.
Cole: Interesting. So let's go back to your childhood, and talk a little bit about school. What did you--- what elementary school did you go to?
Gabe: So I went to--- in kindergarten, or for kindergarten, I went to some school in Mansfield, Connecticut. I could not tell you the name. I think I could--- I think I could drive us there, if I needed to. And then from first through eighth grade, I went to Horace W Porter Middle School--- I guess, elementary school, but it was--- it was all, so. There's a few different wings in--- based in Columbia, Connecticut. And then went to Windham High School, which is in an adjoining town, an adjacent town.
Cole: What do you remember about Horace W Porter school?
Gabe: I mean, I remember--- I remember a few different aspects of like being on the playground. I remember certain teachers. I remember certain--- there were--- like, you know, the oddball things, like Adam Yarnell stabbed me with a pencil in second grade, stuff like that. I remember the lunchroom. I don't remember where the food was, but I remember where all the seats were. If that makes--- you know, like, I can't remember actually ever getting food, but I remember sitting down. And I remember a lot of the--- I remember a lot of the people that I went to--- my graduating class was--- I think we were 64 people? So you know, a pretty small--- a pretty small class. A pretty relatively intimate setting.
Cole: What--- who were these people? You know, were they--- were they people who were friends with you?
Gabe: In terms of my--- my classmates at Horace W Porter?
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: Yeah, I mean, sure. Like there's--- the--- growing up, you always have--- you like--- kind of your crew, and--- and a lot of--- a lot of my crew were friends really from soccer that I happened to go to school with, so. The--- all the rec programs there were town based. And so, between, you know, soccer and--- and I played basketball for a few years, but it was really mainly focused around soccer. I played baseball, but I ended up playing baseball for a number of years in Norwich, which is the town that my father lived in. About 25 minutes away from where I lived. And then the last couple years of little league I ended up playing in Colombia, and then went on to play, kind of--- you know, kind of high school or pre-high school level ball in Colombia as well. And so, yeah, I mean, there was a--- there was a group of friends that I kind of hung out with, and we largely ended up going to the same high school. And so, you know, had--- had relationships with them as well.
Cole: At--- at this, the Horace Porter--- W. Porter school, were the students there very diver--- diverse?
Gabe: No, not at all. It was--- I think, so in my--- in my graduating class, there was one person of color. And he was--- he was half Chinese, half Polish. His mom was, was first generation from--- from Mainland China. And his dad was like, I don't know, eighth generation Polish, but he was 100% Polish.
Cole: And in this--- when you were there at the school, did you consider yourself Jewish? If somebody had asked you?
Gabe: Yeah, yeah. From a--- and really, from a cultural perspective. I think--- so Judaism to me is kind of, there's an ethnic component to it, a cultural component, and then a religious component. And--- and from the, the cultural side, absolutely.
Cole: And that's not hindsight. That's what you would have responded if somebody had asked you?
Gabe: Yeah. I--- I wouldn't have been able to explain the differences and kind of, you know, the aspect that--- that Judaism is not a static thing, and it's not a singular thing. But--- but yeah, I definitely would have said, I'm Jewish.
Cole: Were there other Jewish students at the school that you knew of?
Gabe: There were, but like--- like--- I didn't know them in that regard because I didn't go to synagogue. And there weren't any synagogues in Colombia, in the town that I lived in. When my mom started going to synagogue, started going to services, she went to a town in Heb--- the synagogue in Hebron, which was one town over. And I didn't know any kids from--- from that area, either. I knew them through soccer, but didn't know them by name. Couldn't have--- couldn't have picked them out from the crowd.
Cole: When did your mom start going to that synagogue in the town over?
Gabe: I don't know. I think it had to have been in--- so my brother Luke, when he was--- he was always--- he was always kind of in class to go to--- to get bar mitzvah'ed. And so, I don't know, it had to have been probably when he was 10? So around the time--- I guess, is around the time when I was leaving, you know, when I was about to move out. It may have been a little earlier, but I don't think so. I think I'm--- I think my mom--- I think she attended some services, especially, you know, some of the High Holidays. She--- there was actually--- there was a synagogue in Colombia, that didn't have a congregation, really. It was actually at the, at the head of the road that I spent my high school years--- that the house we moved into between my freshman and sophomore year. And I do remember her celebrating High Holidays at that little synagogue. It's this little like one room building that was boarded up all the time, apparently, except for High Holidays. So it had to have been around that time.
Cole: You said that you regret not going to synagogue when you were a kid, at least from your perspective. Now do you---
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: ---do you associate that with your mom's decision to not confuse you? Do you wish that she had made--- made a different decision?
Gabe: Yeah, I do. Very much. And I mean--- on a lot of levels, it's--- you know, it--- it is definitely part of my heritage. So I definitely have some regrets about both decisions that she made, but then also decisions I made, like raising you. I wish--- I very much wish that I had been practicing and that you had been raised Jewish. Big regret there. So, yeah. I don't--- I don't blame her. I mean, I think some of the reasons that she didn't were some of the reasons that I didn't raise you and your sister Jewish. I think it had to do with, you know, just life. Like, it was--- I think she was--- I think--- I think she was just busy. I don't know that she understood the--- the impact its absence had or has. And, you know, in terms of you and your sister, I don't know that I understood what its presence could have been. And so I think there's--- there's a weird converse kind of look at it. But yeah, I very much--- I regret that. I regret her decision and my decision.
Cole: Yeah. So, flying back again to--- to school.
Gabe: Yeah
Cole: When you were in elementary and middle school, were you a good student?
Gabe: Um, no. I mean, I think--- I think I was from a grade perspective, largely. Didn't try, though. You know, just kind of--- eh, I guess I'll get it done. I think I'm--- I think I can produce some pretty good work and I think I've--- I'm a fairly smart person. And so I think I--- especially--- especially then, I think I got by on--- on kind of, you know, pure ability to remember things and understand things. I don't know that I was a good student, though.
Cole: Did your parents push you to get good grades?
Gabe: No. No, not really. It was--- it was--- I mean, it was largely--- it was largely like a self-directed effort in terms of, like, if I got bad grades, that didn't feel good. That, for sure, there was discussions and those were not--- but I also--- I didn't really get bad grades. I had--- I had a couple of years where I--- you know, the only way to describe it in hindsight is I was just acting out. Don't know why necessarily. Like, sixth grade. Poor Mrs. Lasso, like, what, what an asshole I was to her. And she loved me. And I loved her too. She was a great teacher, but man, was I a pain in the ass to her. And so--- like I had a--- that was a lot of detentions. A lot of trips to the office. But my grades didn't necessarily reflect that. And I don't know that I was a straight A student. I think I--- for the most part, I think I got mainly A's with an occasional B and--- and a very infrequent C, and there was a question about like, "What's going on there?"
Cole: Yeah, and did that same kind of, I don't know, laissez faire attitude towards grades, except for when they were bad, continue into high school as well?
Gabe: On my part, or my--- my parents' part?
Cole: Your parents' part.
Gabe: Yeah, largely. I mean, my father was never really involved in grades at all. Didn't get report cards, as far as I know. He could have, but you know, it doesn't register for me. High school was, you know, again, very self-directed. And I re--- I do remember, it was probably my--- it was probably my sophomore year, beginning to be really mindful of when grades were coming out. And--- with a focus on, alright, I'm going to make sure I grab my report card. There were--- there were more than a few semesters where my parents did not see my report card, because I grabbed it before they--- they saw it.
Cole: Why would you grab it? What would spur that to happen?
Gabe: I just like--- in high school, I probably got more--- more of a scattering of A's and B's. It wasn't it--- you know, and my--- my recollection of grade school was--- was more A's than--- than anything and the--- the occasional B and the infrequent C. High school, I think it was a bit more--- it was a bit more scattered. But in hindsight, my--- like, my GPA was sufficient. I was top 10% of my class, which isn't necessarily anything to be proud of. But my grades couldn't have been that bad, snd I was taking challenging courses. I was part of the--- kind of the college prep track, so. But I also remember, like, I mainly did homework, like, in the--- in the five minutes before class, like, sitting there scribbling it out, you know, so, I was often late with stuff, and I would convince teachers to let me hand stuff in late, so. It was always a--- a bit of a precarious balancing act from my remembering, my re--- you know, my recollection.
Cole: Would you grab the report cards because you didn't want your parents to see them because you would have been ashamed, or because we're worried about them having questions about your bad grades, or something else?
Gabe: Probably more the ashamed. Probably more--- and I wouldn't even say it was shame necessarily, but more feeling badly that--- that this is what I had done, that--- or this is what I hadn't done. It wasn't--- like the conversations were painful, but they were--- they were--- my parents never had expectations of like, you know, if you don't, these bad things are gonna happen to you. It was it was very much a, like, you know, "What's going on here?" And I don't know that I necessarily ever wanted to have a conversation with them about how I was feeling about things.
Cole: Yeah. Let's talk a little bit about your high school. How big was it?
Gabe: So I went to Windham High School, which is--- I mentioned it earlier, town next door, and you know the area. The Town of Windham has the City of Willimantic in it, one of those weird New England things. And so my--- my high school was Windham High School, and it was in Willimantic, which is this city. Failing, you know, industrial town had--- had a mill that had closed down in the early/mid 80s. There was a really large Puerto Rican population there, and a fairly sizable African American population as well. There--- and so like the high school that I went to, it was--- actually, it was, I don't know that there was a majority of any one--- one ethnic population, whites and Puerto Ricans were about equivalent, I think, around 40%, and--- and African American made up the other 20% with, you know, with some--- some smaller--- smaller populations mixed in.
Cole: Yeah, do you--- I'm gonna ask the same question as I did about your middle school. Were you aware that there were other Jewish students here? Did you know who they were or know them at all?
Gabe: No. Nope. Now, for me, high school, especially early on, was--- was a bit about survival. Coming from a, a largely, almost only, white town, and being you know--- being a big white kid who was involved in athletics. You know, in grade school, it was--- you know, I don't know, it was kind of, not Big Man on campus, but for sure, like, I was involved in a lot of the things that kind of everyone did, and we--- you know, life at school revolved around. And so going into high school, I was definitely--- especially because most of the kids that I went to high school with, most of the kids came from the Windham area. And most of them had gone to grade school together. And it was a bit of a regional high school, kind of, in that my year, there was--- Columbia sent students, which was the town I lived in, Willington, which is another couple towns away, also sent students too. And so you know, there was these--- you know, these two small rural communities, and then a larger urban community. So, all of the kids from Windham, they knew each other, and had grown up with each other. The--- the Willington contingent, this was actually the last year--- my freshman year was the last year they sent kids. So most of the Willington residents did not send their kids there. There was a really small contingent, so there was this--- this group from Columbia, and--- and for sure, you know, I remember--- I remember having some challenges in terms of people deciding, "I'm going to--- I'm going to--- he's the one we're going to--- he's the one we're going to take on." And I just remember getting into fights over just being a new kid and being white, honestly. It was--- it was--- it was very much a unique experience for me, at the time.
Cole: When you say it was because you were white, was--- were other kids who are not white the ones who are picking fights with you?
Gabe: Yes and no, I mean, so, yes, but--- I mean, so, all these kids that kind of grew up together in Windham, they all knew each other and were comfortable with each other. And so, it was a bit of--- it was a bit of--- of everybody, to some extent. And--- and part of it was just kind of jostling for, you know, who--- who are going to be, you know, the people that kind of other kids follow. And for me, again, sports was--- was--- was a very much an equalizing aspect. And I was also involved in student government there. I was in student council. And so I kind of--- I fit into a bunch of different groups. And--- and some of the kids that I had challenges with my freshman year I ended up being really good friends with, of--- just independent of race, color, etc. But I remember the first few months of freshman year like, this is not fun. I'm ready to go back to Porter. By the end of soccer season, it had kind of--- it had kind of died down. And then into basketball season, which I--- I played my freshman year. It was--- it ended up being like, oh, this is gonna--- this is fine.
Cole: Let's talk about these extracurriculars. I think you've mentioned basketball, soccer student government. Were there any others?
Gabe: Yeah, so I did, like you mean, in terms of my--- kind of my entire youth career? Or specific to high school?
Cole: Yeah, entire youth career. Things that you did that were associated with school and just outside of school.
Gabe: Yeah. I mean there was--- there was--- I'm trying to think of what else I did. In high school--- I guess student government was kind of a theme throughout. President of my eighth grade class, was on student council all four years of high school. I was never involved, which floors me, given yours--- your and your sisters, kind of, affection and aptitude for theater and choir and things like that. I never did anything remotely associated to that. I think I did one acting class in like sixth grade or something. But that was it. It was a--- kind of a weird oddball thing. So I played baseball. In high school, my--- very much played soccer pretty much year round, and actually did in grade school as well. Played--- you know, played--- played indoor soccer in the winter, did spring soccer in--- in the spring, and summer soccer in the summer. Not quite the way you did. Not quite as organized. It was different--- kind of different teams in different areas. But still played. I did--- one of the things I did in high school was peer mediation. So I was pretty involved in that for--- for, I guess, really, I think it's--- I think we started it my sophomore year. So I did that sophomore, junior, senior years. I think that that's probably the--- the gist of it, you know, between government, doing the peer mediation things, and sports.
Cole: Why student government? What drew you to do it throughout your entire school career?
Gabe: I have no idea. I don't know. And I mean, I was always really interested in it. I'm interested in--- in--- in politics now. But, like you and your sister are way more in tune and, and for you specifically are more understanding of the actual workings of our local government. I'm interested in politics in general. But, you know, then--- I don't know why. I don't even know why I ran for president of my eighth grade class. But I enjoyed it. It was fun. Like, if I had to do it over again, I don't know that I would have. You know, it was--- it ended up being more effort and time than I think--- I think I should have been focusing on--- more on school. But it was a good experience nonetheless. So I don't know if I would--- I would undo it, or redo it differently. But I don't know why. It was kind of one of those things that yeah, I'll run for student council. Sure.
Cole: Yeah. You mentioned that in the classes you took in high school, you were in the college prep track. Did you plan to go to college throughout high school? Was it something that your parents talked about often?
Gabe: It--- no. And not necessarily talked about. But there was--- like, it wasn't an active conversation. But there was--- and it probably was stated at some time, but there was kind of an unstated expectation that well, of course you'll go to college. And--- and one of the reason for going to Windham High School, actually, was, you know, I had two options for high school--- I guess I had three options. One was private, and that wasn't--- that was not an option because I don't know that we had the money to do that. The other two I could go to--- actually, I guess I had--- I had two options in this other subcategory of if you want to do something that is kind of trade specific. I could have gone to Windham Technical School, which is a--- you know, a trade school focused on, you know, electricians, plumbing, things like that. Or I could have gone to Lyman Memorial, which was in a different town, one town over in Lebanon, where the focus was on [incomprehensible] Ag skills. Or, Windham High School, which was the--- kind of the college prep space. And just in general, I mean, I was taking AP classes and things like that, was--- you know, I guess there were really two tracks. I think you and your sister had kind of a similar model. I think, from my--- from my exposure, the way your high school handled it was a little better. I think that, you know, really distinct tracks, but there was more of a blending where you didn't kind of start and finish in the same track. If you wanted to shift. In mine, I only really kind of knew of one track and that was the one that I was in.
Cole: Yeah, these other high school options, the more technical ones, was that an active choice that you made to go to Windham as opposed to these? Or is it just something that happened?
Gabe: More of the latter. I remember filling out a form actually, kind of specifying my intent. But, I was like, I'm not gonna go be a farmer, you know, be a an electrician. But, so.
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: Did either of---
Gabe: I'm not sure if that answers your question? What?
Cole: Did either of your parents go to college?
Gabe: Yeah. I mean, all four did, looking at it from the perspective of these two families. All four of them dead. And interestingly, you know, my father didn't use his degree. You know. So, growing up--- and my--- yeah, so education was--- was a very big part of kind of for sure my mom's side of the family. Yeah.
Cole: Say more about that? Why particularly your mom's side of the family?
Gabe: I mean, so neither my father nor my stepmom, I mean, they used their degree, right. At least when I was growing up. My dad was--- was a--- was a builder, was a contractor. And--- and so I'm sure he used aspects of things that he learned, but not directly. My stepmom was a stay-at-home--- you know, stay-at-home mother, and--- and I don't even know what she went to school for. And then on my--- on my mom's side, both--- both parents had gone to school, and, to some extent, were using that, but--- you know, were using their degrees, but--- I don't know, there was always just an--- kind of that unstated expectation of well, of course, you'd go to college.
Cole: Yeah, let's talk about that process a little bit. How did you decide where you wanted to apply?
Gabe: About--- for college?
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: Oh, this is goi--- yeah, this will be--- this will be a fun conversation. I--- so, in high school, I took classes. I mentioned AP classes. And so I actually had credit for University of Connecticut. And--- and so that was kind of one of those, well, you know, it's right down the street. And I remember Mr. Katumpska, my--- my--- my guidance counselor suggesting that I should apply there because I already had credit for it, you know, towards--- towards a UConn [University of Connecticut] degree. And then my--- my other--- kind of my other schools that I was interested in. I don't remember how I got to them, but ended up being Trinity in Hartford, Wesleyan in Middletown, Connecticut, and then Clark College in--- in Worcestor Uni--- Worcester, Mass [Massachusetts]. And my stepdad had gone to Clark, and so, somehow that--- you know, that--- that stuck for me. Wesleyan was a really good school and had a good soccer program, and a really good school. And then--- and Trinity, not quite as good of a school, but had--- had a soccer program as well. So for all three, I ended up talking to the coaches of the soccer programs and about kind of what that--- what it would look like to participate. And ended up talking to the coach at Clark a few times. And then applied to all four. Didn't get into Wesleyan, got waitlisted at Trinity, got into Clark, and--- and UConn was--- was kind of a slam dunk, was accepted as part of their honors program. And at the time, I wanted to be a teacher. And so I was actually accepted into a five year program to lead with my teaching--- with a degree and my teaching certificate.
Cole: And that was at UConn, the five year program?
Gabe: At University--- yep. Yeah.
Cole: After you were accepted, what--- what do you decide to do?
Gabe: So I really wanted to go to Clark, and at the time--- I mean, you asked about money earlier, that at the time, my mother had just been diagnosed with--- with cancer, and--- and my parents--- again, when I say parents, I almost always mean my mom and Kev--- parents basically said that they weren't--- that they weren't going to be able to take out loans. And so kind of the default was, "Well, you can go to UConn. We can afford UConn."
Cole: Yeah. So you---
Gabe: There wasn't really--- there wasn't really--- there wasn't really a decision to be made, if that makes any sense.
Cole: Yeah, it was just the option that you had?
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: So this is in your senior year of high school, you just decided, or you defaulted, to going to UConn? What was that like?
Gabe: Going to UConn?
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: I mean, I--- so I barely went. I--- I actually kind of, you know, post--- post-Halloween, I don't think I attended any classes. I was working. I was running an after-school program. I was the assistant director of an after-school program at an elementary school. And so I worked, and I was living on campus, but wasn't going to classes and just kind of hanging out with my friends and got thrown out after a semester. That's what happens when you get a 0.0 [GPA], apparently. And moved back in to my parents home--- I had never really moved out. So then my--- the spring semester of what should have been my freshman year, started going to classes at Eastern Connecticut State University, which is in the town of Willimantic. Literally across the street from my high school. Took, I think, three classes there my--- my--- that spring semester of my what should have been freshman year. So yeah.
Cole: Was it a decision that you made to not go to class? Were there things that you were weighing, or was it just something you didn't do?
Gabe: More of the latter. I mean, obviously, that in and of itself is a decision. But just didn't want to be there and, kind of was like eh, I don't think I'm going to go today.
Cole: Yeah. What did your parents--- how did they react to getting a 0.0, as you put it?
Gabe: I don't know that they were pleased. I mean, my parents weren't yellers. And so I think that they were--- I think that they were disappointed. I also think they were worried. So, you know, it was a--- it wasn't necessarily a pleasant conversation, but I don't remember it incredibly distinctly. So it was--- it was--- and they weren't going to--- they weren't going to throw me out of the house. You know, they for sure were not that type of--- of parents, and--- or we didn't have that type of family. So, you know, it just kind of--- it just kind of happened.
Cole: Yeah. And so in that spring semester, you started taking classes at Eastern. Were you still expecting to try to be a teacher at this point?
Gabe: No. No, I really didn't know what I wanted to do. It was--- it was a bit of the--- the reason for the classes at Eastern--- that--- that probably was my parents, that "You're--- you're not going to just kind of live at home and do nothing. And you're not going--- and, so you should enroll at Eastern." And--- with the plan on basically getting back into UConn, in essence. The--- the--- you know, the letter that I got in the decision from UConn to expel me had to do with--- you know, they laid out, you know, basically active participation. But then there was a, you know, if you--- if you want to reapply, in essence, we'd like some proof that you're committed to your education and we would--- we would reconsider this decision. So the--- the going to--- actually I think I only took two classes at Eastern. It may have been--- may have been three or four, but I can't remember. So--- and that was largely because of them, I think.
Cole: Did you finish those classes?
Gabe: Yeah. And got okay grades. And then subsequently--- subsequently moved out the following summer. Moved out of my parents' house.
Cole: When af--- after you finished that semester at Eastern, what happened with reapplying to UConn? Did you keep on taking classes there? Did you try to reapply?
Gabe: Yeah, I did not. I took--- I think I took one other semester at Eastern. And--- so moved out when I was 18, about to turn 19. And--- and subsequently--- you know, I think I took classes one more semester at Eastern. I think I took two semesters worth. I want to say it was six classes total. And then stopped going, stopped taking classes, was working at a few different--- a few different pla--- actually, it was only one job at a time, but was working in restaurants and started managing a Subway [a chain restaurant]. Assistant manager first, and then became a manager of--- of this Subway. And--- and didn't start taking classes again until--- until kind of a few career transitions later, when I was--- so probably four years later, when I was 23.
Cole: Yeah. You said that you moved out just before turning 19. Where did you move?
Gabe: Got an apartment with--- with the--- with my girlfriend and two friends. And, yeah, it was a great little--- great little house in Mansfield--- in Storrs [the town in Connecticut the contains UConn], not in Mansfield. But in the--- in the--- in the Town of Mansfield, I guess.
Cole: What were your roommates and girlfriend up to? Were they students taking classes? Or were they working also?
Gabe: They were--- they were all students. Actually, I don't know--- I don't know if Jay was. I don't know what Jay did. I mean, he worked. But, yeah, so the rest of us--- the rest of them were taking classes. And for me, like, I started when I was--- when I was managing the Subway, was pretty heads down, was pretty focused, was working a ton. It was kind of that and hanging out with my friends.
Cole: You said that you were the--- the assistant director of a after-school program and then the manager of a Subway. How did these things---
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: ---happen? How did you--- how did you end up being part of the management of these different--- different employers, I guess?
Gabe: Yeah. The after-school program, I--- I don't know, I just--- I applied. I was looking for a job and I actually knew--- in a really extended fashion, I knew the woman who was the director. And I was just applying for, you know, a position as--- as a staff member. And as we talked about things, she said, "I actually think that I would like to hire you on, but not just as a staff member, but I'd like you to be my assistant director." So that's kind of how that unfolded through a couple of interviews. The manager thing in the Subway, I was working at one Subway and--- and the manager left to go open his own, a few years--- and so I knew him. And then when--- when I started looking for full-time work, I ended up having a conversation with him. And he brought me on as an assistant, and his plan was to expand to--- he had one--- one store and he wanted to have ten. And so it was--- it was kind of brought on as a bit of a trial period. I think I was assistant manager for about six months, and then ended up taking over that store, and then ended up basically acting--- it wasn't--- I wasn't more than manager, but I ended up managing a couple of stores, if that makes any sense. From a--- from a kind of a staffing, inventory perspective of a couple of different stores.
Cole: Yeah. So you're at this--- you're living in this apartment with your girlfriend, two friends. If your life were a story, what's the next chapter? What happens next?
Gabe: Yeah, so the--- the next--- the next chapter is--- is--- is a bit of kind of a few storylines. Parents worried about me. I--- I--- actually, no that that happened later. Sorry, remembering things in reverse order. Had a conversation with--- with my parents, and this was not like a, like, "Let's sit down and talk." This was literally just a conversation and begin thinking of--- I'm looking at this guy who's about five years older than me maybe. And he's now got three stores. He's looking for his fourth and fifth locations. And I'm like, Well, what would it take for me to do that? I don't have a--- I don't have a dime to my name, and got in my head that if I could come up with enough capital, I could buy a house, and then I could use that house as leverage to then get more capital to then figure out some sort of business. And for me at the time, I probably should just own a Subway. Like, that--- that makes sense. That's what I'm--- that's what I'm good at, apparently. And so, as part of that, I needed--- I needed a different--- I needed a different income stream, and I needed more verifiable income. Not from the perspective of taxes, but just in terms of salary versus hourly. And so I ended up going to work at Pizza Hut and--- and joined their management trainee program and was an assistant manager and ended up jumping around to a few different locations, kind of getting promotions along the way. And at the same time, ended up working with a friend at a local pizza place, Willington Pizza, which you've eaten at before. And so for about--- kind of, the reason I got this job at Willington Pizza was, I'm on this path, like, Alright, I'm gonna--- I'm gonna--- I'm gonna do this, I began talking to some people about the downpayment I would need to actually buy a house. And the number was--- was a bit staggering for me. And so decided I needed a way to make some more money, and so got another job, and ended up working basically two jobs for about six months. And as soon as I had the downpayment and had closed on the house that I was--- that I was buying, I quit the Pizza Hut job and focused on working at Willington Pizza.
Cole: And those were both full time jobs, you had two full time jobs at one point?
Gabe: Yeah, I mean, the Pizza Hut one was--- you know, I was an assistant manager and salaried position. I think the expectation there was that I--- I think, the requirement, or the--- you know, what was expected was 45 hours in a week for a salaried position. And so the Willington Pizza one, I was just working as many hours as I could get when I wasn't at Pizza Hut. And so--- and they were pretty flexible, and people were pretty willing to give up shifts. So for a while, I was working about 85 hours a week.
Cole: Wow. This house that you bought, did end up panning out? Did it give you the--- the capital to--- to continue doing more things?
Gabe: No. No. It was a great experience, and I--- for sure, I wouldn't do it differently. But no, I mean, I was--- I think there was a lot more--- there were a lot of things that I didn't understand about kind of how that would work. And so no, I mean, it didn't work out with the original intent, but it worked out in different ways.
Cole: Like what?
Gabe: I mean, so, you know, one of the big--- one of the big shifts--- and so, this is kind of--- this will be then the next chapter, if you will, the next storyline. Working at Willington Pizza, and I had this--- I had this idea of gumball machines. And my parents like to make fun of me for this one. That, what if I had--- what if I had 10 gum ball machines? Like, how can I make additional money. And the house that I bought was actually--- was a two family. And so I lived in half of it and rented out the other half. And so this gumball--- this gumball brainchild of mine, like, I think my--- I think this really was concerning to my parents, that, like, he needs to figure something else out. And so they--- they ended up paying for me to go talk to a job counselor, to basically kind of take some tests and--- and it's a--- the woman was a friend of her--- of theirs. And so we ended up having a conversation about kind of, you know, what I should consider, what I'd be good at doing, what I like to do. And--- and she had some recommendations. And that was--- that kind of led to--- this is around the time of Y2K. And so the insurance company that my mom worked for, Hartford Insurance Group, they were hiring developers, and they were hiring people to basically help fix all the Y2K problems. And I ended up taking a test--- like the the application process was, you take a test to understand if you'd be a good COBOL programmer. And then depending on your score, they might ask you back or not. And that kind of shifted my focus and--- and my whole career tre--- trajectory, and--- and arguably life trajectory, into a totally different space. I ended up getting the job, and was one of many. It wasn't like I had the job, it was--- I think, my--- my acceptance--- I think each acceptance class was like 20 people, and they were running, like, you know, six to ten classes a year, that was their goal. So that's what I ended up doing.
Cole: So you got this job as a COBOL programmer. What happened next?
Gabe: Um?
Cole: In your career.
Gabe: In terms of--- in my career--- yeah. So I was working as a--- as a programmer, and ended up going back to school. The Hartford paid for--- had a--- had a tuition reimbursement benefit. And so I ended up going back to college--- going and--- joining--- you know, ended up re-registering at University of Connecticut, and ended up--- a colleague came over to me one day, and he--- he suggested that I apply for this internal position. He had already done so and he was joining--- how was going to--- about to move groups. And he said, you should--- you should do this with me. And his name was Jeff, good guy. He was a former banker, and he was probably 15 years old, 10 years, 12 years older than me. And I was like sure, I'll consider it and so I ended up joining this other group and learned a new technology, kind of in a new field. And--- and then, after about six months of being in that group, he came over me one day again, and was like, "You know that we could double our salary, if we left?" I was like, you're--- you're full of it, Jeff. And ended up, he was right. And so ended up taking a job and moved to Minnesota. And that's why your sister has a--- a Minnesotan social security number, as opposed to you. Which--- you have a Connecticut-based security number.
Cole: So let's rewind a little bit, and instead of focusing on career, let's talk about your personal life. This apartment that you had right after college, you said you were living there with your girlfriend? What happened---
Gabe: Yep.
Cole: ---with her? Who was she, and--- and where did that lead?
Gabe: Yeah. So, I mean we ended up--- we ended up splitting up around the time that I bought this house. And--- and actually, I mean, I met your mom working at Willington Pizza. And--- and it was one of those things where my girlfriend and I had--- had--- we had been together since--- on and off since seventh--- for me, seventh grade. And so we had broken up a few different times. And your mom and I were just coworkers and friends. And I had kind of the recognition, the realization, that I really--- I really don't--- I don't love the woman I'm with. And so we ended up breaking up. And--- and--- and a number of months later, your mom and I got together. So that's kind of the--- that's the story of my previous girl--- the girlfriend before your mother. I think that was the question you asked.
Cole: Yeah. And so you met my mom working at Willington Pizza. Who was she at the time?
Gabe: Um, she was one of the head waitresses. And so I worked with her, you know, fairly often, but there was--- it was a big--- it was a big shop. And she had just finished school. And was--- was--- was living in the Storrs still, and was intending to move.
Cole: Do you know what--- what year this was?
Gabe: Yeah, I mean, it had to have been (long pause) [19]96? Maybe 97?
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: Oh, no, earlier than that. 95 probably, or 96.
Cole: And so you--- at some point, you leave Willington Pizza to go be a COBOL programmer. Are you still dating my mom?
Gabe: Yeah, we had--- we had actually--- yep, we were together and we got married. We got married in 98, so it was when I was at the Hartford. And yeah, yeah. Back to you.
Cole: Well, tell--- tell me more. Tell me more. You end up getting married. You're working at the Hartford. What's she doing? And what happens next?
Gabe: Yeah, so, working at the Hartford, married. We--- we--- so we got married and--- and the plan was to wait two years to have kids. And she changed her mind pretty--- pretty quickly after getting married. So about six months after getting married, we--- we decided--- she decided, but we decided that we were going to have a kid and then came Cole. She was--- she had gone to school--- come back to school to get her master's, she was going to be a teacher. And so she was doing--- she was working as a--- working as a substitute teacher and ended up having, you know, worked in a few different school districts while she was doing her master's program. And when--- when we got pregnant with you, we were living in this house. It was rundown, dilapidated, kind of--- and--- and you've lived with me long enough that you understand the construction zone that is most--- most places I've lived in. And--- and she and her mother were not impressed, is the only way I can phrase it. They were they were not at all convinced this was a good decision. So we ended up buying a house in Mansfield, town over, that was well beyond what we could afford, to put it lightly. And so, at the time, that--- my colleague Jeff had said, we could double our salary, I was like, I would love to do that. That sounds--- I'll choose that option. And that led to taking a different position and moving halfway across the country.
Cole: So that new position that you took was that contingent on moving? Or where there's two separate events.
Gabe: Yeah. No, so when I--- when I put my resume out there, we had--- so I had--- I ended up having offers or close to offers from--- from three different places. One was actually in Springfield, Mass. So very close to where you are right now. And that would have required a--- you know, a move potentially, or a longer commute. And then I had some interest from a place that was based in Colorado, and some interest from a place that was in San Francisco. And then the company I ended up choosing, they had an office in St. Paul, and they were trying to start an office in Atlanta. And so the Colorado one did not feel real at all to me, I was just having conversations with them. But San Francisco, I had gotten to the point where we were beginning to discuss finances, and the--- kind of the finances of an offer. And I began looking at cost of living. And so in comparison, St. Paul sounded really, really good. So that was the--- that was--- that was the--- kind of the decision factor was cost of living and--- and salary increase. Let's move.
Cole: Yeah. When you--- when you married my mom, did you think at all about--- about intermarriage? Which is--- in a lot of Jewish families, there's a--- kind of a prohibition or a dislike of Jewish people marrying non-Jewish people. Was that something that---
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: ---your mom ever talked about, or that you felt from your grandparents maybe? Was it something that you thought about?
Gabe: No. No, not at all. I mean, you know, so looking at--- at--- because Judaism wasn't a big part of--- it wasn't a big part of our--- of our--- of my childhood family life in any way. And so, I mean, my--- you know, my mom had married a--- a Catholic. So, it was--- I don't know that it was ever even a discussion or even--- even kind of an implicating factor, even something to think about at all. And I wasn't religious at the time, at all. I was very turned off by Christianity. And so--- and so, I wasn't--- I hadn't gone to church in years and had no plans on--- on doing anything remotely close to an organized religious activity.
Cole: Why were you turned off from Christianity?
Gabe: I think--- I think a lot of it had to do with--- it's not even necessarily experience, but kind of observational experiences, if you will. I don't know. I think I saw a lot of--- of--- of--- you know, the messages that you hear in--- in Christianity in general, then not being exhibited by those that professed to believe these things. And so it just--- to me, it felt very hypocritical and wasn't something that--- that really resonated for me in the first place. And then--- and then seeing it not practiced, almost intentionally, at times, just felt--- just felt really off.
Cole: Yeah. So, this move--- I know I'm skipping around a little bit. But this move, how was that? How was moving away from Connecticut, where you had spent the rest of your life before then?
Gabe: I mean, you know, it was--- I don't know that the expectation was that this was a move forever. I think--- so at the time, your mom--- your mother and I had--- had talked about it as this is an experiment. It's a two year--- let's look at it as basically--- as a bit of a two year commitment, a two year stint. And, I mean, within the--- within the two year timeframe of moving we had--- we had (chuckles) bought another house--- or we had moved into an apartment, with the plan of being there for two years, and--- but in six months, we had decided we were going to buy a house, we had gotten pregnant with another child, your sister, we had bought a car. And we were on the verge of selling the house we had bought and buying another house. So within that two year timeframe. So, it--- I mean, it was--- it was very fast, there was a lot of stuff kind of happening. To kind of add a little bit of life stuff, I mean, I--- I had blown out my knee, I gotten laid off, I had found another job. So it was--- it was a bit of a flurry of activity. So it was really exciting. And--- and very unique. It was tough being away from kind of the things that I knew. But life was busy enough that it--- you know, it was one of those like, just got to keep moving. Got to keep going.
Cole: Yeah. Do you ever regret that decision to move?
Gabe: No. I mean--- so just the fact that I'm hemming and hawing, and can't answer clearly, obviously, there's some? I think that--- the thing is that--- I--- things that don't feel right. I mean, I wish that--- I wish that I was closer with my family, physically. I was pretty intentional about making sure that you and your sis had exposure. And that's why we--- that's why we drove to the Cape every summer. That's why we spend time there, not just in the summer, but the goal was a few times a year. And I think those visits--- I think--- I think they played a part in like, why you're sitting there with, you know, with the [Pioneer Valley] behind you, right, is--- is because of those intentional decisions to make sure that you were on the East Coast. And that you recognize that that's kind of where I was from. And that's where your family--- that's where your extended family lived. So no, I don't regret it. I mean, living in the Twin Cities area has been wonderful from a career perspective, which has enabled me to do a lot of things that I don't know that I would have been able to. You know, kind of looking back, sometimes you look back and things feel inevitable, like oh, well, of course, like this happened, and then that happened, and then this happened. And--- but at the time that it's happening, like, you have no idea how it's going to turn out. And--- and often, you know--- I don't know that--- I didn't have the confidence that it was going to turn out. It was just, all right. I'm going to try this now, I'm going to try that. And so looking back on the--- what feels like an inevitable kind of continuous story now? Like, no, it was a good decision. It's been--- it's been--- it's been a good--- it's been a good outcome. So I don't know that I would regret it.
Cole: Talk to me about what happened after the move. You said those first two years were really jam packed and busy. What did you do in your career? How did it develop since--- since then?
Gabe: Well that's not--- yeah, the--- that isn't necessarily a two year, but the--- kind of the flyby is I jumped around a lot, in terms of--- in terms of employers. And to some extent, looking back on it, I kind of recognize the types of--- the types of projects that I enjoyed doing, and the types of--- kind of programs that I--- that resulted in those projects or spawned those projects, were the result of some really big, heavy lift type initiatives that companies that I worked for were trying to figure out and I got to participate. And as my career progressed, I got to participate in not just the project or kind of creating the program, but in turn, coming up with what--- what is the heavy lift effort? What's the initiative that we should be doing? What's the outcome we're trying to drive towards? And so, you know, over the course of my career, it's--- it's progressed, and I've progressed, and I've developed as a--- as a person and as a professional. And so, you know, now looking at it--- now, I mean, I love what I do. And I don't know that I would have--- I don't know that I'd be in a position to do what I do, and I think I do it pretty well. I don't know that I would be in a position to do it, the way I do it, if I hadn't had these experiences of working for companies that I didn't necessarily really enjoy early on and didn't necessarily really like the work. But the result is something that I'm super proud of. And again, I'm really conscious of this, of, it's not an inevitable thing, like you--- you know, a ton of luck, some really fortunate circumstances, and a bunch of hard work. And then a bit of just magic.
Cole: What is it that you do?
Gabe: Probably the easiest way to describe it is--- that's all--- my role is--- is enterprise architecture. And, you know, it's definitely--- it has roots in IT and technical and technology disciplines. A lot of my peers, both in my company, but in the broader industry, think of it as being very focused on technical architectures. And I don't. A lot of peers also would say, it's--- it's business architecture and technical architecture. And I--- for me, I think it also is--- there's a big part of what I think of as organizational architecture, in essence, the culture of a company. So I work for a software company and I--- my role is part of our sales organization, I'm part of a pre sales team. But I don't sell anything, I don't have a sales value, I don't have a quota. My--- my--- my team's job is to help customers figure out, in essence, how to use our stuff better. And for me, that means having conversations with customers about what they're trying to accomplish. And--- and a lot of the conversation I have now is around, in essence, how they're trying to transform. And in my field, everyone's talking about transformation. And it's an overused word. And--- and I think in a lot of spaces, people use that word. And--- and for me, it's--- it's--- it's a bit of what's your strategy, and the technology stuff comes kind of after, for me, it's very much what are you trying to accomplish and why? And let's figure out ways to do that. So business consulting, you know, strategic transformation, enterprise architecture, is a long winded way to describe I think what I do,
Cole: Yeah. So in the last couple of minutes that we have, there's still a lot of stuff that I want to get to.
Gabe: Yeah. We can go--- I can go--- I can go a little bit over. I don't know if you have a hard stop.
Cole: I can go a little bit over.
Gabe: I can go about 20 minutes over half hour over. Okay, perfect.
Cole: Let's talk about your personal life in---
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: ---these intervening years. You--- at some point, you and my mom got divorced. When was that, and what precipitated it?
Gabe: So, 2009, and--- I mean, there's gonna be aspects of this that I don't know that I want to talk with you--- and not that I don't want to talk with you about it. I don't want to talk about it in context of a--- you know, of a project. It would be when you're ready to have the conversation with me, I'd like to talk about it. But in essence, I'd say, for the purposes of this, that we kind of--- we grew apartment and we got married--- we met really young, we got married really young, we had kids really young. And--- and some people, I think they kind of--- they grow up together. And I think we--- we kind of grew apart together. And so, it was, you know, 2009 is when we--- 2009? Yeah. 2009 is when we split up. We were officially divorced in 2010. So, ask more.
Cole: Yeah, what [crosstalk] after the divorce for you, in your personal life, for you in parenting?
Gabe: What changed?
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: On the parenting--- yeah, I think I'd say not much. Other than the need to navigate--- I will say that, in general, both personal life and parenting, kind of, you know, my personal, me life, and then me, as a--- as a parent, things got a little more--- a little more challenging, while also becoming a little bit crisper. Like, there were things that I really wanted to make sure I imparted to you and your sis. And--- and, like some--- like the idea that--- you know, that it's your life and, and--- and life is all about choices. That was something that I don't know that I would have gotten that crisp on if--- if it had been a traditional two family--- two parent, I'm sorry--- two fam--- yeah, two family shows my--- my background, but a two parent household. So, and then, I mean, the flip side is, I had a lot of time without you guys, which I remember, you know, when we were in the process of splitting up, the thing that jumped out to me was--- was, you know, was--- was nine and eight. And it wasn't how old you guys were, it was, how many years of your life that I was not going to kind of have and be a part of. It was--- you know, half of those years, I just wasn't going to see you at all. On the personal side, I mean a whole bunch of--- you know, I focused a lot on work. And--- and a bit of reflection and kind of--- I don't know if I would call it self-development, but reflection is probably a better way to describe it.
Cole: Yeah. At some point after you got divorced, you started going to synagogue again, right?
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: Why was that?
Gabe: When was that? Or why was that? Or both?
Cole: Well, both.
Gabe: Yeah. I mean, it was--- it was almost immediately. And--- and you guys did not go with me for a while until I was kind of figuring it out for me. And I don't know what your experience of it was like, in terms of the divorce. And I do remember you sitting at the--- at the--- at the kitchen table at Washburn [a street in Minneapolis]. And the--- you know, this was probably February? So your mom had moved out in early November. And we--- we had the holidays, and then, you know, the Superbowl party and--- which were both, for us, meaningful things, you know, they were event-type things, and--- and annual things. And you really struggled with it early on, more than your sister did. And I remember you sitting there and I--- I had made you breakfast, you remember that--- remember that silver table we had, in the kitchen?
Cole: Mm hm.
Gabe: And you saying--- I mean, the whole thing, as we went through this, was we're going to figure out the new normal, and it's okay to--- it's okay to be sad about it, it's okay to be happy. Like, we're allowed to--- kind of, to have a lot of different emotions about it at different times or all at the same time. And I remember you--- you telling me, like, mid-bite, like "Hey, Dad." Like, yeah. "Like this new normal? It's not so bad." And--- and that--- and that was a meaningful thing for me in terms of, like, it's gonna be alright.
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: And so, back to your question of why Judaism or why--- why services, why synagogue? Kind of as this was happening, I had just a ton of--- I mean, I don't know, pain and sadness about kind of where my life was, and where it wasn't. And so, for me, I wanted to explore that and I did not want to go to a Christian church. And I also had this other aspect of--- of who I was that I hadn't yet rationalized and figured out. And so I went and attended a few--- a few services. I was going pretty much every week I didn't have you guys. And then, I ended up sitting down with--- with one of the rabbis at--- at Temple Israel, about kind of what I was experiencing, and just my situation, and he gave me some guidance and advice. And at that point, was when I had asked if you guys would want to go with me, and then we started going--- it was pretty much every week, we were--- you know, we were around. We would go every--- every--- you know, every Friday. And I was--- I was going in the off weeks. So a lot of it was just about having something that was helping me figure out where I was headed and who I was, and who I was--- who I was--- you know, who I had been, and who I was becoming, and--- and being intentional about being reflective, and--- and understanding what it was that I felt was missing.
Cole: Yeah, why did that stop?
Gabe: I mean, I still go occasionally. And--- and I mean, a lot of it had to do with--- the reason it stopped, was--- so when I--- when I met Ann, you know, all of a sudden, there was a kind of a different dynamic. And--- and focus, in terms of you guys, and me, and then our lives, shifted a bit. So, you know--- and going hasn't necessarily stopped for me. At some point, I'd love to go through the conversion process. Because even though I'm Jewish by Jewish law, I don't know that it would, I think I need--- in essence, I need to do the bar mitzvah--- or, sorry, the bar mitzvah. I need to go through that coming of age, if you will, and learning those things. And--- and the reality is--- is that it hasn't been a priority in terms of time, and effort, and attention, and focus. I hope--- my goal is that someday it will be. But I think I'm okay, if it isn't. So, that answer--- does that get to what you're asking, or?
Cole: Yeah, say more about that. You hope that someday, it'll be something you can focus on, but you're okay that you can't right now or that you aren't right now?
Gabe: Yeah, I mean, so for sure on the--- on that second part. I mean, there's only so many--- you know, only so many hours in a day, days in a week. And--- and I feel like I'm living life--- do you know the John Lennon quote of--- I mean, you've probably--- hopefully you've heard me say this, but life is what happens when you're busy making plans for the weekend? Like--- I--- like, it's okay, that I don't have--- I don't have time for that. And I think one of the things that I've--- I've gotten pretty good at, actually, which floors me a little bit is--- is understanding kind of where my limits are, and what it takes for me to recharge. And--- and I know that tackling--- like so there's--- I mean, there's some big life things here that most people kind of have in their life. And for me, they're just going to be later in my life. Graduating college, I'd really like to do. Learning more about Judaism and--- and going through that conversion process, something I'd very much like to do. And I don't know that I would say that I'll have an unsatisfied or--- you know, life if I don't do them. But they're aspirational. And so the balance of like, I'm okay that I'm not doing right now is I'm working on other things, and other things are more important right now. And the idea of putting more than is sustainable and reasonable on my plate isn't something I'm willing to do. So I'm okay with that.
Cole: Yeah, makes a lot of sense. Can you talk about how you view yourself as Jewish right now? I mean, I know you mentioned the three different parts of what Judaism is to you, the ethnic part, the cultural part---
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: ---the religious part. How do you see yourself fitting into those categories or not fitting them.
Gabe: There still is the aspect of the--- the shared experience on the religious side, which has a--- it does have a cultural thing. But then a lot of the things that people would talk about in terms of culture, like matzo ball soup, or--- or Yiddish, I mean, those are--- those are more kind of ethnic aspects of Ashkenazic Jews, and where they came from, and the culture that existed there. So I--- like I have those things to some extent. I wish I had more Yiddish in my life. I wish I had more--- I wish I had more kind of traditional American Jewish things like bagels and lox in my life. But, so I have that. The--- what I think of as really the cultural things of--- of Judaism, High Holidays, and--- and not the religious aspect of it, but just participating in that, that I just don't have as much. I--- I--- like we go to Passover, when it's not a pandemic, right. But--- and--- and I really appreciate the--- kind of the family cultural aspect, I love the fact that there are millions of Jews doing that across the globe. And then there's the religious aspects, which I don't have, you know, not from a more formalized, you know, perspective, I guess. But I think one of the things that's most appealing to me about Judaism on the religious side is there's an aspect of, from my experience, and I don't know enough about this to say that this is right or not, but this is my--- kind of the way I've experienced it and internalized it. And there's an aspect of kind of curiosity and asking questions. Like most--- most Jewish lessons revolve around kind of asking a question of, well, why. And so I think that's, you know, something I--- I appreciate about it. And there's also this aspect of--- of Israel, not the country, but the concept of it means struggle with God. And that it's not--- it's not--- you know, Christi--- Christianity is very much a--- kind of a--- a lord and servant model. And Judaism isn't that. It's very much--- the fact that Israel means struggle with God, I think it says a lot about what Judaism really means. And it's that it's--- this isn't supposed to be easy, this is supposed to be kind of your life. And there's another aspect of Judaism, to me, that is very much kind of God is in small moments. God is in--- in--- kind of manifests in everyday life, like the concept of mitzvahs, of doing small acts of kindness and good. Like, I think--- so to me, that's really what--- what Judaism--- Judaism is. And then there's one other kind of broader thing that I--- that resonates for me. That is--- you know, Judaism isn't any one of those things. It's very much a family type thing. So like, in the Torah, there's--- you know, there's references to basically, the children of Israel, and again, not the nation-state, the--- the concept of the Jewish nation. And--- and the reality is, is that, like, we're all--- we are all descendants, to a large extent, of one family tree, which is kind of unique. And I mean, it's interesting interacting with people in--- in life, work, personal. And Jewish people will kind of seek each other out. I mean, there's only--- what are there, 15 million of us in the world? And so like, we--- and I didn't experience this--- you asked about in kind of grade school, in high school, I did not experience it at all, because it wasn't--- for me, it wasn't part of my life experience at the time, but as an adult, it has very much been a part of it. I've got a handful of Jewish friends, you know, colleagues that like, you know, will--- will exchange--- will exchange, kind of, you know, congratulations and thanks around certain holidays and things like that. Which is kind of cool.
Cole: Yeah. Do you--- do you consider your children, me and Lara, to be Jewish?
Gabe: Yeah. I mean, from the perspective of aspects of what I just talked about. I think--- I think a big part of it is I think religion in general is--- and actually, identity in general, obviously, is--- I mean--- its--- identity is a very personal thing. And so, I don't know how you all--- how the two of you would really identify. And we--- I talked about regret a bit, you know, earlier in our conversation, and I very much wish I had imparted more of--- of each of those kind of three things. There's a reason I make matzo ball soup, you know? There's a reason I make brisket. And it has to do with, you know, the--- kind of the--- both the--- the ethnic aspect of this is kind of--- this is where where we came from, and--- and the cultural aspect of it--- and this is kind of--- this is who we are. And then the religious aspects you never really got. I don't know. So I don't know what you would identify as. I think of you as--- as Jews, if you look at that as a--- as a really broad category.
Cole: Yeah. Yeah. You talked about how at work, now that being Jewish is a little bit more of your--- your active life, you--- you've connected with other Jewish people in some ways, and you've maybe sought them out, or they've sought out you to some extent. But there's a flip side of that, and that's anti-Semitism. Have you experienced anti-Semitism at work, or in your life as a whole, at school as a--- as a kid, or other places throughout your life?
Gabe: Yeah. I mean, my first--- my first real job working as a--- I'm 15 years old, working as a dishwasher, getting paid cash, because it wasn't legal for me to work. And--- and I've told you this story, I think, before. Peter and Nick, these two older Greek guys, and--- when--- when Nick would have a few drinks at the end of the night, occasionally he would--- he would call me dirty Jew, things like that. And then, as more of a--- as an adult, and working professional, I've actually had a handful of--- less than a handful. It's not a ton, but there's at least three where it was very explicit. And where there was references to--- to kind of what Jews are. And--- and--- and also--- the three that I'm thinking of specifically, and there have been some other comments, but not nearly as personal. These were--- these were kind of close colleagues, and I would say friends, and all three of them were really embarrassed and I was like, just so you know, like, I'm not going to take offense, but I'm--- I'm Jewish. And it was--- you know, it was around, you know how Jews are, with some sort of negative connotation. Cheap, or, you know, some aspect of that. So yeah, it's a pretty--- I don't know that I would say that it shapes me, but it definitely--- like, there's anti-Semitism, and I've experienced it, yeah.
Cole: After those--- those comments that were made, you--- did you take offense? Did it drive you a little bit farther away from these people, or no?
Gabe: No? I mean, it's just--- no, I--- I think there is the way they intended it, and then there's the way I take it, and then there's kind of feedback. I think, if anything, I think they'll--- they're--- they're probably more ashamed. And I think that's--- I think that's actually--- it's worth having had them say it, and then realize, well, that's a--- that's a pretty racist thing to have said. And it's--- it's even more meaningful for them to--- to have thought it and to think that that was okay to say. So, no, I mean, none of them--- so, all of them I worked with really closely. And--- and--- and so, I mean, to the point where like, you know, I sat next to one guy, the other guy, you know, we--- we--- we traveled together extensively. The other one, you know, we--- we were on a few projects together, kind of right in a row. And--- and so none of them did I stopped interacting with because of that, and I'm still--- I still talk to--- to--- with all of them. So I think it was worth--- I think it was worth having them having--- having said that, and done that, and then having me--- me having the opportunity to--- to basically kind of call it out and make sure that they understood that they probably shouldn't say that to me. And with the intent of like, I mean, you guys know me, like, am I that? Really? Am I really a dirty Jew?
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: So, I mean, call me--- call me something else, but because of--- because of my ethnicity, my culture, and my religion, like what--- like, those things are kind of separate. So I think it was worth it, actually.
Cole: Outside of those instances, which were kind of comments, did you ever experience discrimination or more structural forces? Because you were Jewish?
Gabe: No, I mean, and--- and, you know, this is coming from the--- you know, the perspective and the vantage of--- the vantage point of, you know, I'm--- I'm a pretty--- pretty fortunate person in the world, you know, white male living in the United States. So I've got a whole bunch of kind of structural advantages. And so no, I haven't experienced anything--- anything, because of a Jewish identity.
Cole: Yeah, let's talk about you calling yourself white. Is there any contradiction in being white and Jewish for you? Or are they totally different aspects of--- of who you are?
Gabe: Um, I mean, I think of--- I think a lot of--- this is--- this is really uneducated, but I think a lot of whiteness is people's perception of you, not necessarily what you identify as. And so, like, you know [unintelligible]--- the reason--- the reason I was a target when I--- freshman year of high school was because I was a big white kid. And to some extent, setting a tone. It was almost always up--- upperclassman that initiated. It was, we're gonna make sure that that all the other kids understand that whatever. So, so no, like, I don't--- you know. I don't think that there's any contradiction in those. I think my comment about it has more to do with the--- the privileged position I'm in, in our society today, inadvertently and unintentionally, but the reality of it. And--- and for me, I think for a lot of people, I think their Jewish--- their Jewish identity ends up creating challenges. Because they're not perceived as--- as being in that position of--- of being white, because it's not as forward. You know what I mean? So no. For me, you know, I don't see a conflict.
Cole: Yeah, yeah. So let's--- in the last couple of minutes, we can move on to the more abstract questions that I sent you.
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: I'll just read the first one of these. So Jews are historically overrepresented in certain fields and among high-achieving individuals. For example, as of 2010, Jews made up 27% of Nobel physics laureates, 21%, of Ivy League student bodies, and 37% of Oscar winning directors, despite what you said about Jews being a relatively small percentage of the world's population, and a small percentage of the United States population as well. Why do you think that this is?
Gabe: I mean, I have no idea. The one thing I think I would--- like--- actually, there's a couple things I think I would call out. Judaism is--- is based on curiosity, and of questioning, I think. And--- and I think that there is--- you know, there is some aspect of the--- and it's not just the--- the questioning, it's the responsibility to question. I mean, the whole coming-of-age aspect of a bar mitzvah, of being mitzvah'ed is--- is you--- you have this responsibility now to ask these questions, to kind of carry this forward and to seek out knowledge. And I think that that--- I think that--- that can be a really powerful thing. I don't think it's inherent to a Jewish person. I think when you look at kind of the concepts around resilience and, like even, I want you to try food ten times, like stuff like that, like there's an aspect of being intentional about that. Or the concepts around grit. I think those have proven to have some--- some implications and benefits that far outweigh the immediate benefit. And I think Judaism has some of those benefits built in, in the way it's taught, the way it's participated in. And so that--- that's one thought about kind of why that is, is--- is--- is people are asked to think a little differently than traditional mindsets. I don't know. That's again, crazy uneducated and--- and just my thoughts about it.
Cole: Yeah, well, that's--- that's what I'm looking for.
Gabe: Yeah.
Cole: Would you consider yourself successful? I mean, if you had to say, am I successful or am I not successful, what would you say?
Gabe: I think it depends on how you're--- how you're measuring success. And I think that's a really subjective thing. I think I'm a good dad. So that, to me, is a big measure of success. I think in terms of, kind of personal life, like, there's aspects where no, like, I think I'm--- I don't know that I'm as successful as I would like to be, um, you know, relationships and things like that. In terms of kind of work life, yeah, relatively. I'm--- I'm proud of--- I'm proud of the work I get to do. And I'm--- I feel very fortunate. I think that is because I've been successful. And I think it's because I've--- I've learned some--- some--- across all of those things, I think I've--- along the way, I've learned some--- some meaningful lessons. And I think the outcome is, yeah, I would--- I would say I'm successful.
Cole: Yeah, yeah. Success in--- in areas that are more economic, in particular, over the past most of a century, have led to claims that Jews are sort of model minority. I mean, things as simple as there are--- Jews are overrepresented in the middle cl--- the middle class compared to lower classes. And usually, model minority is--- is a term that's used to compare Jews with other groups that are numerical minorities of the United States, like Black Americans, that are underrepresented in some of the same areas. Do you think of Jews as a model minority? Why or why not?
Gabe: I don't know. I mean, I feel like even--- even a concept ends up--- even a concept is an attempt to kind of categorize and separate. And you look at some of the other minorities in our country, and, I mean, the structural disadvantages that Jew have, in our country, at least, haven't necessarily experienced. That said, though, I mean, there's a reason why there are Jewish country clubs, which is a weird way to think about it, maybe, but, like it's because there is an exclusion from--- from aspects of society that--- so, I would suggest that despite some of the--- kind of the anti-Semitism, the ability to kind of persevere, and--- and a lot of that has to do with some of those things we just talked about in terms of, like, why are people successful? Or why are Jewish people successful? Or why are more people who are Jewish achieve different levels of success? I don't know. I don't know--- I don't know that I have a real answer to what you just asked. I think--- I think Jewish people have, if you look back from the time of Abraham, in essence, or really, the last 700, 800 years, there have been some pretty--- some pretty focused efforts on--- and kind of on--- on structurally disadvantaging Jewish people, or eliminating Jewish people. So I don't know. Model--- model minority is very much a modern thing. Right? When did the concept come about? Was it--- was it like the 70s? 60s, 70s?
Cole: Yep, 60s and 70s, mostly?
Gabe: I feel like, to some extent, even--- you know, the categorization, then, has to do with how can we explain--- how can we explain things? How can we explain why some can in some can't. And--- and when you look at some of the structural disadvantages that African Americans have, like Jewish people, just in general, don't have the same types. There are a lot of parallels, but it's not, it's not quite the same. Then again, I think Jewish people have had a couple of thousand years to try to overcome some of those systemic things that were put in place, whereas African Americans in our society have had a hundred and fifty.
Cole: Yeah, yeah. Let's talk about at least one of those structural problems that Jews have had to overcome, which was in the 1920s, in response to soaring Jewish enrollments at prestigious colleges in the Northeast, many of them instituted enrollment quotas that were highly effective at keeping most Jews out of their student bodies. How do you feel about this sort of thing?
Gabe: I mean, I think--- so part of it is, you know, from a personal perspective, does it feel right, does it feel okay, and I would say, no. Another aspect is, when you look at the resiliency of--- of Jewish people. Of the Jewish people. Jews just went elsewhere. I mean, and it didn't necessarily impede the ability to succeed, obviously. So part of me is like, alright. I mean, kind of that, the old adage about, you know, every Jewish holiday is--- is they came, they tried to kill us, let's eat. That--- that to me is--- and I don't think that this should apply to other things in our society. But I think that that's indicative, to me, of the way that Jewish people have responded to it. They came, they tried to kill us. Let's eat!
Cole: Yeah. So for--- for wrapping up here, just the last question that I have is about a group that commentators and sociologists have claimed is a little bit closer to--- to Jewish Americans than, say, Black Americans. So since the 1960s, these commentators in newspapers and magazines and sociologists in academia, have claimed that Asian Americans are another example of a model minority. For example, today, Asian Americans are overrepresented in medicine, where 17% of all active physicians identify as Asian, and an Ivy League student bodies, similarly to--- to Jewish people. Do you think that Asian American over-representation is related to Jewish over-representation? Do you think that it comes from a similar--- similar cause, like you were talking about the possible causes of Jewish over-representation?
Gabe: Yeah, I mean, so, I--- I think that when you look at--- at Asian cultures, in general, there is--- there is a very distinct difference than Western cultures. Eastern culture and Western culture just more generically. And I think that--- I think that there's an expectation of kind of the we versus the me that Eastern cultures have. And that--- and that your success represents your family's success. And--- so, I mean, I think there's different reasons behind it. But I think that the--- I mean, the reality of Asian Americans as a model minority, the concepts there, and some of that--- kind of the outcome, I think is similar. But different reasons behind it, maybe? Another, kind of, you know, thought that comes to mind though, is there--- which is--- for Asian Americans as well, you think about internment camps in World War Two, and you think about, you know, some of the--- the--- the immigration models and the treatment of Chinese Americans, for instance, in, you know, the turn of the century. That said, I think that there is--- there is a societal--- an embedded societal hatred of other minorities that outweighs the distrust of Jews or Asian Americans, potentially. It's--- I think it's a little bit more systemic of a problem. And I think that Jewish Americans and--- and Asian Americans have had the mechanisms to kind of alright, I guess we'll do it another way. Whereas some other groups don't have those options. The reason--- they don't have another--- another way around some of those impediments that--- that--- that Jews and Asians have been able to kind of work through and around.
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: Is a thought.
Gabe: You have to tell me if I pass the test later.
Cole: There's no right or wrong answer for---
Gabe: I know--- I--- I know. I know. I know. I know.
Cole: That's the end of my questions for you. Do you have anything that you've thought of through all of this that you think is important to talk about, or say? Or maybe that comes to your mind that might be interesting?
Gabe: No, but--- I mean I--- I would love to--- I'd love to hear your--- your--- your version of--- kind of your answers, your thought process. I mean, you've asked some interesting questions, and you definitely went areas that I wasn't expecting you to. And I'm wondering some of the why behind it. I mean, this wasn't really just about Jewish identity.
Cole: Yeah.
Gabe: It was about identity. So I'm intrigued--- I'm intrigued by how you got to these questions and this approach. I'm intrigued by potentially hearing your answers to some of these things. And also, you as interviewer, but also as--- as my son, like, what is your take on that the things that you asked, and the way I answered. So those are--- but those aren't necessarily short things and there's not a--- the answer's 42, right?
Cole: Yeah, yeah, not exactly. Well, I'm gonna stop the recording.